. GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYBODY.
WELCOME TO THE JANUARY 27TH 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENTS SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESENT RANDLEMAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR PRESENT MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER
PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL PRESENT SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WONG WONG
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT THANK YOU
MADAM CLERK. >> THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE ROMITA COLONIAL WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE
INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAMAKRISHNA ALONE WE HAVE NEVER
CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW
MATERIAL IN A COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN
RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES. >> COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE?
>> I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA AND ONE NATION UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH ON BEHALF
OF THE BOARD I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F.
GOV TV TODAY THAT IS ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA.
THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE THE
TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE.
>> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY COMMUNICATIONS?
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO BE PRESENT INTO IT HERE IN THE
CHAMBER TODAY. WE ARE IN ROOM 250 ON THE
SECOND FLOOR OF CITY HALL FOR OTHERS WHO WOULD LIKE TO JOIN
US. WHEN YOU ARE NOT ABLE TO BE
HERE THE PROCEEDING IS BEING AIRED LIVE ON S.F. GOV.
TV'S CHANNEL 26 OR YOU MAY VIEW THE LIVESTREAM AT WW W DOT S.F.
V TV.ORG. IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT
PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING YOU CAN EITHER SEND AN EMAIL TO
BOSSERT AS HAVE GOV.ORG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE.
JUST ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLETON
CAPITAL B AS THE INITIAL GOOD LIT PLACE CITY HALL ROOM TWO
FOR FOUR SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102.
IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A
FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITY ACT
OR IF YOU NEED TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE CONTACT THE
CLERK'S OFFICE TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING
(415) 554-5184. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO THE APPROVAL OF OUR
MEETING MINUTES. >> YES.
APPROVAL OF THE DECEMBER 16TH, 2025 BOARD MEETING MINUTES.
COLLEAGUES, COULD I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES
AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHERYL SECONDED BY CHAN.
>> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN OH MAN ADELMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR I
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SORTER SADR EITHER ARE LEBANESE
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC
COMMENT AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL OUR CONSENT
AGENDA ITEMS ONE AND TWO ITEMS ONE AND TWO ARE ON CONSENT.
THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE ROUTINE.
IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED
SEPARATELY. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEMS ONE AND TWO SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN
CHAN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR I
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR I HAVE HERE SUPERVISOR FOR SADR SADR I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR REGULAR
AGENDA NEW BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER THREE ITEM THREE
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY 9
BILLION OF PROCEEDS FROM THE SALE OF REVENUE BONDS OR
COMMERCIAL PAPER FOR CAPITAL IMPROVEMENT PROJECTS TO THE
AIRPORT COMMISSION FOR FISCAL YEAR 2025 AND 2026 AND TO PLACE
APPROXIMATELY 9 BILLION ON CONTROLLERS RESERVE PENDING
RECEIPT OF PROCEEDS OF INDEBTEDNESS.
>> COLLEAGUES, I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEMS
FOUR THROUGH SEVEN TOGETHER ITEMS FOUR THROUGH SEVEN
AND THESE ITEMS PERTAIN TO A GENERAL OBLIGATION BOND
AND CAPITAL EXPENDITURE PLAN. ITEM FOUR IS THE ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE BY CHANGING THE REPORTING
REQUIREMENT FOR CAPITAL EXPENDITURE PLANS FROM IDEAS TO
EVEN YEARS WITH THE NEXT REPORT DUE MARCH 1ST, 2028 ITEM FIVE
THIS RESOLUTION AMENDS THE CITY'S TEN YEAR CAPITAL
EXPENDITURE PLAN FOR FISCAL YEARS 2026 THROUGH 2035 TO
AMEND THE PROPOSED TO GOVERNMENT OBLIGATION BOND
PROGRAM AND CONSOLIDATE FUNDING FOR TRANSPORTATION PROJECTS FOR
ITEM SIX AND SEVEN PURSUANT TO CALIFORNIA GOVERNMENT CODE
SECTION 43607 AND 43608. THE VOTE THRESHOLD IS TWO
THIRDS OR EIGHT VOTES OF ALL MEMBERS OF THE BOARD TO APPROVE
PASSAGE OF THESE TWO ITEMS. ITEM SIX THIS RESOLUTION
DETERMINES AND DECLARES THAT THE PUBLIC INTEREST
AND NECESSITY DEMAND THE CONSTRUCTION ACQUISITION
IMPROVEMENT REHABILITATION EXPANSION, RENOVATION
AND SEISMIC RETROFITTING OF THE EMERGENCY FIREFIGHTING WATER
SYSTEM, THEIR FIREFIGHTING FACILITIES AND INFRASTRUCTURE
POLICE FACILITIES AND INFRASTRUCTURE
TRANSPORTATION FACILITIES FOR THE MUNICIPAL RAILWAY BUS
STORAGE AND MAINTENANCE FACILITY AT PATROL YARD
AND OTHER PUBLIC SAFETY FACILITIES AND INFRASTRUCTURE
FOR EARTHQUAKE AND PUBLIC SAFETY AND RELATED COSTS
NECESSARY OR CONVENIENT FOR THE FOREGOING PURPOSES COLLECTIVELY
KNOWN AS THE ESSER ICR FACILITIES TO AUTHORIZE
LANDLORDS TO PASS THROUGH 50% OF THE RESULTING PROPERTY TAX
INCREASE OF ANY TO RESIDENTIAL TENANTS AND TO MAKE A FINDING
THAT THE ESTIMATED COST OF 535 MILLION IS AND WILL BE TOO
GREAT TO BE PAID OUT OF THE ORDINARY ANNUAL INCOME
AND REVENUE OF THE CITY AND AMONG OTHER FINDINGS
AND ITEM SEVEN THIS ORDINANCE CALLS AND PROVIDES FOR A
SPECIAL ELECTION TO BE HELD ON TUESDAY, JUNE 2ND, 2026 TO
SUBMIT TO THE SAN FRANCISCO VOTERS A PROPOSITION TO INCUR
UP TO 535 MILLION IN BOND DEBT TO FINANCE THE ASR FACILITIES
AND TO ADDITIONALLY TO CONSOLIDATE THE SPECIAL
ELECTION WITH THE GENERAL ELECTION TO ESTABLISH THE
ELECTION PRECINCTS, THE VOTING PLACES AND OFFICERS FOR THE
ELECTION TO WAIVE THE WORD LIMITATION ON BALLOT
PROPOSITIONS IMPOSED BY THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS CODE
SECTION 510 TO COMPLY WITH THE RESTRICTIONS ON THE USE OF BOND
PROCEEDS AS SPECIFIED IN SECTION 53410 OF THE
GOVERNMENT CODE TO INCORPORATE THE PROVISIONS OF THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE SECTIONS 5.30 THROUGH 5.36 AND TO WAIVE
THE TIME REQUIREMENTS SPECIFIED IN SECTION 2.34 OF THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE SUPERVISOR WONG OKAY.
I'M PROUD TO SUPPORT THESE ITEMS BECAUSE TOGETHER THEY
REFLECT RESPONSIVE PLANNING AND A REAL COMMITMENT TO PUBLIC
SAFETY ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO INCLUDING NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE
THE SUNSET DISTRICT UPDATING THE CITY'S LONG TERM CAPITAL
PLAN MATTERS. THIS IS HOW WE MAKE SURE MAJOR
INFRASTRUCTURE INVESTMENTS ARE ACTUALLY PLANNED, FUNDED
AND DELIVERED FOR THE SIDE. THAT'S ESPECIALLY IMPORTANT
BECAUSE PUBLIC SAFETY FACILITIES IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD
HAVE OFTEN BEEN DELAYED OR TREATED AS LOWER PRIORITY FOR
THE SUNSET DISTRICT. EARTHQUAKE PREPAREDNESS IS
ABOUT WHETHER EMERGENCY SERVICES CAN REACH OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS QUICKLY AND SAFELY WHEN IT MATTERS MOST
. MANY WEST SIDE FACILITIES
INCLUDING OUR FIRE STATIONS AND THE TERRIBLE POLICE STATION
AND OUR EMERGENCY WATER FIREFIGHTING FWC ARE ALL SORRY
AND ARE EMERGENCY WATER SYSTEMS ARE OLDER AND MORE VULNERABLE
AND MAJOR QUAKE IF THOSE SYSTEMS FAIL RESPONSE TIMES
SUFFER AND RESIDENTS ARE PUT AT RISK.
THIS BOND IS AN IMPORTANT STEP TOWARD MAKING SURE THE SUNSET
IS NOT AN AFTERTHOUGHT. IT RECOGNIZES THAT PREPAREDNESS
HAS TO BE CITYWIDE AND THAT WEST SIDE COMMUNITIES DESERVE
THE SAME LEVEL OF INVESTMENTS AND PUBLIC SAFETY
INFRASTRUCTURE AS ANYWHERE ELSE IN SAN FRANCISCO, THE EMERGENCY
FIREFIGHTING WATER SYSTEM IS ESPECIALLY CRITICAL FOR THE
WEST SIDE AFTER A MAJOR EARTHQUAKE, ACCESS TO WATER CAN
DETERMINE WHETHER FIRES ARE CONTAINED OR BECOME
CATASTROPHIC. THIS REFLECTS THOUGHTFUL
PLANNING AND A CLEAR WILLINGNESS TO ACT BEFORE
DISASTER STRIKES RATHER THAN REACTING AFTER THE FACT.
MOST IMPORTANTLY, IT PLACES THE DECISION WHERE IT BELONGS WITH
RESIDENTS. I URGE MY COLLEAGUES SUPPORT.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG.
AND WITH THAT I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE,
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING AND THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW BUSINESS.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER EIGHT ITEM EIGHT THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO EXPAND
THE DEFINITION OF TAX EXEMPT ENTITIES FOR USE FEES TO UPDATE
THE PROCESS FOR A NOTIFICATION GUIDELINES CONCERNING FILM
PRODUCTION ACTIVITIES THAT MAY CAUSE PARKING OR TRAFFIC
OBSTRUCTIONS TO UPDATE DEFINITIONS FOR THE FILM REBATE
PROGRAM TO UPDATE THE FILM REBATE AMOUNTS AND TO AUTHORIZE
THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR TO ENTER INTO LICENSING AGREEMENTS FOR
THE USE OF THE FILM SRF LOGO AND OTHER FILM COMMISSION
TRADEMARKS ON MERCHANDISE AND WITH CONGRATULATIONS THE
FILM FANS IN THE AUDIENCE. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEMS NINE AND TEN TOGETHER ITEMS NINE AND 10 OR 2
RESOLUTIONS THAT RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE GIFTS FOR THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH. ITEM NINE AUTHORIZES THE
ACCEPTANCE AND EXPENDITURE OF A $77,000 MONETARY GIFT ENTITLED
2024 EPIC FOR A FEDERALLY QUALIFIED HEALTH CENTERS FROM
THE EPIC SYSTEM CORPORATION TO HELP SUPPORT FEDERALLY
QUALIFIED HEALTH CENTERS AND THEIR UNDERSERVED PATIENT
POPULATIONS JULY 1ST, 2024 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2025 AND ITEM
TEN AUTHORIZES THE ACCEPTANCE AND EXPENDITURE OF AN IN-KIND
GIFT OF COVID 19 TEST KITS IN THE TOTAL AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 528,000 FOR FISCAL YEAR 2024 THROUGH 25
FROM THE ADMINISTRATION FOR STRATEGIC PREPAREDNESS S AND
RESPONSE THROUGH THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
IN SUPPORT OF THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH CLINIC PATIENTS
AND STAFF AND I BELIEVE THAT WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM THE SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEMS 11 AND 12 TOGETHER. >> ITEMS 11 AND 12 ARE TO
RESOLUTIONS THAT AUTHORIZE GRANTS FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC HEALTH. ITEM 11 RETROACTIVELY
AUTHORIZES TO SUBMIT AN APPLICATION TO CONTINUE TO
RECEIVE FUNDING FOR THE RYAN WHITE ACT HIV AIDS EMERGENCY
RELIEF GRANT PROGRAM A GRANT FROM THE HEALTH RESOURCES
SERVICES ADMINISTRATION AND TO REQUEST APPROXIMATELY 15.5
MILLION IN HIV EMERGENCY RELIEF PROGRAM FUNDING FOR THE SAN
FRANCISCO GO ELIGIBLE METROPOLITAN AREA MARCH 1ST,
2020 SIXTH THROUGH FEBRUARY 28TH 2027 AND ITEM 12
RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A GRANT
INCREASE FROM THE NATIONAL INSTITUTES OF HEALTH THROUGH
THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN FRANCISCO TO
PARTICIPATE IN A PROGRAM ENTITLED SHORT TRAININGS ON
METHODS FOR RECRUITING SAMPLING AND COUNTING HARD TO REACH
POPULATIONS. THE H TWO HOUR TRAINING PROGRAM
IN THE AMOUNT OF $24,000 APPROXIMATELY FOR A TOTAL
AMOUNT OF 102,000 JUNE 1ST 2020 5TH OCTOBER FOR AN ADDITIONAL
FOR AN ADDITION FROM JUNE 1ST 2025 FOR A TOTAL TERM OF
OCTOBER FIRST 2022 THROUGH MAY 31ST, 2026 AND WE CAN TAKE
THESE SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER 13 ITEM 13 RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE RECREATION
AND PARK DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND CASH AND IN-KIND
GRANTS FROM THE TRUST FOR PUBLIC LAND AND THE THEODORE
AND FRANCES GIBLE PHILANTHROPIC FUND OF THE JEWISH FEDERATION
BAY AREA VALUED AT APPROXIMATELY 1.62 MILLION FOR
THE DESIGN INSTALLATION REPAIR AND CONSTRUCTION OF
IMPROVEMENTS TO COMMERCIAL AND PARK TO APPROVE THE
ASSOCIATED GRANT AGREEMENT. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAME CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 14 AND 15 TOGETHER ITEMS 14
AND 15 OR 2 RESOLUTIONS PERTAINING TO THE ENHANCED
INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING DISTRICTS ALSO KNOWN AS THE EIA
FEES. >> ITEM 14 APPROVES THE
INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING PLAN FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO D
DISTRICT. NUMBER TWO FOR STONES TOWN
AND ITEM 15 APPROVES THE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING PLAN
FOR THE FIVE D DISTRICT NUMBER THREE AND TO INCLUDE THE
DIVISION OF TAXES SET FORTH THEREIN AND FOR ACQUISITION
AND FINANCING AGREEMENT AND DOCUMENTS AND ACTIONS
RELATED THERETO AS DEFINED HEREIN AND TO AUTHORIZE THE
FILING OF A JUDICIAL VALIDATION ACTION FOR BOTH ITEMS.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT SO THIS IS THE
INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING DISTRICT FOR STONE'S TOWN.
I WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUES IN THE IFP COMMITTEE
SUPERVISORS AT CHAN AND WALTON FOR THEIR WORK.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS THE CHAIR OF THE
BUDGET COMMITTEE TAM FOR HER REMARKS AT THE BUDGET COMMITTEE
ON THIS ITEM AND I AGREE THAT IT GENERALLY TAKES US TOO LONG
TO GET TO THE COMMUNITY BENEFITS THAT COME WITH THESE
LARGE PROJECTS FOR THE COMMUNITY.
NEVERTHELESS, SEEING THAT THE BALBOA RESERVOIR TOOK ALMOST 40
YEARS TO GET THERE GOES DOWN REALLY WAS A FRACTION OF THAT.
BUT IT IS TOO LONG TO GET TO THE SENIOR HOUSING AND THE OPEN
SPACE AND THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING THAT THIS PROJECT WILL
DELIVER. BUT I AM REALLY GLAD THAT WE'RE
HERE AND WE ALSO HAVE THIS NEW TOOL THE ENHANCED
INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING DISTRICT THAT WE CAN USE TO
THAT EFFECT. SO WITH THAT I JUST ALL AROUND
THANK YOU TO EVERYONE FOR THE COLLABORATION AND PARTICULARLY
THANK YOU TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE IN WOODY FOR THEIR HARD WORK
IN MAKING THIS HAPPEN. >> THANK YOU AND I ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT. >> CONGRATULATIONS.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR I THINK THAT WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 16 ITEM 16 RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE
OFFICE OF THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A $420,000
GRANT FROM THE CALIFORNIA OFFICE OF TRAFFIC SAFETY.
OCTOBER 1ST, 2025 THROUGH SEPTEMBER 30TH, 2026.
>> TO SUPPORT THE ALCOHOL AND DRUG IMPAIRED DRIVER
VERTICAL PROSECUTION PROGRAM ACTIVITIES AND SERVICES
AND SAME HOUSE SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
17 THROUGH 19 TOGETHER. >> ITEM 17 THROUGH 19 OUR THREE
ORDINANCES THAT AUTHORIZE THE SETTLEMENTS OF LAWSUITS FILED
AGAINST THE CITY. ITEM 17 IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AUTHORIZE SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY STEPHANIE YORK
JAMES EDWARD BROWN AND KAYLA BREYERS AGAINST THE CITY FOR 6
MILLION. THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES ALLEGED
PERSONAL INJURY AND WRONGFUL DEATH CAUSED BY A CITY TREE.
ITEM 18 AUTHORIZES SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY GENERAL
MOTORS COMPANY FOR APPROXIMATELY 71.1 MILLION.
THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES A CLAIM FOR REFUND OF GROSS RECEIPTS
TAXES, HOMELESSNESS, GROSS RECEIPTS, TAXES OVERPAID
EXECUTIVE GROSS RECEIPTS, TAXES PENALTIES AND INTEREST.
OTHER MATERIAL TERMS OF THE SETTLEMENT RELATE TO GENERAL
MOTORS COMPANY FILING POSITION WITH RESPECT TO CITY TAXES.
AND ITEM 19 AUTHORIZES THE SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED
BY MICROSOFT CORPORATION AND SUBSIDIARIES AGAINST THE
CITY. THE LAWSUITS INVOLVE A REFUND
OF GROSS RECEIPTS AND HOMELESSNESS GROSS
RECEIPTS, TAXES. OTHER MATERIAL TERMS OF THE
SETTLEMENT RELATE TO MICROSOFT CORPORATION'S FILING POSITION
WITH RESPECT TO CITY TAXES SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE AUDIENCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST
READING. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
20. ITEM 20 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE A MANAGEMENT AGREEMENT WITH THE NONPROFIT OWNERS
ASSOCIATION FOR ADMINISTRATION MANAGEMENT OF THE ESTABLISHED
PROPERTY BASED COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT KNOWN AS THE
OCEAN AVENUE COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT SUPERVISOR ONE.
>> I'M GOING TO RECUSE MYSELF FROM THIS VOTE.
I USED TO BE A REPRESENTATIVE ON BOARD AS PART OF MY CITY
COLLEGE ROLE SO I STEP OUTSIDE .
>> CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO EXCUSE RESOLUTION MOVED BY
MELGAR SECONDED BY DORSEY. MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU CALL THE
ROLL ON THE MOTION ON THE MOTION TO EXCUSED SUPERVISOR
WONG FROM ITEM 20. SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I.
SUPERVISOR WALTON WILTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I. SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI GENTLEMEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER EITHER ARE CHINESE
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION PASSES AND ON THE ITEM WE CAN
TAKE THAT SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
21 ITEM 21 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUILDING CODE TO
CREATE A PERMIT AND PERMITTING PROCESS FOR HYDROGEN FUELING
STATION EQUIPMENT INSTALLATION AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET
DETERMINATION SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS PRESIDENT
GENTLEMEN, COLLEAGUES ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE
ORGANIZATIONS OPPOSE THE STATE BILL THAT BROUGHT THIS ITEM TO
OUR AGENDA. THEY'VE BEEN DEEPLY CONCERNED
ABOUT THE RISKS OF HYDROGEN PROJECTS PROLONGING FOSSIL FUEL
INFRASTRUCTURE. 98% OF HYDROGEN FUEL IS MADE
FROM FOSSIL FUELS. ONLY 1% IS MADE USING LOW
CARBON ENERGY NAMELY ELECTROLYSIS OF WATER.
>> BUT THIS PROCESS IS STILL ENERGY INTENSIVE AND DEPENDS ON
ABUNDANT ELECTRICITY AT THE CORE OF THE HYDROGEN HYPE IS
THE FOSSIL FUEL INDUSTRY WHICH HAS LOBBIED EXTENSIVELY FOR THE
PROLIFERATION OF HYDROGEN WHICH IS HIGHLY ENERGY INTENSIVE,
POORLY REGULATED AND BECAUSE OF THE NATURE OF HYDROGEN RISKS
RELEASING NITROGEN OXIDE INTO OUR ATMOSPHERE, NITROGEN OXIDES
ARE 20 TIMES MORE HARMFUL THAN CARBON DIOXIDE AS A GREENHOUSE
GAS AN EXACERBATING RESPIRATORY CONDITIONS IN COMMUNITIES SUCH
AS ASTHMA, HYDROGEN IS A TROJAN HORSE FOR FOSSIL FUEL LOCKED
IN AND FOR THIS REASON I'LL BE VOTING NO THANK YOU MADAM
CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 21 SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG
WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL RIGHT
MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER
SADR I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO NOS WITH SUPERVISORS
CHAN AND FIELDER VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 22 ITEM 22 THIS IS A
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE HUMAN SERVICES AGENCIES ANNUAL
SURVEILLANCE REPORT FOR CALL RECORDING TECHNOLOGY AND WE CAN
WELCOME THESE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 22.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN RIGHT MANDEL MAN EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER EITHER ARE
LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 23 ITEM 20 THREE IS A MOTION TO
REAPPOINT DMITRI TERRY CORNETT TO THE SMALL BUSINESS
COMMISSION TERMS A TERM ENDING JANUARY SIX, 2030 AND WE CAN
TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
MOTION IS APPROVED AND MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR COMMITTEE
REPORTS PLEASE CALL ITEM 26. ITEM 26 WAS CONSIDERED BY THE
RULES COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY, JANUARY
26TH, 2026 AND WAS REFERRED WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION.
ITEM 26 IS A CHARTER AMENDMENT FIRST DRAFT TO AMEND THE
CHARTER OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO TO CHANGE THE
CURRENT TWO TERM LIMITS FOR THE OFFICE OF MAYOR AND THE OFFICE
OF MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FROM CONSECUTIVE
TERM LIMITS TO LIFETIME TERM LIMITS AT AN ELECTION TO BE
HELD JUNE 2ND, 2026 SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU PRESIDENT
AND THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR HEARING THIS ITEM TODAY FOR
THIS BALLOT MEASURE TO BE PROPOSED ON THE JUNE BALLOT, I
WANTED TO WALK THROUGH A COUPLE OF COMPONENTS OF WHAT THIS
BALLOT MEASURE WILL DO AND WHAT THE INTENTIONS ARE.
>> FIRSTLY, IT REALLY DOES THREE SIMPLE THINGS ONE, IT
CLARIFIES THE INTENT OF A PREVIOUS BALLOT MEASURE WHICH
SET TERM LIMITS ON BOTH SUPERVISOR AND MAYOR IN SAN
FRANCISCO. AND IT SAYS THAT THERE SHOULD
BE LIFETIME TERM LIMITS AND TWO TERMS FOR SUPERVISOR AND FOR
MAYOR. >> AND EFFECTIVELY THREE CLOSES
THE LOOPHOLE WHICH ALLOWS POLITICIANS TO RUN FOR OFFICE
AGAIN FOR THOSE RESPECTIVE POSITIONS AFTER THEY HAVE TAKEN
A BYE. >> WE'RE CARRYING THIS BECAUSE
THIS IS REALLY ABOUT THE INTENTION OF ALLOWING AN
OPPORTUNITY FOR THE NEXT GENERATION OF LEADERSHIP TO
HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO SERVE IN OUR CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. IN THESE POSITIONS WE'VE SEEN
OVER THE LAST YEAR WITH THE GENERATIONAL CHANGE ON THIS
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WHERE WE'VE HAD NEW IDEAS AND NEW
REPRESENTATION LEADING TO RESULTS.
>> AND FOR THE FIRST WE'VE PASSED HISTORIC LEGISLATION
FROM THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN TO MAKE IT MAKING MAJOR PROGRESS
ON PUBLIC SAFETY AS WELL. >> AND THIRD, THIS IS REALLY
ABOUT SENDING A MESSAGE AROUND DEMOCRACY.
DEMOCRACY REQUIRES CHANGE. IT'S WHY IN OUR CONSTITUTION WE
HAVE TERM LIMITS FOR PRESIDENT. IT'S A DEMOCRATIC PRINCIPLE
THAT WE CAN ALL AGREE ON. >> AND THIS IS ABOUT NOW
IN THIS CURRENT PRECARIOUS MOMENT IN OUR NATIONAL CLIMATE
SENDING A MESSAGE TO WASHINGTON THAT WE IN SAN FRANCISCO WILL
HOLD OURSELVES ACCOUNTABLE TO SAY THAT THE POSITIONS THAT WE
ARE IN CHARGE OF WITH THE SUPERVISOR AND MAYOR FOR WHICH
THERE ARE ALREADY TERM LIMITS IN OUR CHARTER WE'RE GOING TO
CLOSE THE LOOPHOLE TO SEND A MESSAGE AMIDST THIS NATIONAL
CLIMATE ABOUT WHAT WE STAND FOR AS A CITY.
>> IN THE RULES COMMITTEE WE DID HEAR SOME COMMENTS FROM
SOME OF MY COLLEAGUES ABOUT THE CONTENTION ABOUT APPLYING TERM
LIMITS TO OTHER POSITIONS. >> AND AS I MENTIONED THERE,
IT'S AN INTERESTING EXERCISE BUT I FEEL IT TACKLES A
DIFFERENT QUESTION THAN WHAT THIS BALLOT MEASURE IS INTENDED
. THIS BALLOT MEASURE IS ABOUT
CLOSING A LOOPHOLE ON THE EXISTING POSITIONS FOR WHICH
THERE ARE ALREADY TERM LIMITS ESTABLISHED.
IT'S AN INTERESTING EXERCISE TO EXPLORE IT FOR OTHER POSITIONS
BUT I FEEL THAT PROPOSITION REQUIRES FURTHER DILIGENCE TO
DETERMINE WHICH OF THOSE POSITIONS IT SHOULD APPLY TO AS
WELL AS WHICH OF THOSE GROUPS NEED TO BE CONSULTED.
THOSE RESPECTIVE POSITIONS MANAGE THOUSANDS OF EMPLOYEES
THAT WE DO NOT AS A MAYOR OR AS SUPERVISORS AND THE RESPECTIVE
ORGANIZATIONS THAT REPRESENT THOSE EMPLOYEES I BELIEVE
SHOULD BE CONSULTED TO DETERMINE WHAT IS THE
APPROPRIATE FRAMEWORK FOR THOSE RESPECTIVE ORDINANCE.
AND I FEEL IF THAT'S A FURTHER BALLOT MEASURE PEOPLE ARE
INTERESTED IN PURSUING. I'M HAPPY TO HAVE THAT
CONVERSATION AT THAT TIME. >> BUT REALLY AGAIN, THE
PURPOSE OF THIS BALLOT MEASURE IS IN THE CONTEXT OF A NATIONAL
CLIMATE THAT WE'RE SEEING AROUND A CONVERSATION ABOUT
TERM LIMITS AND LOOPHOLES. >> THIS IS ABOUT CLOSING A
LOOPHOLE TO PROVIDE AN OPPORTUNITY FOR GENERATIONAL
CHANGE TO CONTINUE IN OUR CITY BUT ALSO SENDING A MESSAGE AT
THIS TIME. >> COLLEAGUES, I HOPE TO HAVE
YOUR SUPPORT. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON, THANK YOU
SO MUCH, CHAIRMAN ALDERMAN. I THINK THE PUBLIC AND EVERYONE
SHOULD KNOW THIS IS REALLY AN EXERCISE IS ON AND POLITICS.
>> THIS IS A PROPOSAL THAT IS REALLY A SOLUTION IN SEARCH OF
A PROBLEM. IF IT'S NOT THE CASE I WOULD
LOVE FOR ALL OF YOU TO LINE UP ALL OF THE FORMER BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS MEMBERS, ALL OF THE FORMER MAYORS THAT HAVE RUN FOR
A TERM AFTER SERVING EIGHT YEARS AND THEN LINE UP ALL OF
THE FORMER SUPERVISORS, ALL THE FORMER MAYORS THAT HAVE RAN FOR
A TERM AFTER SERVING EIGHT YEARS THAT HAVE ACTUALLY WON.
AND THOSE NUMBERS COULD FIT IN A SMALL BROOM CLOSET BECAUSE
THIS IS ACTUALLY NOT AN ISSUE THAT EXISTS HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. WHAT WE DO HAVE THOUGH IS $1
BILLION DEFICIT PROJECTED HERE FOR THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. WE HAVE A $300 MILLION
PROJECTED DEFICIT FOR THE MUNICIPAL TRANSIT AGENCY
AND THIS IS WHAT WE'RE FOCUSING ON.
ELECTIONS COST MONEY. PEOPLE SPEND MONEY IN ELECTIONS
. AND FOCUSING ON WHAT ONE OR 2
OR 3 OR FOUR OR MAYBE FIVE SIX PEOPLE MAY DO IN A CITY OF OVER
800,000 PLUS PEOPLE. TO ME THIS IS JUST LUDICROUS.
BUT I KNOW IT'S ABOUT POLITICS AND IT'S NOT INTENDED TO ALLOW
FOR MORE PEOPLE TO SERVE IN PUBLIC OFFICE.
>> BECAUSE IF THAT WAS THE CASE THEN I WOULD SAY MY COLLEAGUE
ISN'T GOING FAR ENOUGH WITH THIS LATEST LEGISLATION.
>> AND I TRULY FEEL THAT SINCE WE WANT TO ALLOW OPPORTUNITIES
FOR PEOPLE TO SERVE AND MAKE SURE THAT PEOPLE CAN COME ON
BOARD AND SERVE IN POSITIONS THAT PEOPLE SERVE IN FOR 2030
YEARS WITHOUT TERM LIMITS THEN WE SHOULD APPLY THIS TO ALL
ELECTED OFFICIALS HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
OTHERWISE THIS IS NOTHING BUT A POLITICAL PLOY TO STOP PEOPLE
FROM RUNNING FOR OFFICE AGAIN WHEN THIS IS NOT A PROBLEM THAT
EXISTS. >> I HAVE PRESENTED POLICY
BEFORE THAT WAS NOT CONNECTED TO DATA.
AND I WOULD GET CRITICIZED FOR THAT.
THIS POLICY HAS NO DATA CONNECTED WHATSOEVER.
WE HAVE PROBABLY ONE PERSON IN THE HISTORY OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO THAT HAS DECIDED TO RUN FOR
OFFICE AFTER SERVING TWO FOUR YEAR TERMS AND ONE.
WE HAVE PEOPLE WHO HAVE ATTEMPTED AND LOST BUT MOST
CERTAINLY THIS ISSUE IS NOT SOMETHING THAT SHOULD BE GOING
ON THE BALLOT WHERE MILLIONS OF DOLLARS WILL BE SPENT FOR AN
ELECTION. THERE WAS ALSO A STATEMENT
YESTERDAY THAT ONE OF MY COLLEAGUES SPOKE FOR LABOR
AND SAID THAT LABOR DIDN'T SUPPORT OR HAD CONCERNS WITH MY
WITH MY PROPOSED AMENDMENTS. AND YET WE DIDN'T HAVE ONE
PERSON FROM LABOR LINED UP AND SAY THEY HAD A CONCERN WITH
MY AMENDMENTS BECAUSE THAT WAS SOMETHING THAT WAS CREATED OUT
OF THE BLUE. I DO WANT TO ADD THAT MY
AMENDMENTS DO NOT HAMPER ANYONE WHO IS CURRENTLY IN OFFICE.
THIS IS NOT AN ATTACK ON ANYONE CURRENTLY IN OFFICE AND IN FACT
IT ALLOWS ANYONE IN OFFICE CURRENTLY TO FINISH THEIR TERM
AND SERVE AN ADDITIONAL FOUR YEARS BECAUSE MY AMENDMENTS
TRULY ALLOW FOR OPPORTUNITIES FOR MORE YOUNG, FRESH NEW
DIFFERENT PERSPECTIVES TO HAVE THE ABILITY TO SERVE IN ELECTED
OFFICE. SO WE'RE REALLY TRYING TO PUT
SOMETHING ON THE BALLOT THAT ALLOWS PEOPLE TO VOTE ON
ALLOWING MORE PEOPLE TO SERVE IN OFFICE THEN WE SHOULD
INCLUDE EVERY ELECTED OFFICE. SO JUST TO GIVE A LITTLE
PERSPECTIVE, MY AMENDMENTS IMPOSE A LIFETIME TO TERM LIMIT
ON THE OFFICES OF THE ASSESSOR RECORDER CITY ATTORNEY DISTRICT
ATTORNEY, PUBLIC DEFENDER, SHERIFF TREASURER, MEMBERS OF
THE BOARD OF EDUCATION AND MEMBERS OF THE CITY COLLEGE
BOARD OF TRUSTEES. IT PROVIDES PROVISIONS FOR
ANYONE HOLDING THOSE OFFICES AS OF THE JUNE ELECTION OR ELECTED
AT THE JUNE ELECTION AND WHO WOULD OTHERWISE BE TERMED OUT
UNDER THE NEW TERM LIMIT MAY COMPLETE THEIR TERM OF OFFICE.
AND ONE ADDITIONAL FOUR YEAR TERM.
>> THOSE AMENDMENTS ARE REFLECTED IN THE SHORT AND LONG
TITLES AND SECTIONS 6.100 8.108 .121.
THERE ARE ALSO A FEW CLARIFYING AND CONFIRMING AMENDMENTS TO
THOSE SECTIONS TO THE LONG TITLE.
SO I JUST WANT TO REALLY SAY THAT I AM NOT AGAINST TERM
LIMITS. LET ME START THERE.
I BELIEVE IN FRESH DIFFERENT LEADERSHIP OPPORTUNITIES FOR
EVERYBODY TO SERVE. AND I'D BE THE FIRST ONE TO
SUPPORT THIS HAPPENING FOR ALL ELECTED OFFICIALS.
>> IF THE INTENT IS TRULY ABOUT ALLOWING PEOPLE THE OPPORTUNITY
TO SERVE AND I DON'T THINK THAT'S THE CASE I THINK THIS IS
MORE POLITICAL. SO I WANT TO MOVE THAT MY
AMENDMENTS BE ACCEPTED INTO THIS LEGISLATION.
>> I THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALLIN THERE IS A
MOTION ON THE FLOOR SECONDED BY FIELDER SOUP PROVIDER CHEN.
>> THANK YOU PRESENT GENTLEMEN .
>> I ALSO JUST WANT TO SAY THAT I DO BELIEVE IN CREATING MORE
OPPORTUNITIES FOR YOUNG PEOPLE TO SERVE OUR CITY AS A
MILLENNIAL ELECT. AND I WANT WHEN I LOOK AT THIS
MEASURE AND IF OUR GOAL IS TO EMPOWER MORE MILLENNIALS
AND YOUNGER THAN I BELIEVE THAT WE ALSO NEED TO DO A MORE
RESPONSIBLE EVALUATION AND LOOK AT EVERY SINGLE PUBLIC SERVICES
POSITION INCLUDING COMMISSION SEATS AND OTHER ELECTED OFFICES
INSTEAD OF POTENTIAL ONLY GOING TO THE VOTER MULTIPLE TIMES TO
DECIDE ON MULTIPLE BATCHES OF SEATS FOR CONSIDERATION.
I REALLY WOULD PREFER THAT WE DO IT CAREFULLY
AND MEANINGFULLY AND DO IT ALL AT ONCE.
SO FOR THIS REASONS AND I AM VOTING NO TODAY FOR THE CURRENT
VERSION WITHOUT AMENDMENT THANK YOU SUPER AS A MOTHER.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. I DO SUPPORT THIS LEGISLATION
AND IT IS NOT FOR POLITICAL REASONS.
I THINK THAT WE DO HAVE A TERM LIMITS FOR A REASON AND I DO
SEE A DISTINCTION BETWEEN THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE
MAYOR WHICH ARE OFFICES THAT DO NOT REQUIRE ANY SPECIAL
QUALIFICATIONS SINCE IT IS THE BAR IS ACTUALLY NOT THAT HIGH
IN TERMS OF WHO COMES INTO THESE POSITIONS AND IT IS
IN OUR CHARTER MEANT TO DO THAT.
IT IS MEANT TO BE THE PEOPLE'S HOUSE TO ALLOW THE PEOPLE TO
ACCESS THESE OFFICES AND REPRESENT A WIDE ARRAY.
AND BOTH IN TERMS OF GENERATION AND RACE ETHNIC ORIGIN OF OUR
VERY DIVERSE CITY TO BE INTO THESE SEATS.
THAT'S WHY WE IMPLEMENTED TERM LIMITS.
AND SO IT IS TO ME A VERY DIFFERENT ANIMAL THAN AN OFFICE
OF THE CITY ATTORNEY OR A DISTRICT ATTORNEY OR A
TREASURER THAT REQUIRES VERY SPECIALIZED SKILLS IN ORDER TO
DO THAT JOB. AND THEY ALSO DIRECT ENTIRE
DEPARTMENTS TO SUPERVISE STAFF THAT HAVE SPECIALIZED SKILLS
IN THOSE AREAS AS WELL. SO WHEREAS THERE ARE SOME OF US
WHO COULD DO THOSE JOBS AND SHORT YOU KNOW AFTER WE'RE
DONE HERE GO RUN FOR SOMETHING ELSE.
IT IS NOT ANYONE WHO CAN RUN FOR CITY ATTORNEY AND SUPERVISE
OTHER ATTORNEYS. SO THE POOL OF PEOPLE WHO WOULD
RUN FOR THOSE OFFICE IS IS ALREADY MUCH, MUCH SMALLER THAN
THE POOL THAT WOULD RUN FOR OUR JOBS.
I DO THINK THAT THERE IS A VERY BIG DISTINCTION AND I ALSO
THINK THAT YOU KNOW, TO SUPPORT WHAT MY COLLEAGUE MAHMUD HAD
SAID, WE ARE LIVING IN A TIME WHERE OUR DEMOCRACY IS
IN TROUBLE. I DO THINK THAT IT IS OUR
RESPONSIBILITY NOT JUST TO MAKE THESE OFFICES AVAILABLE TO
ACTUALLY MENTOR OUR SUPPORT, HELP THE NEXT GENERATION OF
LEADERS BECAUSE SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS BEEN AT THE
FOREFRONT OF LEADING NATIONAL ELITE PEOPLE WHO HAVE OUR JOBS
AND THEN MOVE ON TO OTHER POSITIONS LIKE SOME OF US ARE
DOING RIGHT NOW RUNNING FOR OTHER POSITIONS HAVE ALWAYS HAD
AN OUTSIZED INFLUENCE IN OUR POLITICAL PROCESS IN THE
NATION. SO THIS IS ABOUT THE PIPELINE
AND I DO SUPPORT MY YOUNGER COLLEAGUES AS THE GEN XERS WHO
WANT TO COME AFTER AND REPRESENT THE HOPES
AND DREAMS OF THEIR GENERATION AND WHEREAS NOT MANY FOLKS HAVE
DONE IT. I THINK THE SAME ARGUMENT COULD
BE WELL IF NOT SO MANY FOLKS HAVE DONE IT, WHY NOT SEND THIS
MESSAGE FOR THE NEXT GENERATION THAT WE WILL HELP YOU AND NOT
USE THE POWER OF NAME RECOGNITION INCUMBENCY TO HELP
FOLKS GET HIGHER OFFICE, REPRESENT THE FULL DIVERSITY OF
OUR CITY IN THESE OFFICES AND ALSO BUILD LEADERSHIP FOR
TOMORROW. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU. JUST FIRST OFF, I DO SUPPORT
THIS LEGISLATION AND I ALSO SUPPORT MY COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR
WALTON'S AMENDMENT ACTUALLY BECAUSE BECAUSE OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S INTERESTING HISTORY WITH A REVOLVING DOOR OF FOLKS
IN CITY GOVERNMENT ALTHOUGH OFFICES SUCH AS ASSESSOR
RECORDER, CITY ATTORNEY DISTRICT ATTORNEY DO HAVE A
HIGH BAR FOR QUALIFICATIONS, MANY OF OUR OF THE FOLKS THAT
HAVE SERVED IN THOSE OFFICES AND MOST RECENT DECADES HAVE
BEEN APPOINTED AND THERE IS A POWER OF INCUMBENCY THAT I
WOULD ARGUE DOES KEEP PEOPLE OUT.
AND SO THAT IS EXACTLY WHY I SUPPORT SUPERVISOR WALTON'S
AMENDMENT AND AND AGREE THAT WE NEED TO DO THIS IN ONE FELL
SWOOP. AND YOU KNOW, BECAUSE OF OUR
CHARTER AND HOW IT'S WRITTEN, THE MAYOR HAS THE POWER TO
APPOINT MANY OF THOSE POSITIONS AND THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT HAS
HAPPENED. AND SO I DON'T UNDERSTAND WHY
WE WOULDN'T TAKE THIS AMENDMENT FORWARD ALONG WITH THE ENTIRE
LEGISLATION REGARDING BOTH THE MAYOR AND THE SUPERVISORS.
>> AND I JUST WANT TO THANK REGGIE WALTON FOR BRINGING THIS
AMENDMENT TO US. >> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR
DORSEY. >> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT
RANDLEMAN. I INTEND TO SUPPORT THE
ORIGINAL CHARTER AMENDMENT AS PROPOSED WHICH I THINK IS
NARROWLY AND APPROPRIATELY TAILORED TO THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS OFFICES WHICH ALREADY HAVE TERM LIMITS
APPLIED FOR CITYWIDE OFFICES WITHOUT TERM LIMITS.
I THINK THAT'S A DIFFERENT DEBATE.
AND AS SOMEONE WHO SPENT 14 YEARS IN THE SAN FRANCISCO CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE, I WOULD ARGUE THAT THE ABSENCE OF TERM
LIMITS FOR THAT OFFICE HAS ENABLED IT TO HAVE CONTINUITY
THAT REALLY HAS MADE IT A MORE FORMIDABLE FORCE FOR CHANGE
THAN IT WOULD HAVE BEEN OTHERWISE.
LOUISE RAINEY SERVED THERE FOR 16 YEARS AND I THINK THE
CONTINUITY THAT SHE BUILT IN THAT OFFICE ENABLED IT TO
PURSUE HIGHLY SUCCESSFUL AND YEARS LONG BATTLES AGAINST
BIG TOBACCO. DENNIS HERRERA SERVED FOR
NEARLY 20 YEARS. THAT CONTINUITY WAS
INSTRUMENTAL IN BEING A FORCE IN A DECADE LONG FIGHT FOR
LGBTQ PLUS MARRIAGE EQUALITY AND THE WORK THAT HE DID TO
TAKE ON THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION 1.0 AND BY
COMPARISON I KNOW DAVID CHIU IS JUST GETTING STARTED BUT I
THINK THE THE OPTION FOR CONTINUITY IN THAT KIND OF
OFFICE HAS LENT A PROFESSIONALISM AND STATURE
THAT ARGUES AGAINST IMPLEMENTING TERM LIMITS HERE.
SO THE THE THE FIGHT THAT HE IS LEADING HE DAVID CHU IS LEADING
AGAINST THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION AND TO ME IS WHY
WE SHOULD BE GRATEFUL THAT WE'VE GOT AN OFFICE THAT HAS
HAD THAT KIND OF PROFESSIONALISM AND CONTINUITY
THAT I DON'T THINK WE WOULD HAVE IF THERE WAS A LOT OF
TURNOVER AT THE TOP. SO I WILL OPPOSE THE AMENDMENT
AND SUPPORT THE UNDERLYING CHARTER AMENDMENT.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT.
>> I PERSONALLY LIKE WAS SAY THIS THAT I THINK THE WAY THE
EXISTING CHARTER AMENDMENT THE EXISTING CHARTER IS JUST FINE
YOU ARE NOT ALLOWED TO SERVE A CONSECUTIVE TWO TERMS AND THEN
YOU HAVE TO TAKE A BREAK AND THEN YOU HAVE TO COME BACK.
YOU COULD COME BACK IF YOU ACTUALLY DO WANT TO COME BACK.
>> AND I ALSO HAVE MET SUPERVISORS THAT DO NOT EVEN
WANT TO RUN FOR A SECOND TERM. SO THE REASON WHY I AM NOT
RUNNING FOR HER SEAT SO THAT I THINK THE TRUTH IS IS THAT
VOTERS SAN FRANCISCANS SHOULD VOTE FOR PEOPLE WHO QUALIFY FOR
THEIR JOB AND THAT ALSO HAD THE VISION THAT THEY COULD ALIGN
WITH THAT IN THE BEST INTERESTS OF SAN FRANCISCO.
SO I DON'T I DON'T SEE A PROBLEM AS IT CURRENTLY EXISTS.
>> BUT CLEARLY THAT IS THE CASE FOR SUPERVISOR MOVE SOMEHOW
AND I WOULD SAY THAT I THEN ALSO CONCUR IF IT SHOULD SHOULD
WE THEN AGREE THAT IT SHOULD BE APPLICABLE FOR A LIFETIME TERM
LIMIT? THEN I CONCUR WITH ROGER WALTON
THEN IT SHOULD BE APPLICABLE THROUGHOUT FOR ALL ELECTEDS
BECAUSE IF AGAIN THE PRINCIPLE IS TO SAY WE SHOULD HAVE MORE
PEOPLE GETTING INVOLVED AND MORE PEOPLE.
AND FRANKLY MORE PEOPLE GETTING INVOLVED AND MORE PEOPLE
RUNNING FOR OFFICE. I ALSO DO NOT SEE THIS PARTY
REALLY, REALLY SAY IN ANY WAY THAT HAS ANY DATA THAT WOULD
ACTUALLY ENCOURAGE YOUNGER PEOPLE TO RUN.
I MEAN AGAIN, LIKE ANYBODY CAN RUN FOR ANY OFFICE AT ANY
MOMENT WHICH IS THE GREAT THINGS ABOUT DEMOCRACY SEE
AND IT SHOULD BEEN SHOWN AND BE AN AGEISM ISSUE EITHER FOR ONLY
ONE YOUNGER PEOPLE TO RUN. I JUST FIND A LOT OF IT IS THAT
WE'RE BOXING OURSELVES AND PUTTING OURSELVES IN THE
CORNER ABOUT WHO SHOULD QUALIFY AND AND AND THAT WE'RE LIMITING
VOTERS THEIR OPTIONS I THINK IS FUNDAMENTALLY WHAT I'M
DISAGREEING WITH IS THE ARGUMENT FOR MAKING A CHANGE IS
SOMEHOW THAT WE NEED TO HAVE A YOUNGER GENERATION WHEN IN FACT
ARE WE JUST LIMITING CHOICES BY OPPOSE BY YOU KNOW, APPLYING A
LIFETIME TERM LIMITS? >> SO I WILL BE VOTING
IN SUPPORT OF SUPERVISOR WALTON'S AMENDMENT SO THAT WE
CAN SAY THIS IS LEVEL THE PLAYING FIELD AND IT'S LIKE
THIS IS THE APPROACH SHOULD IT NOT WORK WE COME BACK
AND ADJUST IT DOWN THE ROLL. BUT IF IT'S NOT ADOPTED THE
AMENDMENT PROPOSED BY SUPERVISOR WALTON THEN I WILL
BE VOTING AGAINST IT BECAUSE I DO NOT SEE THE REASON AS A
VALID REASON FOR LIFETIME TERM LIMITS.
WHEN IN FACT VOTERS SHOULD HAVE JUST AS MANY OPTION AS POSSIBLE
AT ANY GIVEN TIME FOR THE CANDIDATES.
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT MADAM AND I DO WANT
TO JUST CLEAR UP ONE THING FOR SURE BECAUSE MY PROPOSED
AMENDMENTS DO NOT TAKE AWAY THE NEED FOR THE SPECIALIZED
OPTIONS THAT EXIST FOR ANY CERTAIN OFFICE.
NONE OF THOSE QUALIFICATIONS CHANGE WITH THE ADDITION OF MY
AMENDMENTS. I DO WANT TO SAY THOUGH THAT
SPECIAL QUALIFICATIONS FOR POSITIONS DO NOT EQUAL THE
ABILITY TO BE GOOD ADMINISTRATORS.
JUST BECAUSE YOU HAVE A LAW DEGREE OR SOME KIND OF SPECIAL
CERTIFICATION THAT MAKES YOU PHYSICALLY QUALIFIED FOR
POSITIONS. >> BUT WE HAVE OVER 800,000
PEOPLE IN THIS CITY AND SURELY THOSE SPECIALIZED SKILLS EXIST
WITH THAT 800,000 PLUS POOL OF PEOPLE.
>> IT IS VERY LARGE. IN FACT I KNOW FOR A FACT THAT
IN SOME OF OUR CITY DEPARTMENTS CURRENTLY RIGHT NOW THAT
SPECIALIZATION EXISTS AND WE HAVE PEOPLE WHO NEVER GET AN
OPPORTUNITY THAT WORK FOR THESE DEPARTMENTS.
YEAR IN AND YEAR OUT WILL NEVER GET AN OPPORTUNITY TO GROW
AND SERVE IN ANY OF THESE POSITIONS.
>> PEOPLE WHO WE ALL WORK WITH ON A DAILY BASIS THAT HAVE
THOSE QUALIFICATIONS BECAUSE THEIR BOSS IS NOT TERMED OUT.
AND SO IF THIS IS ABOUT ALLOWING OPPORTUNITIES FOR
PEOPLE TO BE ABLE TO SERVE EVEN PEOPLE WITH SPECIALIZED SKILL
SETS SHOULD HAVE THOSE SAME OPPORTUNITIES TO SERVE.
>> THAT IS NOT WHAT THIS LEGISLATION IS ABOUT.
BUT WE DO HAVE TERM LIMITS IN PLACE RIGHT NOW AND WE ALSO
HAVE APPOINTEES THAT GET APPOINTED TO POSITIONS THAT
HAVE ZERO EXPERIENCE IN THEIR OFFICE WHEN THERE IS TURNOVER
AND THEY'RE GIVEN THE OPPORTUNITY TO LEAVE AND GAIN
THAT EXPERIENCE EVEN OVER PEOPLE WHO MAY HAVE BEEN
IN THOSE DEPARTMENTS AND HAVE DONE THOSE JOBS AND FUNCTION AT
A HIGH LEVEL FOR A VERY LONG TIME.
>> SO THAT COMPLETE ABSENCE OF CONTINUITY EXISTS MORE OFTEN
THAN NOT QUITE FRANKLY HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SO LET'S JUST BE HONEST ABOUT WHY WE PROPOSE WHAT WE
PROPOSE. AND THEN WE CAN HAVE A BETTER
CONVERSATION. >> THIS IS A SOLUTION IN SEARCH
OF A PROBLEM. AND WE'RE SITTING HERE HAVING A
DEBATE ON THE FLOOR WHEN WE HAVE REAL ISSUES HERE IN THIS
CITY. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR WONG. I DO SUPPORT THE LEGISLATION AS
IS. I THINK THAT THERE IS A
DISTINCTION BETWEEN THE OFFICE OF THE MAYOR BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AND SOME OF THESE MORE SPECIFIC POSITIONS SUCH AS
ASSESSOR RECORDER, DISTRICT ATTORNEY, CITY ATTORNEY ADDING
ON TOP OF WHAT SUPERVISOR MAGUIRE MENTIONED.
I ALSO THINK IN TERMS OF THE SPECIALIZATION.
I THINK I SEE IS FOR THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE MAYOR WE
HAVE BROAD POLICY MAKING ROLES ON BEHALF OF THE PEOPLE OF SAN
FRANCISCO WHEREAS SOME OF THESE OTHER POSITIONS I SEE THEM AS
MORE DEPARTMENTAL LEADERS THAT ARE SPECIALIZED AND MORE MORE
OF PROFESSIONALS ARE APPOINTED TO LEAD CITY DEPARTMENTS
IN LESS OF A BROAD POLICYMAKING ROLES AND WE BENEFIT FROM
HAVING PEOPLE IN THESE POSITIONS WITH EXPERIENCE
AND HAVE THAT PROFESSIONALISM. >> I DO RECALL THAT IN THE
UNITED STATES IN THE PAST WE WE DID HAVE A FOR THE PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES WE DID HAVE A A MAYBE A FIX THAT WAS NEEDED
IN OUR UNITED STATES CONSTITUTION TO TO ENSURE THAT
OUR PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES WAS THERE FOR ONLY TWO
TERMS BECAUSE THAT WAS THE INTENTION OF THE INTENTION FROM
FROM THE FIRST TIME THAT WAS PUT TO PUT TOGETHER.
AND I SEE THIS AS DOING SOMETHING SIMILAR FOR OUR BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS. AND THAT'S WHY I SUPPORT IT
IN TERMS OF THE TERM LIMITS FOR SOME OF THESE OTHER POSITIONS.
>> I THINK THERE CAN BE OPEN CONVERSATION FOR IT IN THE
FUTURE AS WELL BECAUSE SHOULD THEY HAVE SHOULD THEY HAVE THE
OPPORTUNITY TO RUN AS MANY TERMS AS THEY WANT OR SHOULD BE
TWO TERMS OR MAYBE SHOULD BE FOUR TERMS SINCE THEY'RE NOT
THEIR MORE PROFESSIONAL ROLES OR SHOULD THEY HAVE SOMETHING
THAT IS LONGER THAN THAT? I THINK THAT'S AN OPEN
CONVERSATION AT THIS TIME. I'M SUPPORTING THE LEGISLATION
AS AS IS. I THINK THAT THIS FOCUS IS ON
CLOSING SOMETHING THAT THAT CURRENTLY EXISTS AND SIMILAR TO
THE PRESIDENT UNITED STATES AND THE CHANGES THAT WERE MADE
TO THE UNITED STATES CONSTITUTION.
I THINK THIS IS SIMILAR. >> THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR ALL THE COMMENTS
AND FEEDBACK. JUST WANTED TO CLOSE OFF BY
AGAIN REITERATING WHAT THE INTENTION OF THIS MEASURE IS.
>> THIS IS ABOUT CLOSING A LOOPHOLE FOR TERM LIMITS THAT
ALREADY EXIST AND AS A BODY WE HAVE A RESPONSIBILITY AS
ELECTED OFFICIALS TO SEND A MESSAGE AND A STATEMENT
IN LIGHT OF CERTAIN CIRCUMSTANCES THAT HAPPEN THAT
ARE SALIENT IN OUR TIMES. >> AND I DO BELIEVE WE CAN WALK
IF YOU CAN CHEW GUM AND WALK AT THE SAME TIME.
WE CAN SOLVE THE PROBLEMS THAT ARE ADDRESSING OUR CITY FROM
HOMELESSNESS TO PUBLIC SAFETY TO BUDGET WHILE ALSO ADDRESSING
ISSUES OF GOOD GOVERNANCE AND MAKING STATEMENTS OF GOOD
GOVERNANCE IN TIMES OF NATIONAL CRISIS.
I THINK WE'RE ALL CAPABLE OF DOING BOTH.
>> THIS ISN'T GOING TO ADD ANY MONEY INTO OUR ELECTION
PROCESS. THERE'S ALREADY AN ELECTION
IN JUNE. IT'S SIMPLY GOING ON THE SAME
BALLOT. >> SO AGAIN, THIS IS REALLY
ABOUT CLOSING A LOOPHOLE. AND IF PEOPLE ARE INTERESTED
AND I THINK THERE'S A LOT TO DISCUSS ABOUT OTHER POSITIONS
AND THEIR TERM LIMITS BUT IT'S A SEPARATE QUESTION THAT I HOPE
COLLEAGUES WE CAN CONTINUE AFTER THIS VOTE AND WE'RE HAPPY
TO DISCUSS THAT GOING FORWARD. BUT FOR THE PURPOSES OF THIS
BALLOT FOR THIS QUESTION AT THIS TIME, I WANTED TO FOCUS
THIS ON CLOSING THE LOOPHOLE FOR EXISTING TERM LIMITS
ALREADY ESTABLISHED ON THE POSITIONS THAT ARE ALREADY
IN THE CHARTER. >> SUPERVISOR JAN PRESIDENT I
KNOW WHEN I JUST WANT TO EXPRESS A STRONG DISAGREEMENT
TO THAT SENTIMENT OF THAT WE SOMEHOW CAN TABLE THIS
CONVERSATION AND NOT TO HAVE A OF ONE DISCUSSION YOU ARE
AMENDING OUR CHARTER IS A CHARTER AMENDMENT.
>> IT'S A SAN FRANCISCO CONSTITUTION.
IT'S A SERIOUS MATTER AND WITHOUT SERIOUS VETTING
AND WITHOUT IN-DEPTH CONVERSATION TO ASK COLLEAGUES
TO SIMPLY PUT IT ASIDE AND IGNORE IT AND JUST TO VOTE
FOR IT. I THINK THAT IS A DISSERVICE TO
VOTERS TO DISSERVICE TO SAN AND SISKIND SO SIMPLY TO NOT
FULLY VET A CHARTER AMENDMENT AND JUST TO PUT IT ON THE
BALLOT AND SEE WHAT HAPPENED. I THINK OFTENTIMES THAT IS WHAT
IS HAPPENING IN OUR CITY IS WHEN SUPERVISORS SIMPLY PUTTING
BALLOT PUTTING POLICIES OR IN THIS CASE EVEN MORE SERIOUS
AS A CHARTER AMENDMENT ON BALLOT WITHOUT FULLY VETTING
WITH CONSTITUENTS AND STAKEHOLDERS AND OFTEN TIME
WE LOOK BACK AND CREATE A LOT OF TENSIONS AND DIVISION SIMPLY
BECAUSE WE IGNORE EACH OTHER AND JUST PUT IT THINGS ON
BALLOT FOR THAT REASON STRONGLY GOING TO BE VOTING AGAINST IT
TODAY. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD AND TO
REITERATE I AGREE THAT THERE SHOULD BE DILIGENCE ON
AMENDMENTS THAT ARE PUT FORWARD AND WE DID DUE DILIGENCE ON
THIS ON THIS PROPOSAL WITH THE RESPECT OF UNIONS THAT
REPRESENT THE WORKERS IN THE OFFICES OF MAYOR AND SUPERVISOR
AND THEY DID NOT HAVE A PROBLEM WITH THE SPOT MOTION GOING
FORWARD. BUT AGAIN THERE WAS NOT
EQUIVALENT DILIGENCE DONE ON OTHER POSITIONS.
THERE ARE MANY OTHER UNIONS THAT WE HAVE TO TALK TO
AND WHEN I TALKED TO THEM THEY HAD NOT BEEN CONSULTED WITH YET
WHETHER THEY OPPOSE OR NOT, I THINK IT'S CLEAR THAT THERE'S
OTHER DILIGENCE TO BE DONE. >> SO I AGREE DILIGENCE SHOULD
BE DONE ON AMENDMENTS IN CHARTER AND THERE'S MANY
DIFFERENT NUANCES OF DIFFERENT CHARTER AMENDMENTS.
THERE'S OTHER PARTS OF HOW MANY OTHER SUPERVISORS SHOULD WE
HAVE THAT SHOULD NOT ALSO BE DISCUSSED IN THE CONTEXT OF
THIS MERIT SIMPLY BECAUSE WE ARE REGULATING THE ELECTORAL
TERM LIMITS OF THIS POSITION. I WOULD NOT CONSTITUTE THAT.
WE SHOULD SUDDENLY ADD IN AN AMENDMENT HERE THAT SAYS WE
NEED 12 SUPERVISORS INSTEAD OF 11.
THAT'S ALSO A SEPARATE QUESTION.
SIMILARLY IN TERMS OF TERM LIMIT, SHOULD WE ADD A THIRD
TERM FOR THE SUPERVISOR THAT WAS DISCUSSED AT THE RULES
COMMITTEE AND I ALSO SAID THAT'S NOT IN THE SPIRIT OF
THIS LEGISLATION. THESE ARE ALL SEPARATE
QUESTIONS TO BE DISCUSSED SEPARATELY WOULD SEPARATE
DILIGENCE. WE'VE DONE THE DILIGENCE ON
THIS QUESTION INVITE OTHER SUPERVISORS TO DO THE DILIGENCE
ON THE SEPARATE QUESTIONS AND INTRODUCE IT AS A SEPARATE
MEASURE IF THAT'S AN INTERESTING OPPORTUNITY FOR
THEM. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
PRESIDENT THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT AND I'M FOR
DISCUSSING EVERYTHING THAT MAKES SENSE WHEN WE HAVE A
CHANGE TO THE CHARTER BUT THIS IS THE SECOND TIME MY MY
COLLEAGUE HAS TRIED TO SPEAK FOR LABOR AND LABOR IS NOT HERE
OPPOSING MY AMENDMENTS AND IN FACT THE PEOPLE HE TRIED TO
CALL TO COME OUT AND SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF HIS LEGISLATION
DID NOT COME AND THEY ARE NOT HERE PROPOSING MY AMENDMENTS
BECAUSE HE CANNOT SPEAK FOR LABOR NOR CAN I.
SO I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT THAT PART IS CLEAR AND IF
WE WANT TO JUST MAKE STATEMENTS ABOUT THINGS THAT WE KNOW ARE
UNCONSTITUTIONAL THEN PUT IN A RESOLUTION I SEE NO ONE ELSE
IN THE QUEUE. I WILL OFFER A FEW THOUGHTS OF
MY OWN. I BELIEVE I DISAGREE WITH ALL
OF MY COLLEAGUES. I, I DO NOT BELIEVE THAT TERM
LIMITS ARE A POSITIVE A GOOD I BELIEVE THEY ARE AT BEST A
NECESSARY EVIL. >> I DO NOT PARTICULARLY LIKE
SUPERVISOR MAHMUD'S AMENDMENT BUT I DON'T LIKE THE CHANGES
THAT ARE IN THE GETS WORSE IN MY VIEW IF WE MAKE THE
CHANGES THAT ARE BEING PROPOSED TODAY TERM LIMITS ARE
INHERENTLY ANTI-DEMOCRATIC. THEY ALSO PREVENT US FROM
VOTING FOR PEOPLE WHO MAY WHO HAVE GAINED EXPERIENCE IN TIME
IN OFFICE. THE ANCIENT ATHENIANS BELIEVE
THAT SOME OF THEIR OFFICES SHOULD BE FILLED BY LOTTERY
AND THAT ANY CITIZEN COULD DO THEM.
I BELIEVE THAT THERE IS AND MAYBE THIS IS JUST BECAUSE
I HAVE BEEN IN THIS JOB FOR SO LONG BUT I DO THINK THAT WE GET
BETTER OVER TIME THAT WE LEARN THINGS THAT WE PICK UP SKILLS
THAT WE ARE LESS LIKELY TO MAKE MISTAKES AND THAT THAT'S A
BENEFIT FOR OUR CONSTITUENTS. NOW TERM LIMITS MAY BE
NECESSARY BECAUSE THERE IS A POWER OF INCUMBENCY.
THERE IS A DIFFICULTY IN CHALLENGING SOMEONE WHO IS
SITTING IN THE SEAT YOU ARE TRYING TO TAKE AWAY FROM THEM
BUT IN MY VIEW THE VOTERS OF SAN FRANCISCO SOLVE THAT
PROBLEM WHEN THEY ENACTED THE TERM LIMITS THAT WE HAVE NOW
AND THIS FURTHER CHANGE GOES FURTHER IN THE DIRECTION OF
PREVENTING PEOPLE FROM VOTING FOR THE PERSON THAT THEY MIGHT
WANT TO VOTE FOR EVEN AFTER WE'VE ALREADY DEALT WITH THE
PROBLEM OF INCUMBENCY. SO I DON'T FEEL THE NEED FOR
THIS CHARTER AMENDMENT BUT I ALSO WON'T BE SUPPORTING THE
AMENDMENT TO THE AMENDMENT ON THAT NOTE, MADAM CLERK, COULD
YOU CALL THE ROLL ON SUPERVISOR WALTON'S AMENDMENT ON THE
MOTION MADE TO ITEM 26? SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL NO
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WALTON NO.
WONG NO. SHE'S MY SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY NO
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD NO.
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN NO MANDEL MIN NO.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR NO. MELGAR NO.
AND SUPERVISOR SORTER SAUTER NO.
THERE ARE FOUR EYES AND SEVEN NOS WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON
CHAN CHIN AND FIELDER VOTING I AND SO THE AMENDMENT FAILS OR
THE MOTION FAILS. MADAM CLERK COULD YOU CALL THE
ROLL ON THE ORIGINAL ITEM? >> YES.
THE QUESTION IS WHETHER TO CONTINUE ITEM 26 ON FIRST
APPEARANCE TO FEBRUARY 3RD. >> SO THIS IS NOT ON THE I'M
SORRY FOLKS I GOT IT CONFUSED. WE'RE NOT VOTING ON THE ITEM
WE'RE VOTING ON CONTINUING THIS TO FEBRUARY THIRD AS WE HAVE TO
DO. >> AND MR. PRESIDENT, WE DON'T
NEED THIS BUT WE'RE JUST GOING TO ADD IT FOR THE RECORD ON THE
QUESTION TO CONTINUE TO FEBRUARY 3RD CAN WE HAVE A
MOTION IN A SECOND? >> WE HAVE A MOTION TO CONTINUE
TO FEBRUARY 3RD MOVED BY CHERYL SECONDED BY MAHMOOD.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THAT MOTION SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON NO WALTON NO SUPERVISOR
WON'T WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN NO.
>> CHIN NO. SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN I MANDOLIN
I SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SORTER SORTER I
THERE ARE EIGHT EYES AND THREE NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON
CHAN AND FIELDER VOTING NO THE CHARTER AMENDMENT IS CONTINUED
TO FEBRUARY 3RD 2026. ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK LET'S GO
TO OUR 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER YES THE 230 SPECIAL ORDER IS
RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU PRESIDENT
MANAGEMENT COLLEAGUES TODAY I WOULD LIKE TO CALL THE FRIENDS
OF DELTA PLAZA PARK HERE TO THE LECTERN.
>> WHERE ARE YOU? COME ON STEP ON UP.
IT IS AN ABSOLUTE HONOR TO COMMEND THIS FANTASTIC GROUPS
OF LEADERS AND STEWARDS OF ONE OF MY FAVORITE PARKS IN THE
CITY ALL TO PLAZA AND SPECIFICALLY WE ARE HERE TO
COMMEND THEIR RECENT CERTIFICATION AS AN OFFICIAL
FIVE 01C3 CERTIFYING THEIR NONPROFIT STATUS AND EMPOWERING
THEIR STEWARDSHIP OF THIS JEWEL OF THE CITY FOR YEARS TO COME.
AS LONGTIME LEADER AND MY FRIEND ANITA DENNIS ALWAYS SAYS
TO PLAZA PARK IS TRULY A CROWN JEWEL OF OUR CITY AND THAT IS
IN LARGE PART BECAUSE OF THE DECADES LONG DEDICATION BY THE
FRIENDS OF ALL TO PLAZA STARTING IN 2000 TO THE
FOUNDING MOTHERS WHICH INCLUDES ANITA RAISED A MILLION AND A
HALF DOLLARS TO INSTALL MANY OF THE PLAYGROUND AND RECREATIONAL
FACILITIES THAT OUR NEIGHBORHOOD CHILDREN ENJOY
TODAY AND BY OUR NEIGHBORHOOD CHILDREN.
I ALSO MEAN MY CHILDREN. SINCE THEN THE FRIENDS OF GROUP
HAS WORKED TIRELESS SOLELY TO MAINTAIN AND IMPROVE THIS PARK
FUNDRAISING CLEANUPS ESTABLISHING A MASTER PLAN FOR
FUTURE INVESTMENTS BUT LIKE MANY OTHER GROUPS CITYWIDE, THE
PANDEMIC AND ESPECIALLY THE RECENT PARKS ALLIANCE DEBACLE
POSED EXISTENTIAL THREATS TO THIS FABULOUS GROUP.
FOLLOWING THE DISSOLUTION OF THE PARKS ALLIANCE, THE FRIENDS
OF ALL TO PLAZA GROUP LOST A SUBSTANTIAL AMOUNT OF THEIR
FUNDS AND WERE LEFT WITH NO FISCAL SPONSOR.
BUT NOW THANKS TO THIS EXTREMELY GOOD LOOKING GROUP
HERE IN FRONT OF US THE FRIENDS OF GROUP IS ENTER AN EXCITING
NEW CHAPTER HAVING FULLY RECONSTITUTED THEIR BOARD
AND BECOMING THEIR OWN FISCAL SPONSOR BY SETTING UP A501C3
AND BECAUSE OF THE MANY DONORS WHO STEPPED UP IN THE WEEKS OF
THE PARKS ALLIANCE, THE FRIENDS OF ALL TO PLAZA GROUP IS CLOSE
TO GETTING THEIR MONEY BACK. >> BUT THIS GROUP IS NOT
STOPPING THERE. >> THEY RECENTLY LAUNCHED A
SUCCESSFUL FUNDRAISING CAMPAIGN AND IN PARTNERSHIP WITH REC
AND PARK ARE WORKING TO RESURFACE THE PLAYGROUND
AND UPGRADE THE PLAY EQUIPMENT AND ALL OF THIS IS MADE
POSSIBLE BY YOU. YOU EXEMPLIFY THE SPIRIT OF
STEWARDSHIP, OF PERSEVERANCE AND OF TOGETHERNESS.
YOU REPRESENT WHAT MAKES SAN FRANCISCO SPECIAL NOW FRIENDS.
>> THESE LEADERS INCLUDE PRESIDENT ANUSHKA SHARMA,
TREASURER GREG SCOTT, SECRETARY ANITA DENNIS AND BOARD MEMBERS
IAN CHADWICK, ALLISON KIRBY DRONE, DAVID HADLEY, CYNTHIA
TRINA AND LADD MARTIN. SO ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS I THANK THE FRIENDS OF ALTA PLAZA PARK ALL OF YOU
AND ALL OF THE OTHER MEMBERS OF YOUR COMMUNITY FOR YOUR
RESILIENCE, FOR YOUR VISION AND YOUR UNWAVERING COMMITMENT
TO CREATING A PARK THAT ALL SAN FRANCISCANS CAN ENJOY FOR
GENERATIONS TO COME. >> CONGRATULATIONS.
AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS ALL WE'D LIKE TO THANK YOU THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AND SPECIFICALLY SUPERVISOR CHERYL AND YOUR
OFFICE SPECIFICALLY MICK DEROSA AND LORENZO ROSAS FOR THIS
COMMENDATION AND MORE IMPORTANTLY FOR YOUR CONTINUED
ADVOCACY AND SUPPORT OF ALTA PLAZA PARK AND OUR
ORGANIZATION. >> OUR MISSION IS TO MAINTAIN
AND IMPROVE ALTA PLAZA PARK ON BEHALF OF OUR NEIGHBORS AND THE
CITY. >> ALTHOUGH THE PARK SITS
IN DISTRICT TWO, IT IS INDEED A HISTORIC TREASURE FOR THE WHOLE
CITY AND MEMBERS ACROSS OUR SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY USE
AND ENJOY OUR PARK ON A REGULAR BASIS AND INDEED EVEN BEYOND
CITYWIDE. >> AS SUPERVISOR CHERYL SAID
OVER THE PAST YEAR WE AS AN ORGANIZATION HAVE COME TOGETHER
CONSTITUTED A NEW BOARD. WE HAVE INCORPORATED AS A NEW
NONPROFIT. WE HAVE NAVIGATED THE
CHALLENGING ENVIRONMENT THAT HAPPENED WITH THE FISCAL
SPONSORSHIP CRISIS AND WORKED WITH OTHER PARK COMMUNITY
LEADERS AS IT RELATED TO OUR FUNDS.
>> WE'VE GONE THROUGH A BRAND AND COMMUNICATIONS REFRESH AN
UPDATE AND NOW WE HAVE LAUNCHED AMBITIOUS AMBITIOUS FUNDRAISING
CAMPAIGN FOCUSED ON THE FREEDMAN FAMILY CHILDREN'S
PLAYGROUND. WE HAVE A LOT OF MOMENTUM
IN THE COMMUNITY. IT IS VERY EXCITING AROUND THE
NEIGHBORHOOD AND ALL OF THAT WOULD ALSO NOT BE POSSIBLE
WITHOUT OUR CONTINUED PARTNERSHIP WITH SAN FRANCISCO
RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT AND SPECIFICALLY WANT TO CALL
OUT ABIGAIL MAYOR AND JACK AVERY FOR THEIR CONTINUED
SUPPORT AND PARTNERSHIP WITH US.
>> WE AS A BOARD ARE VERY FORTUNATE THAT WE HAVE MEMBERS
WHO HAVE DECADES LONG COMMUNITY ADVOCACY, VOLUNTEERING CIVIC
LEADERSHIP AS WELL AS MEMBERS OF THE BOARD WHO ARE RAISING
YOUNG FAMILIES IN THIS CITY ARE DRIVING ECONOMICALLY CREATING
JOBS, GROWING OUR TAX BASE. AND WITH THAT I'D ALSO LIKE TO
THANK THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND INDEED THE MAYOR'S OFFICE
FOR CREATING AN ENVIRONMENT WHERE THOSE OF US IN THE
PRIVATE REALM ALSO WANT TO PRIORITIZE ENGAGING IN THE
PUBLIC REALM AS WELL ALONGSIDE MANY PEOPLE WHO WE FIND
ASPIRATIONAL WHO HAVE GIVEN MANY, MANY YEARS OF SERVICE
IN ENHANCING OUR CITY AND COMMUNITY.
>> AND FINALLY, I'D LIKE TO THANK MY FELLOW BOARD OF
DIRECTORS OR FRIENDS OF ALTA PLAZA PARK, SOME OF WHOM ARE
HERE TODAY, OTHERS WHO ARE NOT AND SPECIFICALLY I DO ALSO WANT
TO CALL OUT ANITA. >> SHE IS FAR TOO HUMBLE TO
TAKE ANY PRAISE BUT WE ARE AN IMMENSE DEBT OF HONOR
AND GRATITUDE FOR HER TIRELESS WORK OVER MANY MANY YEARS.
ALTA PLAZA PARK WOULD NOT BE WHAT IT IS TODAY WITHOUT HER
TIRELESS LEADERSHIP AND SERVICE WITHOUT ORGANIZATION.
AND SO WITH THAT I WILL HAND OVER TO ANITA.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH,
SUPERVISOR SHERYL FOR YOUR OUTREACH TO THE FRIENDS OF ALL
TO PLAZA PARK AT THE VERY START OF YOUR BOARD APPOINT A
APPOINTMENT. AND OUR APPRECIATION GOES AS
WELL TO YOUR LEGISLATIVE AIDE DEL ROSARIO AND LORENZO ROSAS.
BUT IN ACCEPTING ACCEPTING THIS HONOR WE MUST PAY HOMAGE TO THE
FRIENDS OF ALL TYPES OF PARK FOUNDING MOTHERS OF WHICH I AM
NOT ONE. BUT THEY IN 2002 ENVISIONED A
SAFE SOME AND CHALLENGING PLAYGROUND FOR ALL THE CITY'S
FAMILIES AND THEY WERE ELISE FRIEDMAN, MOLLY BROWN, CASEY
JARMAN, LAUREN HALL AND REBECCA BIRDSALL.
AND THEIR MISSION WAS GUIDED WITH GOOD COUNSEL FROM LYNN
NEWHOUSE. SIEGEL NOT BEFORE THE BENEFIT
OF FACEBOOK AND INSTAGRAM AND EVENTBRITE.
THESE WOMEN RAISED $1.5 MILLION TO DEVELOP ONE OF THE MOST
LOVED AND USED PLAYGROUNDS IN THE CITY.
WE HAVE FAMILIES FROM MULTIPLE DISTRICTS FROM THE MISSION, THE
SUNSET, THE POTRERO AND ALL COME TO ENJOY A RECREATIONAL
FACILITIES EXPANSIVE LAWNS IN COMPARABLE VIEWS.
NEXT WE OWE A BIG DEBT OF GRATITUDE TO MY COLLEAGUE JANET
GAMBLE. THROUGH SIX TOWN HALL MEETINGS,
COMMUNITY INPUT RESULTED IN A MASTER PLAN DEVELOPED BY MILLER
COMPANY LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTS. AND IT WAS APPROVED BY THE
PARKS COMMISSION IN 2016. FROM 2015 TO 2018 JANET WORKED
CLOSELY WITH OUR PD AND DPW AND STEERED THE FRIENDS THROUGH
A MAJOR WATER CONSERVED PROJECT AND COMPLETED THE DONOR CIRCLE
IN LANDSCAPING AND VISION BY OUR FOUNDERS.
>> NOW KUDOS ALSO TO SUPERVISORS MARK FARRELL
AND KATHRYN STEPHANIE WHO PROVIDED GENEROUS ADD BACK
FUNDS DURING THEIR TEN YEARS AND THE FRIENDS ARE VERY
GRATEFUL FOR THE MENTORING OF STEPHAN FRONDS OF LAFAYETTE
PARK IN PROZAC AND ALONG WITH LINDA AND JOE LIGHTHIZER OF
MCLAREN PARK FRIENDS OF THE AMP.
OUR ACCOMPLISHMENTS HAVE BEEN MADE POSSIBLE BY THE
COLLABORATIVE RELATIONSHIP WE HAVE WITH SAN FRANCISCO WORK
AND PARKS STAFF. AND FIRST OF ALL PHIL GINSBURG
WAS A VERY GOOD FRIEND TO THE FRIENDS OF ALL TO PLAZA PARK
ALONG WITH SARAH MADELINE, BEVERLY NING, LISA BRANSTON,
ABIGAIL MILLER, JACK AVERY, JOE RODEO, DANA KETCHUM, FELIX
TONG, VINCE MCEVOY, JENNIFER GEE DAVE BURNETT.
AND THE DEDICATION OF OUR PSA MANAGER ZACH TAYLOR SUPERVISOR
TIM TICE AND AND GARDENER EMMA TONY.
AT THE LEAST OUR DEEP GRATITUDE TO THE COMMUNITY PARK NETWORK
ADVISORY COMMITTEE HONORED HERE JUST LAST WEEK BY BOARD
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR ADVOCACY IN SECURING A
REIMBURSEMENT OF THE FUNDS WE LOST THROUGH THE SAN FRANCISCO
PARKS ALLIANCE BANKRUPTCY. AND THAT WAS WHERE ASHIQ ZARIF
ILDIKO POLONI AND MATTHEW BLAINE.
THANKS TO TO MY WONDERFUL BOARD WHO HAVE COME FORWARD AND TO
SUPPORT OUR REINVIGORATED EFFORT AND MISSION TO MAKE THE
PARK THE BEST IT CAN BE. AND THANKS ONCE MORE SUPERVISOR
CHERYL FOR THIS ACKNOWLEDGMENT AND YOUR ONGOING SUPPORT
. HMM.
MIXED UP DISTRICT THREE SUPERVISOR SAUTER.
>> TODAY I HAVE THE HONOR OF RECOGNIZING GRACE.
>> THE LONG STANDING BUT LONG STANDING CANTONESE PROFESSOR AT
CITY COLLEGE. >> COLLEAGUES PROFESSOR YU
PROFESSOR YU OR YU LOCY AS WE CALL HER IS TRULY REMARKABLE.
AND LET ME TELL YOU WHY. RAISED IN HONG KONG PROFESSOR,
YOU GRADUATED FROM NATIONAL TAIWAN UNIVERSITY AND MOVED TO
THE UNITED STATES IN THE LATE 1960S.
SHE RECEIVED HER MASTER'S DEGREE IN COMPARATIVE
LITERATURE FROM UC BERKELEY IN A BILINGUAL EDUCATION
DOCTORATE FROM NEW YORK UNIVERSITY.
SHE SHE TAUGHT CANTONESE FROM 1978 TO 1983 AT SAN FRANCISCO
STATE UNIVERSITY AND TAUGHT ENGLISH TO IMMIGRANTS AT CITY
COLLEGE. IN 1990 SHE BEGAN TEACHING
CANTONESE FULL TIME AT CITY COLLEGE.
TODAY SHE IS THE LAST AND ONLY CANTONESE TEACHER AT CITY
COLLEGE. AND AS FAR AS I CAN TELL NO ONE
IN SAN FRANCISCO HAS TAUGHT MORE STUDENTS CANTONESE THAN
PROFESSOR YU. IN A CITY DEEPLY SHAPED
AND BUILT BY OUR CHINESE COMMUNITY IS CANTONESE IS THE
LANGUAGE THAT HAS CARRIED THE STORIES ALONG FOR GENERATIONS
OF SAN FRANCISCANS AND THAT IS STILL USED EVERY SINGLE DAY TO
MAKE OUR CITY WORK. I HAD THE PLEASURE OF TAKING
TWO SEMESTERS OF CANTONESE WITH PROFESSOR YU AT CITY COLLEGE
WHEN I ARRIVED FOR THE FIRST DAY OF CLASS.
THE FIRST THING I NOTICED WAS HOW POPULAR SHE WAS.
STUDENTS WERE LINED UP IN HALLWAYS IN THE HALLWAY
AND SITTING ON THE FLOOR ON THE SIDE OF THE ROOM.
AND THAT IS ALL BECAUSE THEY WANTED TO GET A SPOT IN THAT
CLASS. >> CLASS WITH PROFESSOR YU IS
LESS LIKE AN ACADEMIC EXERCISE AND IT FEELS MORE LIKE A GET
TOGETHER WITH FAMILY AND FRIENDS.
>> SHE WEAVES IN SONGS, STORIES AND HISTORY WITH HER TEACHING
AND THEN A FEW MORE SONGS SHE REALLY LOVES TO SING WITH HER
STUDENTS. >> PROFESSOR USE LOVE
AND ADVOCACY FOR CANTONESE IS NOT A SOLO ACT.
IN FACT HER WORK HAS BEEN CHAMPIONED BY THE EMERGING
SAVED CANTONESE MOVEMENT. THIS ORGANIZED ORGANIZATION HAS
SPREAD ACROSS THE COUNTRY TO FIGHT FOR CANTONESE CLASSES
IN MANY SCHOOLS AND COMMUNITIES HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
WE'RE LUCKY TO HAVE HAD INCREDIBLE LEADERS
AND SUPPORTING SUPPORTERS INCLUDING JULIA KWAN WHO
FOUNDED THE GROUP AT CSUF. WE'VE ALSO HAD STRONG SUPPORT
FROM ELECTED LEADERS INCLUDING THEN CITY COLLEGE TRUSTEE WONG
WHO LED A PUSH TO SAVE THE PROGRAM AND ESTABLISH A
CERTIFICATE PROGRAM. PROFESSOR YU.
PROFESSOR YOU THANK YOU FOR YOUR DEDICATION TO SAN
FRANCISCO AND TO THE INCREDIBLE LANGUAGE OF CANTONESE.
THANK YOU FOR TEACHING MYSELF AND THOUSANDS OF STUDENTS SO
MUCH OVER YOUR NEARLY FIVE DECADES OF TEACHING IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND NOW I WILL ATTEMPT TO SAY A FEW WORDS
IN CANTONESE OF WHICH I AM SURE YOU WILL.
YOU WILL TELL ME AFTERWARDS HOW BAD MY TONES TRULY ARE.
>> SO HERE WE GO. COMING UP, MORE HOI HOI SOME
YONG WHY NOT A UTOPIA WHERE YOU GO SOME FANCY YINHONG HING YUK
OR SIX U.S. YOGANANDA YANG WHY NOT SAYING GOING HIGH CITY
COLLEGE HAKKA TUNG YUE LOCI OH YOU LOCI YOU LACK YAO SIN LIONG
TONG MY WHOLE KUNG LEK SOME FANCY OR YOU LOCI THOUGHT
AND PROFESSOR BEFORE YOU SPEAK A FEW OF MY COLLEAGUES WOULD
ALSO LIKE TO BRIEFLY SAY A FEW THINGS.
>> SUPERVISOR WANG THOSE ARE YOU LONG SEE I KNEW JULIA KWAN
AND UH, DANNY BEFORE THEY TOOK TOOK SOME OF YOUR CLASSES.
>> I WOULD SAY THEIR CANTONESE HAS IMPROVED.
>> I REMEMBER LISTENING TO JULIA'S TONES AND BEFORE
AND AFTER CLASSES AND THERE WAS A LOT OF IMPROVEMENT.
>> SO THIS IS FOR FOR PROFESSOR YU.
>> IT'S I'M SO GLAD THAT WE'RE ABLE TO HONOR YOU TODAY.
YOUR WORK HAS BEEN SO VITAL TO ENSURING THAT THE NEXT
GENERATION OF PUBLIC SAFETY WORKERS HEALTH CARE WORKERS,
SOCIAL WORKERS, NONPROFIT WORKERS AND OTHER FOLKS THAT
HAVE PUBLIC CONTACT ARE ABLE TO SERVE OUR COMMUNITIES.
>> MY OWN PARENTS ARE ORIGINALLY FROM HONG KONG AND I
WAS BORN AND RAISED OVER HERE AND GROWING UP THERE WERE MANY
TIMES LIKE MANY OF THE OTHER FOLKS IN IN THE AUDIENCE WE HAD
TO HELP OUR PARENTS TRANSLATE TO HELP THEM BE ABLE TO FILL
OUT FORMS OR GET ACCESS TO SERVICES AND THAT'S THE
EXPERIENCE OF OUR ABC. >> FOR THOSE THAT DON'T KNOW
WHAT THAT IS, IT'S AMERICAN BORN CHINESE AND SO MANY PEOPLE
HAVE GONE THROUGH THE HALLS OF CITY COLLEGE TO LEARN CANTONESE
BECAUSE THEY WANT TO IMPROVE THEIR CANTONESE SKILLS AND BE
ABLE TO SERVE THEIR COMMUNITY. WE HAVE POLICE OFFICERS,
FIREFIGHTERS, HEALTH CARE WORKERS LIKE JULIA THAT HAVE
ATTENDED CLASS BECAUSE THEY WANT TO TALK TO THE PEOPLE THAT
THEY SERVE AND IT'S SO IMPORTANT THAT WE CONTINUE OUR
ADVOCACY TO DEVELOP A CANTONESE PROGRAM AT CITY COLLEGE.
ORIGINALLY THERE WAS A INTENT TO CUT ALL OF OUR CANTONESE
CLASSES EVEN THOUGH OTHER THAN ENGLISH AND SPANISH, CANTONESE
IS THE OTHER BIG LANGUAGE IN THE CITY.
IT DID NOT MAKE SENSE AT ALL THAT WE WOULD HAVE NOT HAVE A
CLASS FOR THIS MAJOR LANGUAGE IN OUR CITY WHEN WE HAD OTHER
CLASSES FOR SO MANY OTHER LANGUAGES BUT NOT CONTINUOUSLY
DO NOT MAKE SENSE AT ALL AND THE REASON IS THAT THE THE
CLASSES DIDN'T HAVE THE SAME VALUE AS OTHER CLASSES WERE
WHEREAS OTHER CLASSES HAD DIFFERENT DIFFERENT PROGRAMS
AND CERTIFICATES THAT COUNTED TOWARDS STATE REQUIREMENTS.
CANTONESE NEVER HAD THAT AND WE WERE ABLE TO ESTABLISH A NINE
UNIT CERTIFICATE PROGRAM AND AT THE SAME TIME THERE'S STILL
MORE WORK TO DO TO DEVELOP A 1618 UNIT CERTIFICATE PROGRAM
SO THAT IT DOES COUNT TOWARDS STATE REQUIREMENTS AND THERE IS
VALUE IN THE CLASSES SO THAT ADMINISTRATORS DON'T SEE IT AS
JUST A CLASS THAT DOESN'T HAVE VALUE IN TERMS OF THOSE METRICS
BUT VALUE FOR ME FOR MEETING THE STATE REQUIREMENTS.
>> BUT ON ITS OWN THOUGH THERE IS PLENTY OF VALUE.
>> PEOPLE JUST ARE LOOKING AT THESE METRICS BUT THE VALUE
THAT CONTINUES CAUSES THAT PROFESSOR YU TEACHES THAT IT
PROVIDES TRUE VALUE TO OUR COMMUNITY AND ENSURING THAT OUR
SENIORS AND OUR IMMIGRANTS ARE ABLE TO ACCESS SERVICES, ARE
ABLE TO TALK TO THEIR HEALTH CARE WORKERS.
SO I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR ALL YOUR WORK SUPPORTING OUR
COMMUNITIES AND YOUR DECADES OF LEADERSHIP BEING THERE FOR FOR
ALL OF US. OUR COMMUNITY IS SO THANKFUL
FOR YOU AND ONCE YOU RECOGNIZE THE OBVIOUSLY A SURPRISE
SURPRISE THERE. SAUDER THANK YOU FOR BRINGING
THIS FORWARD AND BEING A STUDENT OF CANTONESE AND BEING
ABLE TO REPRESENT THAT BIG PART OF OUR COMMUNITY BY REALLY
PUTTING YOURSELF INTO THE CULTURE AND LANGUAGE AND FOR
THE SAVE CANTONESE MOVEMENT ESPECIALLY JULIA FOR STEPPING
UP AND BEING A REAL LEADER WITH YOUR CHARISMA AND YOUR ADVOCACY
BRINGING PEOPLE TOGETHER SO THAT WE DO HAVE THIS LOCAL
MOVEMENT. I'M HAPPY TO BE ABLE TO BE
THERE TO BE A PART OF THIS JOURNEY AND TO BE ABLE TO
SUPPORT AND LOOKING FORWARD TO CONTINUING THE EFFORT TO SAVE
CANTONESE. THANK YOU PROFESSOR YOU PLEASE
CONTINUE YOUR WORK. WE NEED YOU AS AN INSTRUCTOR TO
STAY AT CITY COLLEGE. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR IS
THERE CHEN YELLOW SEA. >> OH, OKAY.
ALL RIGHT. BUT THEY ALREADY SAID WHATEVER
I WROTE IN MY SPEECH YELLOW SEA TO MY GOING INTO YELLOW SEA
HOME AND ALSO IN CONGO YET GOING ON DONGHUA YES
AND HUNTING CONDO DANCY HEY EUGENE GONG DANG ORTEGA LEXIE
THOMAS I'M EACH IS NOT JUST LANGUAGE BUT YOU PRESERVE
HERITAGE AND THANK YOU FOR ALL OF YOU TO CONTINUE TO PRESERVE
CANTONESE AND I ALSO WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR LIFETIME
DEDICATION TO CULTURAL AND EDUCATION AND THE ADVOCACY
WORK. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
OH SU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD A REAL HONOR TO TO ME YOU PROFESSOR,
YOU AND I WHY DON'T KNOW HE HAS SEEN SO MANY IN THE COMMUNITY
TALK ABOUT WHAT YOU'VE DONE FOR THEM FOR GENERATIONAL CHANGE
BUT ALSO JUST FOR PASSING DOWN THE LANGUAGE I'VE KNOWN
SUPERVISOR SLAUGHTER FOR FOR MANY YEARS AND I'VE SEEN HIS
CANTONESE GET A LITTLE BIT BETTER OVER THE TIME.
SO I WANTED TO THANK YOU FOR FOR HELPING HIM AND HELPING SO
MANY PEOPLE AND REALLY APPRECIATIVE OF WHAT YOU'RE
DOING THE COMMUNITY I DO HOPE THAT AS ONE FINAL QUESTION FOR
YOU, I THINK WE'RE ALL VERY CURIOUS.
WHAT GRADE DID YOU GIVE SUPERVISOR SAUTER IN PLACE IF
YOU'RE WILLING TO SAY HEY OH WOW, THANK YOU AGAIN PROFESSOR
YU THE FLOOR IS YOURS. >> OKAY BUT EVERYBODY ALREADY
SAID WHAT I REALLY OKAY I READ IT GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS
LADIES MANDELMAN, FIRST I WOULD LIKE TO EXPRESS MY HEARTFELT
THANKS TO THE SUPERVISOR DANNY SALTER FOR THE HONOR OF THIS
COMMENDATION. I FEEL HUMBLED.
I HAVE BEEN PRIVILEGED TO TEACH CANTONESE FOR MANY YEARS.
IT HAS NEVER BEEN A JUST A JOB TO ME IT IS TRULY MY CALLING.
>> I'M PROUD OF MY CHINESE HERITAGE AND I CHERISH EVERY
OPPORTUNITY TO SHARE MY CULTURE AND MY NATIVE LANGUAGE WITH
ANYONE WHO WISHES TO LEARN. I RECEIVED MY EDUCATION IN HONG
KONG AND TAIWAN AFTER GRADUATING FROM COLLEGE I CAME
TO THE UNITED STATES TO STUDY COMPARATIVE LITERATURE AT UC
BERKELEY AND LATER BILINGUAL EDUCATION AT NEW YORK
UNIVERSITY. >> I'M DEEPLY GRATEFUL TO MY
ALMA MATERS FOR BROADENING MY UNDERSTANDING OF ENGLISH
AND WESTERN CULTURES. WHILE I WAS A GRADUATE STUDENT
AT UC BERKELEY, I WAS GIVEN THE OPPORTUNITY TO TEACH CANTONESE
IN THE ASIAN AMERICAN STUDIES DEPARTMENT THERE AS WELL AS
IN THE LINGUISTICS DEPARTMENT AT UC SAN DIEGO.
THE EARLY TEACHING EXPERIENCES SPARKED MY LIFELONG
PASSION FOR CANTONESE EDUCATION .
>> AFTER COMPLETING MY STUDIES AT NYU, I BEGAN MY CAREER
TEACHING CANTONESE AT SAN FRANCISCO STATE UNIVERSITY
AND LATER A CITY COLLEGE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
MY CONTINUED CLASSES ARE LIKE BIG FAMILIES.
STUDENTS SHARED LAUGHTER AND JOY THROUGH ACTIVITIES SUCH
AS REAL PLACE SKITS, SINGING KIND OF POP SONGS, DISCUSSIONS
AND DELIVERING SPEECHES ON A VARIETY OF SUBJECTS.
THROUGH THESE SPEECHES WE LEARNED THAT AUSTRALIANS
CELEBRATE CHRISTMAS AT THE BEACH WITH BARBECUES AND THE
LINE DOES HAS DEEP ROOTS IN MARTIAL ARTS.
STUDENTS HAVE SHARED STORIES OF CLIMBING THE HIMALAYAS, RUNNING
MARATHONS, TRAVELING THROUGH WASHINGTON AND BEIJING AND MANY
OTHER REMARKABLE EXPERIENCES. ONE STUDENT, A YOGA TEACHER
BERNIECE EVEN LET A TEN MINUTE YOGA BREAK FOR TWO SEMESTERS.
WE ALSO VISITED RESTAURANTS TOGETHER TO EXPLORE CANTONESE
CUISINE. THESE LIVELY INTERACTIVE
EXPERIENCES HELP STUDENTS FROM FRENCH FORM FRIENDSHIPS THAT
LAST FAR BEYOND THE CLASSROOM. >> I HAVE ALSO LEARNED FROM MY
STUDENTS. IN CLOSING, I WANT TO THANK THE
PRESIDENT OF THE TRUSTEES BOARD OF TRUSTEES OF CITY COLLEGE
ALAN WONG FOR PASSING A RESOLUTION TO PROTECT CANTONESE
CLASSES AND THE MEMBERS OF SAFE CANTONESE FOR THEIR DEDICATION
TO PRESERVING CANTONESE AS AN ESSENTIAL PART OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S CULTURAL HERITAGE. THANK YOU AGAIN FOR THIS HONOR
. >> YEAH.
THANK YOU. >> STUDENTS COME TO THE SITE
DURING AN AND THESE ARE FOR YOU.
AND WHAT CAN WE JUST NAME? YEAH, YEAH, YEAH.
I CAN SEE THAT. >> MARGARET MYRON, COME TO THE
FRONT. COME ON IN.
JERRY COME TO THE FRONT. ANGELA.
YES. SO DON'T BE SO HARD TO GET ME.
YOU'LL NEED TO KNEEL. ANGELA.
COME ON. COME ON.
COME ON IN. YOU HAVE TO COME IN CLOSER TO
ME. LINES, PLEASE.
SOME MORE HERE. HERE WE GO.
COME ON IN TIGHT, TIGHT, SIDEWAYS.
ALL RIGHT. >> YOU JUST DO THIS LIKE ONE
FIRST, PLEASE. SO A LITTLE BIT TIGHTER AND THE
RIGHT SIDE OF THIS QUESTION RIGHT?
DON'T ME HERE. OKAY, LET'S GO.
IT'S LIKE OKAY. OKAY.
LET'S GO OUTSIDE. OH, OUTSIDE RIGHT NOW?
YEAH
. ALL RIGHT.
NEXT UP. DISTRICT NINE SUPERVISOR
FIELDER. >> THANKS.
PRESIDENT MIDDLEMAN COLLEAGUES. >> LAST MONTH IN THE MISSION
OUR COMMUNITIES SUDDENLY LOST A TRUE PILLAR.
SO TODAY I AM POSTHUMOUSLY COMMENDING RICARDO PENA WHOSE
PRESENCE SHAPED THE MISSION DISTRICT FOR MORE THAN TWO
DECADES. AND AT THIS TIME I WOULD LIKE
TO INVITE HIS WIFE CONNIE TO THE PODIUM.
>> FOR OVER 20 YEARS RICARDO WAS A FAMILIAR AND WELCOMING
FACE ON 24TH STREET AT MICHIGAN .
>> HE WAS AN ARTIST, A BUSINESS OWNER AND ABOVE ALL A FRIEND TO
EVERYONE WHO CROSSED HIS PATH. >> HIS COMMITMENT TO THE
MISSION WAS CONSTANT AND HANDS ON.
YEAR AFTER YEAR HE VOLUNTEERED WITH JAIME THE CUATRO HELPING
TO BEAUTIFY THE CORRIDOR AND KEEP ITS SPIRIT ALIVE.
HE SHARED HIS GIFTS FREELY TEACHING DANZA CLASSES AT THE
MISSION CULTURAL CENTER FOR LATINO ARTS AND SHARING THE
CULTURE WAS NOT ONLY PRESERVED BUT LIVED AND FELT.
RICARDO WAS MORE THAN A COMMUNITY MEMBER.
HE WAS OUR GUARDIAN A SPIRITUAL WARRIOR.
MANY OF US CAME TO SEE HIM AS AN AZTEC WARRIOR OF LOVE.
THROUGH HIS DANZA AND THE STEADY RHYTHM OF HIS DRUM HE
CARRIED MEDICINE, PRAYER AND HEALING.
HIS PRESENCE WAS GROUNDING. HIS ENERGY WAS PROTECTIVE.
HE BECAME THE HEARTBEAT OF THE COMMUNITY OFFERING STRENGTH
AND CALM IN MOMENTS WHEN THE COMMUNITY NEEDED IT MOST.
DEEPLY PROUD OF HIS NORTE INDIGENOUS ROOTS.
>> RICARDO DEVOTED HIS LIFE TO PRESERVING AND SHARING DANCE
AZTECA ALONGSIDE HIS WIFE CONNIE.
>> HE LED GRUPO GO OUT ON A WALK.
>> PASSING ANCESTRAL KNOWLEDGE TO GENERATIONS OF MISSION YOUTH
. TOGETHER THEY BLESSED COUNTLESS
CEREMONIES THROUGHOUT THE NEIGHBORHOOD REMINDING US THAT
TRADITION IS NOT SOMETHING OF THE PAST.
IT IS SOMETHING WE CARRY FORWARD.
RICARDO'S LIFE WAS DEFINED BY SERVICE AND GENEROSITY.
HE WAS KNOWN AS WISE, KIND, HUMBLE, CALM AND DEEPLY
PEACEFUL. HE NEVER HESITATED TO BE OF
SERVICE DURING THE PANDEMIC. HE STOOD SHOULDER TO SHOULDER
WITH COMMUNITY MEMBERS AT THE MISSION FOOD HUB HELPING
DISTRIBUTE THOUSANDS OF FOOD BOXES AND OFFERING DIGNITY,
PRESENCE AND CARE DURING SOME OF OUR MOST VULNERABLE MOMENTS.
ABOVE ALL, RICARDO WAS A LOVING FAMILY MAN A DEVOTED HUSBAND,
FATHER THE TEACHER AND FRIEND. HE LEAVES BEHIND A BEAUTIFUL
FAMILY OF THEN SUNDAYS HIS WIFE CONNIE HIS CHILDREN SOJI
AND CUAUHTÉMOC AS WELL AS A COMMUNITY FOREVER SHAPED BY HIS
LOVE. >> RICARDO'S LEGACY LIVES ON
IN EVERY DRUMBEAT, EVERY DANCE STEP, EVERY CEREMONY AND EVERY
ACT OF SERVICE. INSPIRED BY HIS EXAMPLE.
>> HE TAUGHT US HOW TO LISTEN WITH OUR HEARTS, HOW TO SERVE
WITH HUMILITY AND HOW TO WALK TOGETHER IN UNITY.
THOUGH HE IS NO LONGER WITH US IN BODY, HIS ACTIONS CONTINUE
TO GUIDE OUR COMMUNITY REMINDING US THAT TRUE
LEADERSHIP IS ROOTED IN LOVE, SERVICE AND SHARED HUMANITY.
THANK YOU TO CONNIE FOR SHARING HIM WITH US PLEASE AND I WANT
TO PASS TO MY COLLEAGUES ADVISOR MELGAR.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR THAT
REALLY MOVING TRIBUTE TO CONNIE .
HIGH WATER MARK. I'M SO SORRY FOR YOUR LOSS TO
THE REST OF THE DANCE FAMILY WE LOST.
YOU KNOW OF A FRIEND, A LEADER, SOMEBODY WHO EMBODY THE CONCEPT
OF LA CULTURE ACURA AND GAVE SO MUCH TO US IS LEAVING SO MUCH
TO ALL OF US. SO MAY HIS MEMORY BE A
BLESSING. WE DEEPLY HONOR HIM TODAY
AND THANK YOU FOR HAVING SHARED HIM WITH US.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR JEN HONEY.
>> I ALSO WANT TO SAY I'M DEEPLY SORRY TO LEARN THE LOSS
AND MY DEEPEST CONDOLENCES GO OUT TO YOU AND ALL THE LEVINS.
>> THANK YOU. THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> IT'S PRETTY MINIMAL. THREE KG IS FOUR.
SO I WANTED TO THANK I WANTED TO THANK GOD AND OUR MOTHER FOR
BEING HERE TODAY. I WANTED TO THANK ALL THE
SUPERVISORS. THANK YOU.
ESPECIALLY TO SUPERVISOR JACKIE FIELD AND MILLER IN WRITING ME
SORRY. >> I KNOW, I KNOW ALL OF YOU
THINK I DON'T HAVE WORDS TO SAY A LOT BUT I JUST WANTED TO SAY
IN HONORING HIM IT'S AN HONOR FOR ME FOR HIM.
>> I WANT AT THE TIME FROM MY FAMILY EVERYBODY FOR THE RECORD
TO PREMIERE. GET IT GIVEN TO MY HUSBAND.
LOVE LOVELY HUSBAND. HE WAS SUCH A GREAT MAN.
>> HE IS. HE ALWAYS WILL BE.
HE WAS HE ALWAYS TAKE CARE OF US.
>> BUT NOT ONLY THE WHOLE COMMUNITY NO MATTER WHAT COLOR
OR WHAT AGE YOU WERE. HE WAS ALWAYS THERE FOR
EVERYBODY TRYING TO LEAVE AND HELP EACH OTHER AND HELP
EVERYBODY. >> AND I JUST KIND OF SAY
SOMETHING THAT THAT WORK THAT HE LOVES TO SAY ALL THE TIME
AND ESPECIALLY TO ME AND ALL HIS COMMUNITY AND FAMILIES
AND FRIENDS. HE ALWAYS SAYS LESS TALK
AND MORE ACTIONS. SHOW ME.
SHOW US. SHOW ME THAT YOU CAN DO IT.
DON'T JUST SIT ON ME. YOU'RE GOING TO DO IT.
JUST DO IT. AND ALSO HE ALWAYS SAYS HE
LOVES EVERYBODY. HE LOVES ALL OF US.
AND THANK YOU. I HAVE NO WORDS TO SAY.
>> BUT IN HONORING HIS LEGACY WE WILL CONTINUE.
ME, MY FAMILY, MY KIDS AND MY FAMILY.
THIS THIS GROUP AND MY FAMILY ALL MY COMMUNITY FAMILY WHO
WILL NOT LET IT LET ME DOWN UNTIL NOW THAT I WANTED TO
THANK FOR HOLDING ME. SINCE THEY HEAR HE PASSED IT IS
YOURS. >> THINK OF IT AS YES IT'S
OKAY. I
AND FROM DISTRICT EIGHT AND STAR.
COME ON UP. >> I DON'T LIKE THIS ONE AT ALL
. >> TODAY COLLEAGUES, I'M
PRESENTING A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO AARON STARR WHO
RECENTLY RETIRED AFTER TWO DECADES OF SERVICE IN THE
CITY'S PLANNING DEPARTMENT. AARON FIRST JOINED THE
DEPARTMENT AS AN INTERN IN JUNE OF 2001.
>> HE LATER BECAME A PLANNER ON THE NORTHWEST QUADRANT TEAM OF
THE NEIGHBORHOOD PLANNING DIVISION WHERE HE REVIEWED
DEVELOPMENT PROPOSALS. IN 2013 HE JOINED THE
LEGISLATIVE AFFAIRS TEAM BEFORE BEING PROMOTED TO MANAGER OF
LEGISLATIVE AFFAIRS IN 2014. IN THIS ROLE HE REGULARLY
REPRESENTED THE PLANNING COMMISSION AT THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AND LAND USE COMMITTEE HEARINGS AND PROVIDED
WEEKLY LEGISLATIVE REPORTS TO THE PLANNING COMMISSION.
>> AMONG AARON'S MANY ACHIEVEMENTS IS THE CODE
REORGANIZATION PROJECT WHICH STANDARDIZED DEFINITIONS ACROSS
THE PLANNING CODE AND INTRODUCED A UNIFIED ZONING
CONTROL TABLE FOR ALL ZONING DISTRICTS.
STREAMLINING INTERPRETATION AND APPLICATION FOR PLANNERS,
DEVELOPERS AND THE PUBLIC. HE OFFERED THE CANNABIS LAND
USE CONTROLS HELPING TO STEER A REGULATORY FRAMEWORK FOR
CANNABIS BUSINESSES IN THE CITY.
HE DRAFTED THE RESTAURANT RATIONALIZATION ORDINANCE WHICH
REDUCED THE NUMBER OF EATING AND DRINKING ESTABLISHMENT
DEFINITIONS FROM 13 TO 3 SIGNIFICANTLY SIMPLIFYING THE
PERMITTING PROCESS. HE ALSO PLAYED A KEY ROLE
IN DRAFTING PROPOSITION H AND THE CONSTRAINTS REDUCTION
ORDINANCE AIMED AT REDUCING BARRIERS TO ECONOMIC
DEVELOPMENT AND HOUSING. AND BEYOND ALL THAT HE HAS OVER
THE COURSE OF HIS CAREER COMPLETED NEARLY 700 INDIVIDUAL
PLANNING DEPARTMENT CASES. AARON HOLDS A MASTER'S DEGREE
IN CITY AND REGIONAL PLANNING FROM CAL POLY SAN LUIS OBISPO
AND A BACHELOR OF ARTS AND HUMANITIES FROM SAN
FRANCISCO STATE WITH CONCENTRATIONS IN ARCHITECTURE
IN ARCHITECTURAL AND ART HISTORY.
>> THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S DECEMBER 18TH PROCLAMATION
HONORING AARON ON THE OCCASION OF HIS RETIREMENT CELEBRATED
HIM AS A PLANNING POLYMATH WHO WIELDS A DEEP KNOWLEDGE OF THE
PLANNING CODE A DEFT APPROACH TO POLICY AND A KEEN
UNDERSTANDING OF LAND USE LEGISLATION.
INDEED, AARON, THE CITY HAS BEEN FORTUNATE TO HAVE YOU
THESE LAST 20 YEARS AND I FEEL FORTUNATE TO HAVE BEEN ABLE TO
WORK WITH YOU THESE LAST SEVEN AND A HALF AND TO HAVE BEEN
ABLE TO REPRESENT YOU AS A CONSTITUENT.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. AND BEFORE YOU SPEAK I ALSO
HAVE COLLEAGUES WHO WANT TO SAY NICE THINGS ABOUT YOU.
AND WE WILL START WITH SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
>> THANK YOU, AARON AND REALLY SORRY TO SEE YOU GO.
I JUST WANTED TO COMMENT ON WORKING WITH YOU HAS BEEN
REALLY AMAZING OVER THE LAST YEAR BECAUSE YOU TAUGHT ME SO
MUCH ON WHAT I THOUGHT WAS THE SIMPLEST LEGISLATION TO EVER
WORK ON THE SHARED HOUSING REFORM ACT ABOUT MAKING IT
LEGAL FOR MORE THAN FIVE PEOPLE TO LIVE TOGETHER.
BUT I THINK WHAT YOU SHOWED ME AND HELPED US ON OUR FIRST
LEGISLATION END UP BEING THE LAST LEGISLATION WE ENDED UP
PASSING WAS THAT THERE ARE A LOT OF UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES
IN OUR HOUSING CODE IS COMPLEX. IT'S LIKE A GAME OF JENGA.
WE TRY TO CHANGE ONE THING AND IT ENDS UP CHANGING MANY
OTHERS AND THAT TO BE RESPONSIBLE LEGISLATORS WE HAVE
TO ACCOUNT FOR ALL THOSE POTENTIAL EXTERNALITIES AND I
THINK REALLY APPRECIATED YOUR PATIENCE OVER THAT ENTIRE YEAR
PROCESS OF WALKING US THROUGH HOW TO MINIMIZE THOSE
UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES AND WORK THROUGH A FRAMEWORK
THAT IS BOTH GOVERNMENT AND ROLE BUT ALSO DOES THE
ORIGINAL INTENT OF THE LAW. SO I THINK IN PARTNERING WITH
YOU ON THAT AND THROUGH THE REZONING PROCESS AND SO MANY
OTHER PIECES OF LEGISLATION, I REALLY APPRECIATED YOU ALWAYS
FIGURING OUT THE INTENT OF WHAT WE'RE TRYING TO ACCOMPLISH
AND THEN ALSO SEEING HOW WE CAN MAKE SURE THAT IT'S ACTUALLY
POSSIBLE TO ADMINISTER AND BEING IN COMPLIANT WITH OUR
COMPONENTS OF OUR LAW AS WELL. SO YOU'VE BEEN A GREAT PARTNER
TO OUR OFFICE AND REALLY SAD TO SEE YOU GO BUT REALLY THANK YOU
FOR HELPING US THROUGH THIS THROUGH THIS YEAR AND WISHING
THE BEST ON THE NEXT STEPS AS WELL.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU. SO MR. START KNOWS HE'S LIKE MY
FAVORITE. I'M SO SORRY TO SEE YOU GO.
>> I HAVE HAD THE GREAT PLEASURE AND HONOR OF WORKING
WITH YOU FOR SO MANY YEARS FROM THE TIME I WAS ON THE PLANNING
COMMISSION AND NOW AT LINDY'S AND TRANSPORTATION AND ASIDE
FROM THE THINGS THAT PEOPLE SAY ABOUT YOU, YOUR KEEN INTELLECT
,YOUR DEEP KNOWLEDGE OF THE PLANNING CODE, YOUR DIDACTIC
PROCESS AND YOU KNOW JUST DEEP CONTRIBUTION TO OUR CITY, I
HAVE ALWAYS JUST REALLY ADMIRED YOUR SENSE OF HUMOR.
YOU ARE ONE OF THE FUNNIEST PEOPLE I'VE EVER MET
AND SOMETHING THAT I SAID IN MY REMARKS OF THE PLANNING
COMMISSION THAT I HEARD YOUR COWORKERS TEASE YOU ABOUT ALL
DAY WAS YOU KNOW THAT YOU ARE THE MASTER OF A SUBTLE SHADE.
>> AND THAT HAS HELPED YOU IN THE POLITICAL PROCESS WHICH
IS NOT ABOUT THE DEEP KNOWLEDGE OF THE CODE BUT ACTUALLY BEING
ABLE TO NAVIGATE, YOU KNOW, ALL OF THESE PERSONALITIES
AND BEING ABLE TO DO THE RIGHT THING AND DO IT WITH GRACE
AND ELEGANCE. AND SO I AM SO DEEPLY GRATEFUL
THAT YOU HAVE BEEN IN THIS POSITION AND HELPED US DO ALL
OF THE GREAT PROGRESS THAT WE'VE DONE IN TERMS OF LAND USE
HERE IN THE CITY. I'M SO SORRY TO HEAR YOU GO BUT
I KNOW YOU'LL STILL BE AROUND AND HOPEFULLY WILL RUN UNTIL
EACH OTHER ON THE STREET SOMEWHERE DISTRICT EIGHT
AND YOU WILL BE AROUND OUR CITY STILL BEING YOU STILL BEING
FUNNY AND WONDERFUL. SO THANK YOU FRIEND FOR ALL THE
TIME YOU'VE SPENT WITH US AND YOUR DEEP CONTRIBUTIONS TO
OUR CITY SUPERVISOR DORSI THANK YOU PRESIDENT EDELMAN AARON,
CONGRATULATIONS ON A WELL-DESERVED RETIREMENT AND A
DISTINGUISHED CAREER IN CITY SERVICE.
I KNOW YOU'VE BEEN AN INCREDIBLY VALUABLE ASSET TO
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT BUT YOU'VE ALSO BEEN A TRULY
VALUABLE PARTNER TO OUR OFFICES AND HELPING US NAVIGATE THE
LEGISLATIVE PROCESS. MY LEGISLATIVE STAFF HAS
LEARNED SO MUCH FROM YOUR EXPERTISE AS HAVE I ON ALL OF
OUR EFFORTS AND MY TEAM WANTED ME TO EXPRESS THEIR
APPRECIATION IN ADDITION TO MY OWN.
YOU'VE BEEN A GREAT THOUGHT PARTNER AND I REALLY APPRECIATE
THE GUIDANCE THAT YOU HAVE OFFERED PARTICULARLY ON SOME OF
MY OFFER OFFICERS EARLIEST PROJECTS INCLUDING THE
NIGHTTIME ENTERTAINMENT ZONE IN SOMA AND THE ARTICLE EIGHT
CODE REORGANIZATION. SO THANK YOU SO MUCH
AND CONGRATULATIONS. THANK YOU AND STAR THE FLOOR IS
YOURS. THANK YOU ESPECIALLY SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN FOR SPONSORING THE COMMENDATION.
THIS IS A REAL HONOR SO SOME OF YOU MAY BE WONDERING HOW I CAN
RETIRE AT THE YOUNG AGE OF 50 WITH ONLY 20 YEARS OF SERVICE.
THE ANSWER IS SIMPLE I'M A GOOD PLANNER.
>> I TRULY THOUGH THANK YOU FOR THIS RECOGNITION OVER THE YEARS
I SPENT COUNTLESS HOURS SITTING IN THAT BOX WAITING FOR AN
APPEAL WHILE THIS BOARD RECOGNIZED EXTRAORDINARY PEOPLE
AND COMMUNITY LEADERS TO NOW BE STANDING HERE.
JOINING THAT GROUP IS DEEPLY MEANINGFUL TO ME.
I GREW UP IN MOUNTAIN VIEW AND SAN FRANCISCO WAS ALWAYS
THE CITY. IT HAD A MYSTIQUE, AN ENERGY
AND A SENSE OF POSSIBILITY THAT SUBURBAN LIFE AS GOOD AS IT WAS
JUST DIDN'T HAVE MOUNTAIN VIEW A WONDERFUL PLACE TO GROW UP.
IT'S GOT GREAT WEATHER LIKE REALLY GOOD WEATHER PARKS
AND SCHOOLS BUT SUBURBS CAN BE ISOLATING CARS AND DETACHED
HOMES CREATE DISTANCE BOTH PHYSICAL AND SOCIAL.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS TAUGHT ME SOMETHING DIFFERENT.
THIS IS WHERE I FELL IN LOVE WITH CITIES WHERE I LEARNED
THAT THE BUILT ENVIRONMENT SHAPES HOW WE LIVE TOGETHER,
HOW WE MEET, HOW WE CONNECT, HOW CULTURE FORMS, THE
IMPORTANCE OF PUBLIC SPACE AND THIRD PLACES THE SIMPLE JOY
OF WALKING TO MEET YOUR DAILY NEEDS AND RUNNING INTO YOUR
NEIGHBOR OR FRIEND ALONG THE WAY BECAUSE OF THAT BEING ABLE
TO NOT ONLY LIVE HERE BUT TO SERVE THIS CITY HAS BEEN BOTH A
PRIVILEGE AND AN HONOR. I'VE WORKED ON MORE ORDINANCES
THAN I CAN COUNT SOME BETTER THAN OTHERS BUT IF I CAN CLAIM
ONE ACCOMPLISHMENT FROM MY TIME HERE IT'S THIS THAT I HELPED
IN SOME SMALL WAY MAKE A CITY I LOVE.
I'M VERY DEEPLY A LITTLE BETTER .
I CAN'T LEAVE THIS PODIUM WITHOUT THINKING MY COLLEAGUES
AT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT MANY OF WHOM ARE HERE RIGHT OVER
THERE. THANK YOU.
>> AND I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY HUSBAND BILL WEBER WHO'S HERE
TODAY. HE'S BEEN WITH ME THROUGH A LOT
WHEN I WENT TO GRAD SCHOOL AND MY ENTIRE TENURE HERE AT
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT. SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH, BILL
AND ESPECIALLY WANT TO THANK ANGELA CAVALLO AND THE CLERK OF
THE BOARDS OFFICE WITHOUT WHICH I WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN ABLE TO
DO MY JOB SUCCESSFULLY. THIS BOARD IS FORTUNATE IN MANY
WAYS BUT THE CLERK STAFF TRULY TOPS THE LIST.
ANGELA, ALISA, ERIKA AND JOHN AND MANY OTHERS THANK YOU FOR
YOUR KINDNESS, YOUR PROFESSIONALISM AND YOUR
EXTRAORDINARY PATIENCE. THANK YOU AGAIN FOR THIS HONOR
AND FOR THE GRACE YOU'VE SHOWN ME OVER THE YEARS.
WHATEVER COMES NEXT FOR ME I KNOW THIS I WILL ALWAYS BE
GRATEFUL TO THIS CITY AND I HOPE TO CONTINUE FINDING WAYS
BIG OR SMALL TO BE OF SERVICE TO MY COMMUNITY AND TO SAN
FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU.
AARON, COME ON INTO THE WELL WHAT?
I'M A GOLFER. WOW.
SMILE
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, SHALL WE GO TO OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL
ORDER PLEASE CALL ITEMS 24 AND 25 TOGETHER ITEMS 24 AND 25
COMBINED WERE SCHEDULED PURSUANT TO A MOTION NUMBER M
20 5-1 31 CONTAINED IN FILE NUMBER 25 1221 APPROVED BY THE
BOARD ON DECEMBER 16TH 2025 FOR THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO
CONVENE IN A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE FOR A PUBLIC HEARING
TODAY JANUARY 27TH, 2026 FOR THIS SPECIAL ORDER AT 3 P.M. TO
CONSIDER AN ORDINANCE ITEM 25 TO APPROVE AMENDMENTS TO THE
REDEVELOPMENT PLAN FOR THE MISSION BAY SOUTH REDEVELOPMENT
PROJECT TO INCREASE THE MAXIMUM BUILDING HEIGHT FROM ONE 60FT
TO TWO 50FT 250FT AND TO INCREASE THE NUMBER OF DWELLING
UNITS PERMITTED ON THE NORTHERN ONE HALF OF BLOCK FOUR EAST
ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK NUMBER 8711.
LOT NUMBER 029 CAPITAL B FOR THE DEVELOPMENT OF AN
AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
SO WE'RE NOW SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE TO
CONSIDER THE AMENDMENT TO THE REDEVELOPMENT PLAN FOR THE
MISSION BAY SOUTH REDEVELOPMENT PROJECT BLOCK FOR EAST.
AND IT LOOKS SUMMARIZED DORSEY LIKE YOU MIGHT HAVE SOME
OPENING COMMENTS FOR THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT COLLEAGUES
ANY TIME THE CITY SEEKS TO AMEND THE MASTER PLAN FOR ONE
OF OUR REDEVELOPMENT AREAS WE MUST SIT AS A COMMITTEE OF THE
WHOLE FOR A HEARING ON IT. AND SO I APPRECIATE YOUR
INDULGENCE FOR THIS HEARING ON TODAY'S REQUESTED AMENDMENT TO
INCREASE OUR CAPACITY FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN MISSION
BAY. THE AMENDMENT BEFORE US TODAY
WOULD INCREASE THE HEIGHT ON BLOCK FOUR AND INCREASE THE
NUMBER OF ALLOWABLE AFFORDABLE UNITS.
THIS AREA IS JUST ACROSS THE STREET FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO
POLICE DEPARTMENT HEADQUARTERS WHERE I ONCE WORKED SO I'M
EXCITED TO SEE THE CONTINUING PROGRESS FOR THE NEIGHBORHOOD
AND I'M INCREDIBLY PROUD TO REPRESENT MISSION BAY.
GENERALLY IT HAS BECOME A THRIVING TRANSIT ORIENTED MIXED
USE SOCIOECONOMIC AKILI DIVERSE NEIGHBORHOOD IN MY VIEW IT'S A
NEIGHBORHOOD THAT'S NOT SOLELY IMPORTANT FOR THE 31% SURGE
IN SALES TAX REVENUE IT HAS BEEN DELIVERING TO OUR BALANCE
SHEET AS ONE OF ONLY FOUR CITY NEIGHBORHOODS TO EXCEED
PRE-PANDEMIC RETAIL SPENDING LEVELS.
IT'S ALSO IMPORTANT BECAUSE IT'S A TEMPLATE FOR A TRULY
INCLUSIVE 21ST CENTURY URBANISM .
THE CHANGES WE'LL BE HEARING ABOUT TODAY WILL FURTHER THAT
VISION AND ADVANCE THE CITY'S AFFORDABILITY AND HOUSING GOALS
AND I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT AND I WILL NOW I GUESS THROUGH
THE CHAIR TURN IT OVER TO PHILIP WONG FROM OCA.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH SUPERVISOR DORSEY BOARD
PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS PHILIP WONG. I AM A DEVELOPMENT SPECIALIST
WITH THE HOUSING TEAM AT THE OFFICE OF COMMUNITY INVESTMENT
AND INFRASTRUCTURE. >> AND THE REQUEST BEFORE YOU
TODAY IS TO APPROVE AN AMENDMENT TO THE MISSION BAY
SOUTH REDEVELOPMENT PLAN TO INCREASE UNIT COUNT
AND BUILDING HEIGHT TO MAKE CONSISTENCY FINDINGS WITH THE
GENERAL PLAN AND THE EIGHT PRIORITY POLICIES OF THE
PLANNING CODE. ACTIONS THAT WILL FACILITATE
THE DEVELOPMENT OF 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN PHASE TWO
OF MISSION BAY SOUTH BLOCK FOR EAST.
>> THIS NEXT SLIDE IS JUST A BIT OF BACKGROUND ON THE
PROJECT AREA AND THE PROJECT SITE WITHIN ITS CONTEXT BLOCK
FOR USES LOCATED IN THE MISSION BAY SOUTH REDEVELOPMENT PROJECT
AREA AND WAS CREATED IN 1998 TO EXPAND AFFORDABLE HOUSING
DEVELOPMENT AND ADDRESS BLIGHTS ENVISIONED AS A MIXED INCOME
AND MIXED USE COMMUNITY. IT'S NEARLY COMPLETE WITH BLOCK
FOUR EAST AND BEING ONE OF TWO REMAINING HOUSING DEVELOPMENT
SITES OF THE 1218 AFFORDABLE UNITS ALLOWED IN THE PROJECT
AREA 1053 ARE COMPLETE AND THE REMAINING 165 WILL BE
CONSTRUCTED IN THE FIRST PHASE OF THE PROJECT.
>> OCI ISSUED A REQUEST FOR QUALIFICATIONS IN NOVEMBER OF
2023 AND SELECTED CURTIS DEVELOPMENT AND BAYVIEW SENIOR
SERVICES AS THE DEVELOPERS OWNERS AND OPERATORS OF THE
PROJECTS. >> AND ON NOVEMBER 18TH OF 2025
OCI COMMISSION PROVIDED MAJOR APPROVALS FOR THE PHASE ONE
AND PHASE TWO PROJECTS INCLUDING BASIC CONCEPT
AND SCHEMATIC DESIGNS IN ADDITION TO AMENDMENTS TO
THE MISSION BAY SOUTH DESIGN FOR DEVELOPMENT A MAJOR PHASE
REDEVELOPMENT PLAN AND OWNER PARTICIPATION AGREEMENT TO
AGAIN FACILITATE BOTH PROJECTS. ON DECEMBER 11TH OF 2025 THE
PLANNING COMMISSION ALSO RECOMMENDED APPROVAL OF THE
REDEVELOPMENT PLAN AMENDMENT AND PROVIDED GENERAL PLAN
CONSISTENCY FINDINGS. >> AS PART OF THESE PROJECT
APPROVALS OCI DETERMINED THE PROJECTS EXEMPT FROM CEQA UNDER
ASSEMBLY BILL 1449 AB 1449 WENT INTO EFFECT IN JANUARY OF 2024
EXEMPTING 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECTS FROM SEQUA
INCLUDING THOSE WITH PLAN AMENDMENTS.
>> THIS SLIDE DETAILS THE AMENDMENTS TO THE REDEVELOPMENT
PLAN. THE AMENDMENT IS LIMITED TO THE
PHASE TWO PROJECT SITE OR THE NORTHERN HALF OF BLOCK FOUR
EAST. THE FIRST AMENDMENT IS
INCREASING THE NUMBER OF ALLOWABLE AFFORDABLE DWELLING
UNITS BY 250. THE SECOND IS INCREASING THE
MAXIMUM TOWER HEIGHT FROM 160FT TO 250FT TO ACCOMMODATE THE
INCREASED NUMBER OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING UNITS WITH A RANGE OF
LARGER FAMILY SIZE UNITS. THIS SLIDE SHOWS THE BLOCK FOR
EACH PROJECT IN CONTEXT WITH THE WELL DEVELOPED MISSION BAY
SOUTH REDEVELOPMENT AREA AND IN CLOSE PROXIMITY TO THE
DEVELOPMENT IN PROGRESS AT MISSION ROCK.
FOR EASES WITH WITH IS WITHIN A 15 MINUTE WALK OF LOCAL
AND REGIONAL TRANSIT THE NEW MISSION BAY SCHOOL WHICH IS
OPENING LATER THIS SUMMER MISSION BAY PARKS ENTERTAINMENT
AND RETAIL. THIS SLIDE IS A RENDERING OF
THE PROJECT HIGHLIGHTING THE PHASE ONE PROJECT LOOKING TO
THE NORTHWEST. AND THIS RENDERING HIGHLIGHTS
THE PHASE TWO PROJECT. >> THIS SLIDE SHOWS RENDERINGS
DEMONSTRATING THE VIEW OF THE LOBBY ENTRANCES OF EACH OF THE
PROJECTS AT THE CORNERS WITH HIGH VISIBILITY AND GROUND
FLOOR ACTIVATION. >> THE OVERALL PROJECTS WILL
PROVIDE A TOTAL OF 398 UNITS OF WHICH 80 UNITS WILL BE SET
ASIDE FOR FAMILIES EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS ANTICIPATED TO BE
SUPPORTED BY THE LOCAL OPERATING SUBSIDY PROGRAM OR
LOSS FOR EAST WILL SERVE HOUSEHOLDS AT A RANGE OF INCOME
LEVELS TO ACCOMMODATE OUR PRIORITY CERTIFICATE OF
PREFERENCE HOLDERS. THE UNIT MIX IS ROUGHLY 25% ONE
BEDROOM, 50%, TWO BEDROOM AND 25% THREE BEDROOM UNITS.
NOTABLY PHASE TWO WILL ALSO HAVE LARGER FAMILY SIZE UNITS
WITH FIVE FOUR BEDROOM UNITS AND TWO FIVE BEDROOM UNITS.
BOTH PROJECTS WILL ALSO PROVIDE SECURED CLASS ONE BICYCLE
PARKING AS WELL AS ONSITE VEHICULAR PARKING.
>> AND THIS LAST SLIDE IS AN OVERVIEW OF OUR SCHEDULE
CONCURRENT WITH APPROVAL OF THE REDEVELOPMENT PLAN AMENDMENT
ORDINANCE FOR PHASE TWO. THE DEVELOPERS WILL PURSUE
FINANCING THROUGH OUT THIS YEAR FOR PHASE ONE WITH THE GOAL OF
STARTING CONSTRUCTION IN EARLY 2027 WITH COMPLETION IN 2020
NINE AND PHASE TWO WILL PURSUE FINANCING IN 2027 WITH
CONSTRUCTION STARTING IN EARLY 2028 AND COMPLETION IN 2030.
SO I'M JOINED BY OUR WONDERFUL DEVELOPERS OCI CITY STAFF.
FOR ANY QUESTIONS THAT YOU MAY HAVE.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME AND CONSIDERATION.
>> THANK YOU AND I DO NOT SEE ANY COMMENTS OR QUESTIONS FROM
COLLEAGUES. SO MADAM CLERK, LET'S CALL FOR
PUBLIC COMMENT ON THIS MATTER. >> ALL RIGHT.
IF YOU ARE HERE TO PROVIDE GENERAL PUBLIC EXCUSE ME PUBLIC
COMMENT ON THIS MATTER, PLEASE STEP OVER TO YOUR RIGHT HAND
SIDE OF THE CHAMBER. >> HOW IS THIS GOING TO BE LONG
THIS MEETING HERE BECAUSE OF PUBLIC COMMENTS AND WAITING.
>> OKAY. SO YOU ARE BUILDING YOU WANT TO
BUILD MORE RABBIT CAGES. THAT'S A BLACK ROACH.
>> OKAY, LOOK, IT'S ABSOLUTE INCOMPETENCE AND BUT GO FOR IT.
>> I MEAN TAKE THE MONEY. WE WILL FIND YOU AND WE'LL FIND
EVERYONE WHEN THE TIME COMES. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. >> WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES. >> THANK YOU.
GOOD AFTERNOON, COMMISSIONER. MY NAME IS DEMETRIUS WILLIAMS.
I'M THE PRESIDENT OF THE SAN FRANCISCO HYPER LOCAL BUILDING
TRADES CONTRACTORS COLLECTIVE. AND WE'VE BEEN MONITORING THIS
PROJECT ALONG WITH GOING TO OCI AND TALKING TO THE OWNERS
AND THE DEVELOPERS HERE. WE SUPPORT THE PROJECT BUT WE
ALSO WANT TO ENCOURAGE THE YOU KNOW, THE DEVELOPERS TO INCLUDE
COMMUNITY CONTRACTORS ON THE DEVELOPMENT PHASES.
WE WERE OVER HERE BEEN AXON AND THE BAIN AND TRYING TO GET
THE SENIOR CITIZEN TO UNDERSTAND HOW IMPORTANT IT IS
TO KEEP CONTRACTORS FROM THE COMMUNITY INVESTED AND INVOLVED
IN THE COMMUNITY ESPECIALLY WHEN WE DEVELOP IN IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD. THIS IS SUPPOSED TO BE
SOMETHING AFFORDABLE FOR THE COMMUNITY.
SO YOU SHOULD BE USING COMMUNITY CONTRACTORS
ESPECIALLY KNOWING THE IMPACT THAT IT'LL DO FOR THE CITY.
WE'RE TRYING TO INSOURCE OUR RESOURCES AND KEEP IT IN THE
CITY, NOT OUTSOURCE IT UNLESS SOMEBODY ELSE DEVELOPER GET
RICH AND WE STAY POOR IN OUR OWN COMMUNITY.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> MR. DE COSTA, WELCOME.
>> WELL OF SUPERVISORS THIS IS A TIME WHEN WE USE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING IN A VERY FUNNY WAY. AFFORDABLE TO WHOM?
AFFORDABLE TO WHOM? >> NOW BESIDES HAVING THESE
TRICKY THINGS WHERE YOU HAVE TO GET INTO A LOTTERY AND GORDILLO
KNOWS HOW TO DO THAT AND DISTRIBUTE THE HOUSING.
WE ARE NOT TAKING CARE OF OUR PEOPLE.
IN THE SOUTHEAST SECTOR OF THIS CITY WE SHOULD BE ASHAMED OF
OURSELVES THAT WE HAVE YOUNG PEOPLE SITTING DOWN
AND WATCHING OTHERS COME FROM COLORADO, FROM PHENIX, FROM
GORDILLO KNOWS WHERE AND WORKING IN OUR COMMUNITY
AND WANTS TO KNOW WHERE YOUR SUPERVISORS SHOULD GO INTO THE
COMMUNITY AND SEE FOR YOURSELVES HOW OUR COMMUNITY IS
SUFFERING. >> IT'S A SHAME THAT WE HAVE SO
MANY DISEASES IN OUR AREA. THEY TAKE SURVEYS, THEY GOT
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS. THE DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH BUT
THEY DON'T INVEST IN OUR COMMUNITY.
>> SO THE PRESIDENT I KNOW YOU FOR A LONG TIME AND IT IS TIME
THAT WE DO WRITE OUR PAPER CANNOT SUFFER ANYMORE.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. >> THANK YOU, MR. DE CASTRO FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. HOLD YOUR APPLAUSE PLEASE.
THERE IS NO SOUNDS OF APPLAUSE EITHER FOR OR AGAINST THE
SPEAKER. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. WELCOME.
HI. MY NAME IS ARI HARRIS AND I'M
HERE FROM DISTRICT TEN. I'M IN FULL SUPPORT OF THE
CONTRACTORS THAT YOU NEED TO BE A PART OF THE SOLUTION AND A
PART OF THE UPWARD MOBILITY AND THE ECONOMICS THAT ARE
CURRENTLY BEING CUT THAT ARE COMING INTO OUR DISTRICT WHICH
IS DISTRICT TEN. >> ALSO I WOULD LIKE TO TO
PLEAD WITH YOU GUYS TO ALSO REVISIT TO BE MORE TAX CREDIT
YOU NEED A MODEL FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING BECAUSE THAT PROGRAM IS
DEAD PROGRAM IS DESIGNED TO GET YOU TO MARKET RATE RENT
INDIVIDUALLY PRICING YOU PRICING FAMILIES OUT.
AND WHAT HAPPENS IS THAT YOU CREATE MORE HOMELESSNESS AMONG
SINGLE PARENT HOMES AND JUST FAMILIES IN GENERAL BECAUSE
THEY HAVE TO START ALL OVER AND THE WAITING PROCESS
IN BETWEEN THAT THAT TIME WHEN YOU ARE PRICED PRICED OUT TO
FIND ANOTHER UNIT THERE'S ANOTHER WAITING LIST AND THEN
IT'S THAT LONG STRETCH OF TIME. SO WHAT HAPPENED TO THE LOW
INCOME HOUSING UNIT MODEL? >> THE THIRD PERCENTAGE FOR OUR
LOW INCOME EARNERS THAT WHEN YOUR INCOME DROPS DROPPED ARE
YOU LOSE A JOB BECAUSE YOU'RE WORKING WORKING TWO JOBS
AND GOT TO HUSTLE NINE TIMES OUT OF TEN JUST TO AFFORD TO
LIVE IN THIS CITY. SO WHAT WE ARE DOING IS
CREATING MORE HOMELESSNESS. WE ARE PUSHING PEOPLE OUT OF
THE CITY IN THE 30 PERCENTILE HOUSING MODEL FROM THE SAN
FRANCISCO HOUSING AUTHORITY WHEN IT WAS IN EXISTENCE
AND IT'S GETTING IN THAT'S GETTING TAKEN AWAY.
>> THERE WERE PEOPLE THAT WERE EITHER YOUNG PARENTS AND PEOPLE
THAT WERE COMING UP OR FINDING THEIR WAY IN THIS IN THIS WORLD
AS FAR AS ECONOMIC GROWTH. AND THEN WHEN THE INCOME
DROPPED THEIR RENT DROPPED TO ACCOMMODATE THEIR RENT, WHEN
THEIR RENT INCREASED THEIR RENT THEIR RENT INCREASE BUT IT KEPT
PEOPLE STABILIZED AND PEOPLE HOUSED UNTIL THEY FIGURED OUT
THEIR LIFE PATH. SO THAT'S SOMETHING I WOULD
WANT YOU TO TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION AND ALSO THINK
ABOUT WE HAVE THIS SEGMENT OF OUR COMMUNITIES THAT MEET THESE
THAT MEET THESE INCOME RANGES BUT DON'T NECESSARILY MEET THE
BENCHMARK TAX CREDIT CREDIT STANDARDS FOR FOR INCOME.
>> YOU UNDERSTAND WHAT I'M SAYING?
SO WE GOT GOT A HUGE PART OF OUR COMMUNITIES THAT ARE BEING
LEFT OUT OF THAT PROCESS AS FAR AS BEING ABLE TO AFFORD TO LIVE
IN THE CITY, STAY IN THIS CITY AND BE FLUID IN THE CITY.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS DENNIS WILLIAMS JR
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE FILLMORE COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT
CORPORATION AND A LOCAL SAN FRANCISCO REAL ESTATE
DEVELOPER. I STOOD TODAY IN THE RALLY WITH
THE LABOR UNIONS I SUPPORT. I'M ALSO AM A MEMBER OF THE
S.F. HYPER LOCAL BUILDING TRADES CONTRACTORS COLLECTIVE.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS REPEATEDLY COMMITTED TO EQUITY AND IN
AND I SUPPORT OCI PROJECT SAN FRANCISCO HAS REPEATEDLY
COMMITTED TO EQUITY AND PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE INVESTMENT.
HOWEVER DEVELOPER LEVEL PARTICIPATION OWNERSHIP,
CO-DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY AND LOCAL TERM ECONOMIC
PARTICIPATION REMAIN LARGELY ABSENT FROM MAJOR CAPITAL
PROJECTS ESPECIALLY THOSE LOCATED IN IMPACTED HISTORICAL
BLACK NEIGHBORHOODS AROUND THE AROUND THE CITY.
PROTECTION OF FREEDOM WAS THIS HAS BECOME COMMON PRACTICE EVEN
WHEN WE HAVE BEEN INVOLVED FOR YEARS IN THE PLANNING
AND ENTITLEMENT PROCESSES. >> SAN FRANCISCO SHOULD REQUIRE
CLEAR ENFORCEABLE PATHWAYS FOR LOCAL MINORITY LED DEVELOPERS
AND CONSTRUCTION FIRMS TO PARTICIPATE IN DEVELOPMENT
REHABILITATION AND SEISMIC RETROFIT SCOPES.
ALSO OWNERSHIP DEVELOPMENT PARTNERS WHERE APPROPRIATE WE
MUST ALIGN ACQUISITIONS AND RENOVATION DECISIONS WITH
COMMUNITY STABLE STABILIZATION GOALS.
SCUSE ME SO PUBLIC INVESTMENT IS NOT UNINTENTIONALLY
ACCELERATE DISPLACEMENT OR EXCLUDE COMMUNITIES ROOTED
ENTITIES. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. IF YOU ARE HERE TO PROVIDE
COMMENTS ON THE AMENDMENTS TO THE REDEVELOPMENT PLAN FOR
MISSION BAY SOUTH REDEVELOPMENT PROJECT PLEASE THIS IS YOUR
OPPORTUNITY TO ADDRESS THE BOARD.
STEP OVER TO YOUR RIGHT. ARE THERE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS?
>> OKAY, MR. PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK PUBLIC
COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED AND THIS MATTER HAS BEEN HEARD AND IS
NOW FILED AND WE CAN CONSIDER ITEM 25.
MADAM CLERK CAN YOU CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 25 ON ITEM 25
SUPERVISOR CHERYL. >> HI CHERYL I SUPERVISOR FOR
WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISE HER CHAN I
CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN I MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
AND SUPERVISOR SAUDER SADR EITHER ARMY LEBANESE WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING.
>> AND WITH THAT MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL.
>> YES SUPERVISOR CHERYL IS FIRST UP TO INTRODUCE NEW
BUSINESS. COLLEAGUES TODAY I'D LIKE TO
ENDURE ADJOURN THIS MEETING IN MEMORY OF CHOATE CROCHETING
YAO WHO KNEW PASSED AWAY LAST WEEK AT THE AGE OF 107
IN NOVEMBER WE COMMENDED MRS. CHU AT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
HERE FOR HER AND HER FAMILY'S CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE CITY
AND AS ONE OF THE OLDEST SAN FRANCISCANS TO HAVE LIVED SHE
HELD GENERATIONS OF HER FAMILY TOGETHER WITH GRACE, WISDOM
AND DEVOTION. >> MRS. CHU WAS BORN
IN HONOLULU, HAWAII ON JUNE 9TH, 1918 THE FOURTH OF NINE
SIBLINGS TOGETHER WITH HER HUSBAND DR. CHU LANG CHUNG THEY
BUILT A BEAUTIFUL LIFE IN MACAO RAISING SEVEN CHILDREN
AND LATER BECOMING GRANDPARENTS AND GREAT GRANDPARENTS MANY
TIMES OVER 16 GRANDCHILDREN 19 GREAT GRANDCHILD JUNE WITH THE
FAMILY CONTINUING TO GROW HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, A MATRIARCH,
A WORLD TRAVELER AND A FORCE OF LOVE, HER LEGACY WILL CARRY ON
THROUGH HER NUMEROUS FAMILY MEMBERS INCLUDING DISTRICT TWO
RESIDENTS TERESA AND HOWARD HU AND LESLIE HU, FOUNDER OF
PIERCE'S PLEDGE. THE COURAGE AND COMPASSION THAT
DEFINE HER FAMILY ARE A REFLECTION OF THE SAME STRENGTH
THAT HAS CARRIED MRS. CHIU THROUGH MORE THAN A CENTURY OF
LIFE. ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO HER
FAMILY AND ALL WHO MOURN HER PASSING.
MAY WE ALL REMEMBER HER, HER LEGACY AND THE LIFE SHE
BEAUTIFULLY LIVED AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUPERVISOR
WALTON. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH, MADAM
CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE AN
IN MEMORIAM FOR MS.. RUTH VERLIN DAVIS.
RUTH VERLIN DAVIS. BORN VERLYN CROSS WAS BORN
OCTOBER 21ST, 1930 32 IN NEW ORLEANS.
SHE WAS RAISED IN GRETNA, LOUISIANA AS A SEVENTH CHILD OF
WILBERT AND LILLIAN CROSS. VERLIN ATTENDED ELEMENTARY
SCHOOL IN GRETNA AND GRADUATED FROM L.B. LANDRY HIGH SCHOOL
IN 1951. IN FEBRUARY OF THAT YEAR SHE
ACCEPTED CRISIS AS A PERSONAL SAVIOR.
THIS MARKED THE BEGINNING OF A LIFELONG JOURNEY OF FAITH
AND SERVICE. AFTER GRADUATING FROM HIGH
SCHOOL AND DEEPENING HER SPIRITUAL COMMITMENT, VERLIE
MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA IN MAY OF 1953.
THERE SHE REUNITED WITH PROVIDENCE BAPTIST CHURCH WHERE
REVEREND CLINTON ROGERS SERVED AS PASTOR.
ON JUNE 19TH, 1954, SHE WAS AT HER HIGH SCHOOL SWEETHEART
CURTIS CORNELIUS DAVIS. TOGETHER THEY HAD THREE
CHILDREN JUANITA AND DENISE ODETTE AND KURT CORNELIUS DAVID
VERNON WENT TO SCHOOL TO BECOME A NURSE AND WORKED AS A
LICENSED VOCATIONAL NURSE FOR 34 YEARS.
SHE WORKED IN THE MEDICAL INTENSIVE CARE UNIT AT ST
MARY'S HOSPITAL WHERE SHE CARED FOR PATIENTS WITH COMPASSION
AND SKILL AT THEIR MOST VULNERABLE TIMES.
BERLIN BECAME A DEDICATED AND ACTIVE MEMBER OF PROVIDENCE
BAPTIST CHURCH WHERE SHE WORKED HARD IN MANY AREAS OF CHURCH
LIFE AND MINISTRY INCLUDING SERVING AS A SUNDAY SCHOOL
SUPERINTENDENT AND TEACHER, A YOUTH DIRECTOR AND A
PARTICIPANT IN THE WOMEN'S MINISTRY.
ALWAYS WILLING TO SERVE WHEREVER NEEDED BEYOND BERLIN'S
HOME AND PROFESSION, SHE AND CURTIS LIVED OUT THEIR
FAITH THROUGH ACTION. THEY BEGAN BY SERVING HOT MEALS
AND HOUSE INDIVIDUALS ON SIXTH STREET FROM THE BACK OF AN OLD
CAMPER TRUCK. THAT GREW INTO A LARGER
MINISTRY. WHEN PROVIDENCE BAPTIST CHURCH
LAUNCHED ITS HOMELESS SHELTER PROGRAM, THIS EFFORT SOON
INVOLVED AND TRANSFORMED THE ENTIRE CONGREGATION.
RUTH VERLIN DAVIS LEFT A PERMANENT MARK ON THE LIVES SHE
TOUCHED. HER LEGACY OF FAITH PRAYER
SERVICE AND LOVE ENDURES THROUGH HER FAMILY CHURCH.
HER PATIENTS AND HER COMMUNITY GO TIME MOVES FORWARD.
NOTHING CAN ERASE THE IMPRINT SHE MADE THROUGH HER WORK, HER
SERVICE AND HER PERSONAL RELATIONSHIPS.
SHE MADE OTHERS FEEL SEEN, VALUED AND CARED FOR CREATING
AN EVERLASTING EXAMPLE OF FAITH LIVED THROUGH LOVE AND ACTION.
>> HER LIFE CONTINUES TO SPEAK HER PRAYER STILL ECHO AND HER
LEGACY REMAINS FOREVER IN OUR HEARTS.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON
SUPERVISOR WANG. YOU SAY SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR.
SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES, I AM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO REAFFIRM SAN
FRANCISCO'S COMMITMENT TO THE RIGHTS OF OUR TRANSGENDER
GENDER NONCONFORMING INTERSEX AND TO SPIRIT SAN FRANCISCANS
AND THEIR ACCESS TO MEDICALLY NECESSARY HEALTH CARE INCLUDING
GENDER AFFIRMING CARE. IN DECEMBER 2025, THE CENTERS
FOR MEDICARE AND MEDICAID SERVICES CMS ANNOUNCED TWO
PROPOSED RULES THAT WOULD RESTRICT ACCESS TO GENDER
AFFIRMING CARE FOR YOUTH BY ATTACKING HOSPITALS
PARTICIPATION IN MEDICARE AND MEDICAID AND FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT AND FEDERAL GOVERNMENT REIMBURSEMENTS FOR
YOUTH IN NEED OF MEDICAL CARE. LET US BE CLEAR LEGAL SCHOLARS
HAVE CONFIRMED THAT THERE IS NO CURRENT FEDERAL LAW THAT
PROHIBITS GENDER AFFIRMING CARE FOR CHILDREN AND ADOLESCENTS.
AND EVEN OUR ATTORNEY GENERAL ROB BONTA CONFIRMED THAT GENDER
AFFIRMING HEALTH CARE SERVICES AND GENDER AFFIRMING MENTAL
HEALTH CARE SERVICES ARE RIGHTS SECURE BY THE CONSTITUTION
AND LAWS OF CALIFORNIA. MEANWHILE, AS THESE RULES ARE
STILL BEING CONTEMPLATED, SOME INSURANCE CARRIERS AND HEALTH
CARE PROVIDERS LIKE KAISER HAVE ALREADY ANNOUNCED HALTING
GENDER AFFIRMING UV SURGERIES. >> THIS IS A CLEAR ATTACK ON
ONE OF OUR MOST VULNERABLE POPULATIONS IN OUR COMMUNITIES.
>> WE KNOW THAT CONTINUITY OF CARE IS CRITICAL FOR BOTH THE
PHYSICAL AND MENTAL WELL-BEING OF TG AND SEE EYE TO AS
CHILDREN AND YOUTH. THIS UNCERTAINTY OF CARE WILL
CAUSE LASTING HARM TO THEM AND THEIR FAMILIES AND OUR
ENTIRE COMMUNITY. THIS RESOLUTION DEMANDS THAT
HEALTH CARE PROVIDERS AND INSURANCE CARRIERS MUST
PRIORITIZE PEOPLE. THEY MUST ADHERE TO STATE
AND LOCAL LAWS AND STOP PRACTICES THAT WOULD
PREEMPTIVELY CANCEL PATIENTS ACCESS TO MEDICALLY NECESSARY
CARE. I WOULD LIKE TO EXTEND MY
DEEPEST GRATITUDE TO THE TRANS CAUCUS OF THE HARVEY MILK LGBTQ
DEMOCRATIC CLUB AND RAINBOW FAMILIES FOR CREATING THE
SOLUTION RESOLUTION WITH ME AND MY TEAM AND COLLEAGUES.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR EARLY CO-SPONSORS.
>> I'M VERY GRATEFUL. AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN.
SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU MADAM CLERK COLLEAGUE.
>> TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO CONDEMN THE
IMMINENT CLOSURE OF THE SAN FRANCISCO IMMIGRATION COURT.
SAN FRANCISCO IS ONE OF THE BIGGEST COURTS IN THE ENTIRE
IMMIGRATION COURT SYSTEM AND IT'S FOR MANY IMMIGRANTS
THE FIRST REAL CONTACT THEY HAVE WITH OUR NATION'S JUSTICE
SYSTEM TO PURSUE ASYLUM AND FIGHT DEPORTATION.
THE EXECUTIVE OFFICE OF IMMIGRATION REVIEW HAS REPORTED
THAT SAN FRANCISCO'S MONTGOMERY STREET COURT WOULD NOT RENEW
ITS LEASE AND IS SET TO SHUTTER BY JANUARY 2027.
>> THIS COURT WHICH BEGAN 2025 WITH 21 JUDGES NOW HAS JUST
FOUR REMAINING AFTER 13 WERE FIRE AND FOUR MORE RETIRE AT
THE END OF THIS YEAR AND THERE ARE 120,000 CASES DUE PENDING
THE FIRST IT DEPARTURE OF SO MANY IMMIGRANT JUDGES COMBINED
WITH THE CLOSURE OF THE SAN FRANCISCO COURT WILL HAVE A
CHILLING EFFECT ON THE FAIR ADJUDICATION OF CASES
AND ABILITY OF PEOPLE TO PURSUE ASYLUM.
IMMIGRATION LAW EXPERTS CONTEND THAT IF CASES ARE REASSIGNED TO
OUT OF SAN FRANCISCO ASYLUM SEEKERS COULD NOT BE WRAPPED.
>> ASYLUM SEEKERS COULD BE DROPPED OFF TO CRITICAL
SERVICES THE CITY'S LEGAL AID COMMUNITY PROVIDES.
I WANT TO THANK MY EARLY CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISOR WALTON
CHEN FIELDER. MALCOLM MOORE.
I LOOK FORWARD TO YOUR SUPPORT OF THIS IMPORTANT RESOLUTION AT
A TIME WHERE IT IS AS CRITICAL AS EVER TO PROTECT DUAL PROCESS
AND ACCESS FOR OUR NATION'S IMMIGRANTS TO OUR JUSTICE
SYSTEM AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, I AM TODAY CALLING
FOR A HEARING BEFORE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS PUBLIC SAFETY
AND NEIGHBORHOOD SERVICES COMMITTEE TO EXPLORE ISSUES
THAT MAY BE UNDERMINING THE EFFECTIVENESS OF OUR CITY'S
DRUG COURT PROGRAM. THIS COMES IN RESPONSE TO A
RECENT INVESTIGATION BY THE SAN FRANCISCO CHRONICLE WHICH
PUBLISHED ITS FINDINGS EARLIER THIS MONTH.
THE CHRONICLE'S INVESTIGATION FOUND THAT DRUG COURT CASES
HAVE MORE THAN TRIPLED SINCE 2023 AND THAT DEFENDANTS
CHARGED WITH VIOLENT CRIMES INCLUDING ATTEMPTED MURDER,
ARMED ROBBERY AND ASSAULT WITH A DEADLY WEAPON HAVE BEEN
INCREASINGLY DIVERTED INTO A PROGRAM THAT WAS ORIGINALLY
DESIGNED TO SERVE LOW LEVEL AND NONVIOLENT OFFENSES.
>> THE CHRONICLE'S INVESTIGATION IDENTIFIED OTHER
TROUBLING ISSUES RELATING TO DRUG COURT WHICH I THINK MERIT
OUR FURTHER EXPLORATION AS LAWMAKERS.
THAT INCLUDES THAT TERMINATIONS FROM DRUG TREATMENT PROGRAMS
SIGNIFICANTLY OUTPACED GRADUATIONS WITH 259
PARTICIPANTS SENT BACK TO CRIMINAL COURT COMPARED TO ONLY
134 WHO SUCCESSFULLY COMPLETED THE PROGRAM AND THAT OUR DRUG
TREATMENT CAPACITY IS PRESENTING SEVERE BOTTLENECKS
WITH SOME DEFENDANTS ACCEPTED INTO DRUG COURT WAITING UP TO
FOUR MONTHS IN JAIL FOR A TREATMENT SLOT TO OPEN.
I WILL BE INVITING DISTRICT ATTORNEY BROOK JENKINS OFFICE
TO PRESENT HER PERSPECTIVE ON THESE ISSUES AND WHETHER SHE
BELIEVES THE SCALE OF DRUG COURT DIVERSIONS IS WARRANTED
GIVEN THE FACTS OF THE CASES THAT SHE HANDLES AS WELL.
I WILL INVITE A REPRESENTATIVE FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
HEALTH TO DISCUSS WHAT WE AS A CITY ARE DOING OR PERHAPS
SHOULD BE DOING BETTER TO EXPAND CAPACITY TO MEET THE
GROWING NEED. ALTHOUGH NOT DIRECTLY REBEL
RELEVANT TO DIVERSION, I THINK IT WOULD ALSO BE HELPFUL FOR US
TO BE APPRIZED OF THE NON DIVERSIONARY CUSTODIAL
TREATMENT AND RECOVERY OPTIONS THAT OUR SHERIFF'S OFFICE
OFFERS IN SAN FRANCISCO'S JAILS.
SO I WILL BE INVITING SHERIFF PAUL MIYAMOTO OR HIS
REPRESENTATIVE TO PRESENT ON THAT AS WELL.
I HAVE VISITED AND INTERACTED WITH PARTICIPANTS FROM THE
SHERIFF'S ROADS TO RECOVERY PROGRAM AT SAN BRUNO AND I
THINK THAT TOGETHER WITH ITS SISTERS AND CARE COORDINATOR
PROGRAMS ARE DOING VERY IMPRESSIVE WORK TO HELP THOSE
WHO ARE JUST AS INVOLVED GET ON THE OTHER SIDE OF THEIR
ADDICTIONS. AND FINALLY, WHILE WE CAN'T
COMPEL ANYONE FROM SAN FRANCISCO SUPERIOR COURT TO
ATTEND, I WILL CERTAINLY INVITE THE PRESIDING JUDGE OR HER
REPRESENTATIVE TO OFFER THEIR PERSPECTIVE IF THEY WOULD LIKE
. AS SOMEONE IN RECOVERY FROM
ADDICTION MYSELF I YIELD TO NO ONE IN THE STRENGTH OF MY
BELIEF IN THE LIFE CHANGING AND EVEN LIFESAVING
POSSIBILITIES OF DRUG TREATMENT AND RECOVERY.
I AM HOWEVER UNAWARE OF ANY RECOVERY TRADITION FOR WHICH
ACCOUNTABILITY AND TAKING RESPONSIBILITY AREN'T
FOUNDATIONAL ELEMENTS. DRUG COURT DIVERSION IS NOT
AND SHOULD NOT BE A GET OUT OF JAIL FREE CARD STILL DONE
RIGHT? IT'S PERHAPS THE BEST AND MOST
IMPORTANT INTERVENTION WE COULD OFFER IN MANY CIRCUMSTANCES
AND THAT MAY WELL INCLUDE CIRCUMSTANCES FOR VIOLENT
OFFENDERS. A RECENTLY PUBLISHED 2025
REVIEW BY RESEARCHERS AT THE OTHER USF, THE UNIVERSITY OF
SOUTHERN FLORIDA ENTITLED DRUG COURT FOR VIOLENT OFFENDERS A
REVIEW OF RECIDIVISM OUTCOMES FOUND THAT SOME DRUG COURTS CAN
BE EFFECTIVE IN REDUCING RECIDIVISM FOR BOTH VIOLENT
AND NONVIOLENT OFFENDERS. SOME OF THE STUDIES ANALYZED
FOUND NO SIGNIFICANT DIFFERENCES IN RECIDIVISM RATE
BETWEEN VIOLENT AND NON VIOLENT OFFENDERS AND AT LEAST ONE
SUGGESTED THAT VIOLENT OFFENDERS WITH TWO OR MORE
PRIOR CONVICTIONS MAY HAVE HIGHER RECIDIVISM RATES,
SUGGESTING THAT SOME ELIGIBILITY RESTRICTIONS MAY BE
APPROPRIATE. MY OFFICE WILL BE REACHING OUT
TO THE RESEARCHERS OF THAT PAPER TO INVITE THEIR
PERSPECTIVE FOR THIS HEARING AS WELL.
I DO WANT TO THANK THE SAN FRANCISCO CHRONICLE AND ITS
LEAD JOURNALIST FOR THEIR ENTERPRISE REPORTING ON THAT
INVESTIGATION. DAVID HERNANDEZ I ALSO WANT TO
THANK THOSE FROM THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY'S OFFICE THE SHERIFF'S
OFFICE, THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH AND RECOVERY
COMMUNITY MEMBERS WITH WHOM I HAVE SPOKEN ABOUT THIS HEARING.
I VERY MUCH LOOK FORWARD TO HEARING THEIR PERSPECTIVES
WHATEVER DISAGREEMENTS WE MAY HAVE FROM TIME TO TIME ON DRUG
POLICY, I'M SURE WE ALL AGREE THAT SAN FRANCISCANS DESERVE A
DRUG COURT THAT WORKS AND THAT SUCCEEDS SIMULTANEOUSLY
IN PROTECTING PUBLIC SAFETY AND PROVIDING THE HELP ALL
JUSTICE INVOLVED PEOPLE DESERVE TO SEEK AND MAINTAIN THEIR
RECOVERY FROM ADDICTION AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR
FIELDER. >> SUBMIT SUBMIT.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK AND COLLEAGUES EVER SINCE IT
WAS FIRST SURVEYED BY JASPER O'FARRELL AND 1847 MARKET
STREET HAS BEEN AN INTEGRAL PART OF GETTING AROUND SAN
FRANCISCO HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF COMMUTERS A DAY USE THIS
CORRIDOR WHETHER UNDERGROUND OR ON MUNI METRO OR BART OR UP ON
THE SURFACE WHERE BUSSES, STREETCARS, BIKES, SCOOTERS
AND TAXIS ALL VIE FOR SPACE. >> BUT IT'S MORE THAN JUST THE
BACKBONE OF THE CITY'S TRANSPORTATION NETWORK.
IT'S THE SOUL OF THE BAY AREA WHETHER IT'S THE PRIDE PARADE,
A WARRIORS CHAMPIONSHIP CELEBRATION OR PROTEST FOR OUR
RIGHTS, MARKET STREET IS THE BACKDROP OF OUR REGION'S MOST
POWERFUL MOMENTS. >> IT'S ALSO LONG BEEN A
COMMERCIAL ENGINE OF THE CITY WITH OFFICES DOWNTOWN LANDMARK
RETAIL NEAR UNION SQUARE AND ARTS AND CULTURE AND THE
MID-MARKET AREA. ALL OF THIS IS WHY I'M CALLING
TODAY FOR A HEARING ON THE CITY'S VISION OF MARKET STREET
. >> THIS CORRIDOR HAS BEEN AT
THE CENTER OF CIVIC CONVERSATIONS FOR DECADES,
INCLUDING THE BETTER MARKET STREET PLAN THAT BEGAN UNDER
MAYOR NEWSOME AND CULMINATED IN MOST OF MARKET STREET EAST
OF VENICE GOING CAR FREE IN 2020.
>> SINCE PRIVATE TRAFFIC HAS BEEN REMOVED FROM THE CORRIDOR,
INJURY COLLISIONS ARE DOWN 40% AND BIKES AND BUSSES MOVE
SMOOTHLY AND ON TIME. EVEN WITH THIS SUCCESS THE
FINANCIAL CLIMATE IN THE CITY HAS MEANT A MAJOR SCALING BACK
OF THE INFRASTRUCTURE PLANNED FOR MARKET STREET WITH WHAT WAS
TO BE A TRANSFORMATIVE PROJECT FEATURING SEPARATED BICYCLE
LANES REDUCED TO A MINOR SET OF MAINTENANCE CHANGES
AND ACCESSIBILITY IMPROVEMENTS. >> INSTEAD OF A FUTURE FOCUS ON
TRANSIT AND BIKES, TWO MAJOR EVENTS POINT TOWARDS A
DIFFERENT DIRECTION AND MARKET STREET.
>> RECENTLY AS PART OF MUNI CUTS THE SIX WAS PULLED OFF OF
MARKET STREET ENTIRELY AND THE FIVE AND NINE BUSSES NO LONGER
RUN THE LENGTH OF MARKET STREET WHEN THE RAPID COUNTERPARTS ARE
RUNNING. >> ADDITIONALLY, THE MAYORAL
ADMINISTRATION OPENED UP MARKET STREET TO WAYMO VEHICLES
AND CERTAIN OTHER RIDESHARE VEHICLES FOR PICKUPS AND DROP
OFFS. >> WE'VE HEARD IN OUR COMMUNITY
AND OUR DISTRICT CONCERNS REGARDING THE DISTANCE THIS
DECISION FROM RESIDENTS WHO NOTE THIS WAS DONE WITHOUT
APPROVAL FROM THE S.F. MTA BOARD OR THIS BOARD.
>> FOR MANY CONSTITUENTS WHO RELY ON MARKET STREET FOR
TRANSIT, THIS OPAQUE SHIFT HAS RAISED CONCERNS FOR THE FUTURE
OF THE CORRIDOR. >> THOSE OF US WHO MOVE BY
TRANSIT, BIKE OR SCOOTER IN THE CORRIDOR DESERVE TO KNOW HOW
THESE CHANGES AFFECT SAFELY AND QUICKLY.
WE CAN GET AROUND AND WHAT CHALLENGES CAN BE EXPECTED
WHILE WE WAIT FOR THE TRANSPORTATION VISION TO COME
TOGETHER. THE WORLD IS CHANGING AROUND
MARKET STREET THE OLD WESTFIELD MALL IS CLOSING DOWN.
COMMUTE PATTERNS ARE SHIFTING. CITY INITIATIVES AIM TO FILL
VACANT STOREFRONTS AND BUILD HOUSING.
WHEN I WALKED DOWN MARKET STREET I SEE THE PRESENT
DIFFICULTIES THE DRUG CRISIS ON OUR STREETS, THE SHUTTERING OF
BUSINESS. >> BUT I SEE THAT EVEN THROUGH
THE DIFFICULTIES IT'S STILL A VITAL PART OF HOW WE GET AROUND
OUR CITY AND A KEY ASSET OF THE NEIGHBORHOODS THAT IT CONNECTS
LIKE THE TENDERLOIN. LAST YEAR THE URBAN LAND
INSTITUTE AND THE CIVIC JOY FUND INVITED THE PUBLIC TO COME
UP WITH IDEAS TO REIMAGINE MARKET STREET.
THESE IDEAS FROM A NEVER ENDING BENCH TO AN URBAN FOREST SHOW
THAT THERE'S SO MUCH ENERGY AND CREATIVITY BEHIND MAKING
THE STREET AS GREAT AS WE CAN. WE ALL WANT MARKET STREET TO BE
VIBRANT AND WELCOMING. >> BUT THE QUESTION REMAINS HOW
DO WE GET THERE? >> SO TODAY FOR THE HEALER FOR
THE HEARING WE'RE CALLING FOR ON MARKET STREET.
WE WANT IT BECAUSE WE NEED TO HEAR FROM THE DEPARTMENTS
AND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND HOW THEY PLAN TO KEEP MARKET STREET
MOVING AND WHAT STEPS WILL BE TAKEN TO ENSURE THE PUBLIC IS
INFORMED. WE ARE A FANTASTIC CITY AND SAN
FRANCISCANS DESERVE TO HAVE A POSITIVE HOLISTIC VISION OF
WHAT MARKET STREET CAN BE IS TOO FAR AND TOO IMPORTANT TO BE
DEFINED BY PIECEMEAL MEASURES AND OUR RESIDENTS ARE FAR TOO
IMPORTANT TO BE KEPT IN THE DARK.
>> WE NEED TO BE CLEAR IN OUR COMMITMENT TO TRENDS TO
TRANSIT, SUSTAINABLE TRANSPORTATION AND A ROBUST
ECONOMIC ENVIRONMENT ON OUR CITY'S MOST IMPORTANT STREET
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN THANK YOU, MADAM
CLERK. COLLEAGUES IT WAS TWO WEEKS AGO
THAT THIS BOARD ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF RENE GOODE WHO WAS
KILLED ON JANUARY 7TH AT AGE 37 BY A FEDERAL IMMIGRATION AGENT
IN MINNEAPOLIS, MINNESOTA. TODAY I'M ASKING THAT WE
ADJOURN OUR MEETING IN MEMORY OF ALEX JEFFREY PERETTI WHO WAS
KILLED ON JANUARY 24TH, 2026, ALSO AT THE AGE OF 37 BY U.S.
BORDER PATROL AGENTS IN MINNEAPOLIS.
HE WAS KILLED LESS THAN TWO MILES AWAY FROM THE SITE WHERE
GOODE HAD BEEN KILLED. ALEX WAS BORN IN ILLINOIS
AND GRADUATED FROM PREBLE HIGH SCHOOL IN GREEN BAY, WISCONSIN
IN 2006. HE WENT ON TO GRADUATE GRADUATE
FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA IN 2011 WITH A
BACHELOR'S DEGREE IN BIOLOGY. SOCIETY AND THE ENVIRONMENT.
>> AFTER GRADUATING HE BRIEFLY WORKED AS A RESEARCH ASSISTANT
BEFORE RETURNING TO SCHOOL FOR NURSING.
AT THE TIME OF HIS DEATH HE WAS AN ICU NURSE AT THE MINNEAPOLIS
VETERANS AFFAIRS MEDICAL CENTER.
FRIENDS, COLLEAGUES AND PATIENTS HAVE REMEMBERED
HIM AS AN EXCELLENT NURSE WHO LOVED BEING ABLE TO HELP PEOPLE
. HIS FAMILY HAS DESCRIBED HIM AS
A KINDHEARTED SOUL WHO CARED DEEPLY ABOUT HIS FAMILY
AND FRIENDS AND THE AMERICAN VETERANS HE CARED FOR IN HIS
FREE TIME. ALEX OF MOUNTAIN BIKE BIKING
AND SPENDING TIME WITH HIS DOG JOEL ALEX IS SURVIVED BY HIS
PARENTS MICHAEL AND SUSAN. THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO MOURNS THE LOSS OF ALEX PERETTI AND EXTENDS OUR
DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO HIS FAMILY, HIS LOVED ONES AND THE
CITY OF MINNEAPOLIS. REST IN PEACE AND POWER.
ALEX PERETTI. NEW YORK MEMORY BE A BLESSING
AND COLLEAGUES AS WE DID FOR RENE GOOD.
I WOULD ASK THAT WE DO THIS ON BEHALF OF THE FULL BOARD SO WE
WILL HAVE THAT ON BEHALF OF THE FULL BOARD.
>> THANK YOU AND THE REST OF THE EVENTS.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUE.
>> TODAY I AM INTRODUCING THE CLEAN STREETS AND FAIR WAGES
ACT BECAUSE AS EVERYONE HOLDS HOLD YOUR APPLAUSE EVERYONE
PLEASE. >> THANK YOU.
BECAUSE SOMETHING IN OUR CURRENT SYSTEM IS NOT WORKING
AND SAN FRANCISCANS KNOW IT. FOR YEARS WE HAVE BEEN TOLD
THAT OUTSOURCING STREET CLEANING WOULD BE CHEAPER
AND MORE EFFICIENT BUT INSTEAD OUR STREETS ARE AS DIRTY AS
EVER. BUT WE HAVE SEEN THE RISE OF
PRIVATE CONTRACTORS BILLING THE CITY NEARLY $200 AN HOUR WHILE
PAYING WORKERS POVERTY WAGES, CUTTING CORNERS ON SAFETY,
FAILING TO PROVIDE BASIC PAYROLL TRANSPARENCY AND THAT'S
NOT EFFICIENCY. FUNDED BY TAXPAYER DOLLARS THIS
IS EXPLOITATION. THIS ORDINANCE DOES SOMETHING
VERY SIMPLE AND FAIR. IT APPLIES PREVAILING WAGE
AND PAYROLL TAX TRANSPARENCY RULES TO STREET CLEANING
CONTRACTS JUST LIKE WE ALREADY DO FOR A CITY CONSTRUCTION
PROJECT. >> PEOPLE WHO DO THIS THANKLESS
ESSENTIAL WORK THAT WE ALL RELY ON DESERVE A LIVING WAGE AND A
CHANCE TO AFFORD TO LIVE IN THE CITY THEY MAINTAIN.
IF YOU TAKE PUBLIC MONEY YOU PAY FAIR WAGES.
IF YOU TAKE PUBLIC MONEY, SHOW YOUR BOOKS.
>> IT ALSO DON'T WANT TO GET IN TROUBLE WITH ANGELA HERE,
GUYS. >> IT ALSO PRIORITIZES OUR
NEARLY 400 TRAINED ACCOUNTABLE PUBLIC STREET CLEANING WORKERS
REPRESENTED BY LABORERS LOCAL TO 61 WORKERS.
WORKERS WHO ALREADY DO THIS JOB SAFELY, EFFICIENTLY AND WITH
PRIDE. THE RESULT IS BETTER OUTCOMES
CLEANER STREET FAIR PAY, REAL ACCOUNTABILITY AND MILLION
SAVED. OUR CITY DOLLARS WILL NOT BE
USED TO UNDERMINE COLLECTIVE BARGAINING AGREEMENTS WITH OUR
MOST VULNERABLE WORKERS. >> OUR CITY WILL NOT BE A RIGHT
TO WORK CITY. THIS IS ABOUT PROTECTING
WORKERS, RESPECTING TAXPAYER HOURS AND RESTORING TRUST
IN HOW CITY HALL DOES BUSINESS. I HOPE TO HAVE ALL OF YOUR
SUPPORT FOR THIS ORDINANCE TO MAKE OUR STREETS CLEANER, OUR
WORKERS RESPECTED, TREAT IT WITH DIGNITY AND FAIRLY
COMPENSATED. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. TODAY ALSO ALONG WITH
SUPERVISORS CHEN CHAN FIELDER AND WANG I AM INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION CALLING ON THE GOVERNOR AND STATE LEGISLATURE
TO FULLY INVEST IN OUR PUBLIC EDUCATION SYSTEM.
>> WHILE THE GOVERNOR'S PROPOSED BUDGET IS PROMISING WE
NEED LONG TERM FINANCIAL STABILITY TO ENSURE THAT WE DO
NOT COME BACK TO THIS CRISIS SITUATION TIME AND TIME AGAIN.
RIGHT NOW THE PROPOSAL INCLUDES WITHHOLDING $5.6 BILLION
IN PROP 98 FUNDS ACROSS CALIFORNIA.
>> THERE ARE AT LEAST 18 EDUCATOR UNIONS WHO ARE AT AN
IMPASSE WITH THEIR RESPECTIVE SCHOOL DISTRICTS OVER CONTRACT
NEGOTIATIONS INCLUDING OUR OWN. HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, UCSF.
THIS ALARM BELL WAS RUNG MANY, MANY MONTHS AGO WITH A STATE
WIDE WE CANNOT WAIT. WE CAN'T WAIT.
CAMPAIGN BY THE TEACHERS BY CALIFORNIA TEACHERS ASSOCIATION
CALLING FOR FULLY STAFFED SCHOOLS, SMALLER CLASS SIZES,
SMALLER CASELOADS, COMPETITIVE WAGES AND BENEFITS FOR
EDUCATORS AND STAFF. WHILE I AM HOPEFUL THAT OUR
LOCAL UNION AND DISTRICT WILL COME TO A RESOLUTION, WE CANNOT
CONTINUE GOING ON LIKE THIS WITHOUT SIGNIFICANT PLANS FROM
THE STATE ESPECIALLY AS OUR FEDERAL GOVERNMENT IS
UNDERCUTTING FUNDING. THIS RESOLUTION PUTS ON THE
RECORD OUR SUPPORT AMPLIFYING THE CALL TO ACTION, ADDRESSING
THE ROOT CAUSES OF THE EDUCATOR SHORTAGE CRISIS AND THE
DIVESTMENT IN PUBLIC EDUCATION. >> ON A LOCAL LEVEL I'M ALSO
URGING OUR CITY DEPARTMENTS TO SUPPORT SFD IN DEVELOPING JOINT
SOLUTIONS TO SUPPORT OUR OWN HOUSE FAMILY POPULATION
AND PROVIDE ADDITIONAL RESOURCES FOR FAMILIES AT RISK
OF IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT. THESE ARE DEMANDS THAT THE
UNION HAS REQUESTED WHICH I FEEL ARE UNDER OUR CITY'S
ABILITY TO SUPPORT THE TALKS OF A POSSIBLE STRIKE IS UNSETTLING
FOR STUDENTS, FOR FAMILIES AND STAFF.
BUT WE NEED TO DO THE RIGHT THING BY OUR COMMUNITY TO
PUBLIC EDUCATION BY FULLY FUNDING IT.
AND FINALLY, MADAM CLERK, I HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM AND I WOULD
LIKE TO REFER AFTER I'M DONE TALKING TO MY COLLEAGUE
SUPERVISOR FIELDER. I AM HEARTBROKEN COLLEAGUES BY
THE PASSING OF MY DEAR FRIEND JOSEPH WAY QUIET KNOWN TO MANY
OF US AS DR. LOCO DR. LOCO HIS LIFE EMBODIED THE POWER OF
CULTURE, EDUCATION AND JOY. JOSE INSPIRED GENERATIONS AS A
PROFESSOR EMERITUS OF LATINO LATINO STUDIES AT SAN FRANCISCO
STATE UNIVERSITY WHERE HE TAUGHT STUDENTS TO HONOR
CHICANO MUSIC HISTORY CULTURE AND IDENTITY.
HE WAS A SCHOLAR, A VETERAN AND ANTHROPOLOGIST AND AN
AUTHOR WHO SERVED CHICANO CULTURE.
HE WAS ALSO THE BANDLEADER OF DR. LOCOS ROCK IN HOW THE BANJO
BAND HE CREATED A SOUND THAT BLEND IN NEW ORLEANS R&B,
AFRO-CARIBBEAN RHYTHMS, MEXICAN RANCHERAS AND TEX-MEX SOUL A
MUSICAL EXPRESSION THAT CAPTURED THE RICHNESS,
RESILIENCE AND CREATIVITY OF MEXICAN-AMERICAN LIFE.
>> JOSE DIDN'T JUST STUDY CULTURE HE LIVED IT.
HE CREATED IT, HE CELEBRATED IT AND HE SHARED IT WITH EVERYONE
SO GENEROUSLY. KQED WROTE THAT GUERRA HASN'T
JUST STUDIED AND DOCUMENTED CHICANO CULTURE, HE EMBODIED
THE CREATIVE FRISSON GENERATED BY CULTURAL REVOLUTION AS A AS
A LEADER OF ROCK IN HELPING YOUR BAND A VEHICLE THROUGH
WHICH HE EXPLORED THE VERDANT POSSIBILITIES OF MEXICAN
AMERICAN LIFE AND IDENTITY. WE'LL SAY I WAS ACTIVE AS A
RESEARCHER AND PERFORMANCE ART OF ANCIENT MESOAMERICAN NATIVE
WIND INSTRUMENTS ESPECIALLY ROCK ARENAS THROUGH WHICH
THROUGH HIS COLLABORATION WITH HARVARD UNIVERSITY'S PEABODY
MUSEUM OF ARCHEOLOGY AND ETHNOLOGY THEY NEEDED TO BE
HEARD. DAVID CARRASCO DESCRIBED WHERE
AS AN ANTHROPOLOGIST A MUSICIAN WHO THOUGHT WHO SOUGHT TO
BREATHE LIFE INTO INSTRUMENTS BY PLAYING THEM AGAIN CENTURIES
AFTER SILENCE. HARVARD MAGAZINE REPORTS THAT A
PERFORMANCE BY WAY OF LED CURATORS TO RECONNECT THE
INSTRUMENTS HE WAS PLAYING WITH HUNDREDS OF SIMILAR CLARINETS
STORED IN THE MUSEUM'S VAULTS. HIS WORK CONTRIBUTED SO MUCH
IN HIS PERFORMANCES HELP REINTRODUCE ANCIENT
MESOAMERICAN SOUNDSCAPES TO MODERN AUDIENCES.
HIS LEGACY LIVES ON IN THE CLASSROOMS HE SHAPED THE
STAGES. HE ENERGIZED THE COUNTLESS
LIVES HE TOUCHED THROUGH HIS GENEROSITY OF SPIRIT.
MY HEART GOES OUT TO HIS WIDOW STACEY POWER QUASAR, HIS
DAUGHTER EATONVILLE AND THE THOUSANDS OF STUDENTS AND MUSIC
LOVERS THAT HAVE THE PLEASURE OF KNOWING DR. LOCAL.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDS. I JUST WANTED TO THANK MY
COLLEAGUES, THE VIRGIN MELGAR FOR YOUR BEAUTIFUL TRIBUTE
AND MY CONDOLENCES TO THE FAMILY.
>> YOU KNOW THE MISSION DISTRICT WAS IS GOING TO DEEPLY
MISS MR. HOSA. WE ARE AND HIS WORK HAS SHAPED
A LOT OF THE MISSION COMMUNITIES LANDGRAF HAS.
DANCE AND THE NEXT GENERATION OF OF PEOPLE WHO TAKE PRIDE
IN THEIR CHICANO HERITAGE. SO HE'LL BE DEEPLY MISSED
AND HIS MUSIC AND LEGACY LIVE ON EVERY DAY IN THE HEART OF
THE MISSION. SO THANK YOU SO MUCH SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR CHEN YOU WANTED TO BE REFERRED
TO SPEAK ON BILL GROSS ITEM. >> THANK.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. AND ALSO I WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR MAL GAR AGAIN FOR YOUR WORK ON URGING THE STATE
FUNDING FOR OUR PUBLIC SCHOOL. TODAY I'M ALSO JOINING YOU AS A
PUBLIC SCHOOL MOM BECAUSE OUR STUDENTS, FAMILIES AND TEACHERS
NEED ACTION NOW. >> OUR PUBLIC SCHOOLS HAVE
FACED CHRONIC UNDERFUNDING LEADING TO LARGER CLASS SIZE
STAFFING SHORTAGE AND STAGNANT WAGES THAT MAKE IT VERY HARD TO
ATTRACT AND RETAIN OUR EDUCATORS.
>> THIS CONDITION THIS CONDITIONS DIRECTLY IMPACT
STUDENT LEARNING SAFETY AND WELL-BEING.
THE GOVERNOR AND STATE LEGISLATORS MUST INCREASE THE
BUDGET FOR PUBLIC EDUCATION AND WE NEED STABLE FUNDING
AND FULLY RESOURCES SCHOOLS FOR OUR KIDS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN. >> SUPERVISOR SAUTER, THANK YOU
FOR YOUR PATIENCE. THANK YOU.
COLLEAGUES, TODAY I HAVE THE HONOR OF INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION TO ADD A COMMEMORATIVE STREET NAME TO
AND FOR WHO WAY TO CELEBRATE A HERO OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
CHINATOWN THAT OFTEN GETS OVERLOOKED.
TIEN FOO WU WEI WILL BE ADDED TO JOY STREET BETWEEN CLAY
STREET AND SACRAMENTO STREET. THIS ALLEY SITS NEXT TO CAMERON
HOUSE WHICH I CONSIDER TO BE AMONG THE MOST IMPORTANT
COMMUNITY INSTITUTIONS NOT ONLY IN DISTRICT THREE BUT IN ALL OF
SAN FRANCISCO. SINFUL WILL COURAGEOUSLY WORKED
WITH DONALD DANA CAMERON AFTER WHOM CAMERON HOUSE IS NAMED TO
RESCUE HUNDREDS OF ASIAN WOMEN AND GIRLS FROM SEX AND HUMAN
TRAFFICKING IN THE LATE 1800S AND EARLY 1900S.
>> BORN INTO INDENTURED SERVITUDE IN 1886, WU WAS
HERSELF RESCUED BY CAMERON HOUSE WORKERS AS A YOUNG GIRL.
INSTEAD OF LEAVING THE TRAUMA OF HER OWN EXPERIENCE BEHIND,
SHE CHOSE TO DEDICATE HER LIFE TO ENSURING THAT OTHER GIRLS
WOULD NEVER AGAIN FACE SUCH EXPLOITATION.
FLUENT IN CANTONESE AND DEEPLY TRUSTED BY THE WOMEN WHO
ARRIVED AT THE DOORS OF CAMERON HOUSE, SHE WORKED TIRELESSLY
DAY AND NIGHT TEACHING ACCOMPANYING SURVIVORS TO
COURT, ADVOCATING PUBLICLY FOR THEIR RIGHTS AND OFFERING
REASSURANCE AT EVERY MOMENT THAT THEY SOUGHT REFUGE.
WE WOULD GO ON TO BE A LIFELONG FRIEND AND ASSISTANT TO DAWN
IN CAMERON. WHEN CAMERON RETIRED IN THE
1930S, WU LED THE WORK EVEN MORE SO MAKING PUBLIC
APPEARANCE TO RAISE FUNDS AND AWARENESS ACTING AS A
GUARDIAN FOR THE WOMEN WHO HAD TESTIFIED AGAINST THEIR SLAVE
DEALERS WHO NEVER MARRIED. TURNING DOWN MANY SUITORS.
MEN ARE VERY USEFUL, SHE ONCE SAID.
WHEN IT COMES TO MOVING FURNITURE IN HISTORICAL
ACCOUNTS OF CAMERON HOUSE RESIDENTS INCLUDING THOSE OF WU
HERSELF, THE ALLEYWAY OF JOY STREET, BROOKLYN BETWEEN CLAY
AND SACRAMENTO WAS ONE WHERE THE GIRLS WOULD PLAY LAUGH
AND RECLAIM THE MOMENTS OF CHILDHOOD THAT HAD BEEN TAKEN
FROM THEM. OUR STREET NAMING WILL HONOR
TIEN FOR WU ON THIS VERY STREET AND SEEK TO RESTORE HER MEMORY
TO THE LANDSCAPE OF CHINATOWN AND GIVE VISIBILITY TO A WOMAN
WHOSE LEGACY DESERVES MORE PUBLIC RECOGNITION.
I WANT TO THANK THE INCREDIBLE TEAM AT CAMERON HOUSE FOR
BRINGING THIS IDEA TO MY OFFICE PARTICULARLY PARTICULARLY THE
ANIMA AND THEIR CEO SCOTLAND. THANK YOU AS WELL TO THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS FOR THEIR SUPPORT ON THIS AND TO
MICHELLE AND OTHERS IN MY OFFICE FOR PREPARING THIS
RESOLUTION. THEN THE REST OF I SUBMIT THANK
YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER. >> MR. PRESIDENT, SEEING NO
NAMES ON THE ROSTER THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION OF
NEW BUSINESS. >> LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. IF YOU ARE HERE TO PROVIDE
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT YOU OBVIOUSLY KNOW WHAT TO DO LINE
UP ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER.
WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES AND YOU MAY SPEAK
TWO MINUTES AS PRESENTED ITEMS 29 THROUGH 58 ON THE ADOPTION
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE CALENDAR AND OTHER GENERAL
MATTERS THAT ARE NOT ON THE BOARD AGENDA.
ALL RIGHT. WELCOME TO OUR FIRST SPEAKER.
YOU HAVE TWO MINUTES. GO.
>> I GET TO GO. NUMBER SIX ELECTION YOUR
READING GLASSES. IT MAKES YOU LOOK MORE LIKE GA
IN THE 1967 JUNGLE BOOK. >> NUMBER SEVEN.
FORGET IT. OKAY.
THIS IS MY LAST IN ENGLISH EVER SO SINCE IT'S NOW ABSOLUTELY
ABSOLUTELY PLAIN TO TEST HERE. TOUCH SMELL SEE THAT ABSOLUTE
INCOMPETENCE MISTAKENLY MECHANICALLY COLD AIR IS NOW
IN FULL BLOOM. >> >> THAT'S SINCE YOU NEVER
LISTEN TO ME EXPLAINING YOU OUGHT NOT TO GET THERE IN THIS
TRAP BY FOCUSING ON BEAUTY EMOTIONALLY IN ORDER TO BE
HAPPY THEREFORE JUSTIFY YOUR REASON FOR BEING.
>> NOW I'M GOING TO TAKE CARE OF MY COUNTRY SO NEXT TIME I'LL
SPEAK ONLY IN FRENCH. NO TRANSLATION YOU DON'T
DESERVE TRANSLATION. >> NOW YOU CAN DO THE JOB.
AT LEAST MAYBE YOU'RE GOING TO RAISE YOUR LEVEL SINCE THE
FUTURE IS FRENCH. YOU HAVE TO UNDERSTAND
SOMETHING. >> IT'S ALL CONNECTED TO THE
FRENCH REVOLUTION. INDEED.
BIGGEST MISTAKE IN HISTORY TO GET THE HEAD OF THE KING.
WE THE 16TH. >> IT WAS ALREADY CLEARLY.
>> ANYWAY, 30S. I'M GLAD TO INFORM YOU THAT NOW
IS THERE IS A SONG COMING. BREAK THE SILENCE AGAINST
INSTITUTIONALIZED CHILD TRAFFICKING IS COMING.
IT'S GOING TO BE AVAILABLE ONLINE VERY SOON UNDER MY NAME
SO YOU CAN CHECK IT OUT. I DON'T KNOW IF IT WILL HELP
MEDICINE BECAUSE EVERYBODY IS SO AFRAID OF THE SUBJECT.
>> BUT THAT'S IT OF THE MERCI BEAUCOUP.
>> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
SHALOM TO YOU. >> MY NAME IS SOLILOQUY A
CHANDLER CHANDLER ABOLITIONIST AND SOCIAL JUSTICE FIGHTER FOR
MY PEOPLE AND FOR MY NATION TO MAKE A BETTER HUMANITY.
THE REASON I'M HERE TODAY IS THAT MY SPIRIT IS VERY
DISTRAUGHT. I'M VERY CONCERNED ABOUT WHAT'S
HAPPENING IN THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AT THIS TIME.
AND I THINK THE UNFORTUNATE SITUATION THAT'S HAPPENING
IN MINNEAPOLIS YOU'RE NOT AWARE THAT DURING THE TIME OF THE
GEORGE FLOYD RIOT THAT HAPPENED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO WHERE
MULTI-THOUSAND SURVIVED DURING THE REIGN OF FORMER
MAYOR LONDON BREED, THERE WAS HUNDREDS OF POLICE OFFICERS
WITH THEIR SHIELDS ON ON THESE CITY HALL STEPS THAT YOU SIT
HERE AND REPRESENT. IT WAS THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE WHO
CAME TO SET THIS BUILDING ON FIRE.
IT WAS MYSELF WHO STOPPED IT. >> YOU CAN LOOK IT UP.
IT'S IN THE STORIES IN THE IN THE NEWSPAPERS.
A BLACK WOMAN WITH A BLOW HORN .
>> THEY WROTE THE STORY. I PROCEEDED ALL OF THOSE
PROTEST HOURS FROM MISSION HIGH TO GO BACK TO VALENCIA POLICE
DEPARTMENT. >> IT WAS HUNDREDS OF POLICE
OFFICERS WITH SHIELDS THERE. >> THERE WAS A CAUCASIAN GIRL
DRESSED IN BLACK WITH A BACKPACK ON HER BACK WHO TRIED
TO JUMP OVER THE BARRIER GATES AT THE VALENCIA POLICE
DEPARTMENT. THERE WAS GETTING READY TO
START A RIOT WHERE THESE OFFICERS WOULD HAVE TO SHOOT
THESE PROTESTERS. >> HOW I STOPPED THOUSANDS FROM
BEING SHOT IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THIS BUILDING FROM BEING
SET ON FIRE. I SAY IT TO EVERY ONE OF THOSE
PROTESTERS, EVERY ONE OF YOU WHO FEEL THAT YOU ARE THE
CHOSEN ONES. >> I NEED YOU TO GET
IN POSITION RIGHT NOW AND I NEED YOU TO ESCORT ALL OF THESE
PROTESTERS OUT OF HERE. >> AND EVERYONE WHO HEARD MY
VOICE THEY ASSISTED ME OF GETTING THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE TO
AVOID BURN IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> THEN MONICA CHANDLER, THANK
YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. THANK YOU.
>> TODAY WE'LL HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER NOW MISS CHANDLER.
>> WHAT'S HAPPENING IN MINNEAPOLIS?
THE POLITICAL. >> WE'LL HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER NOW MISS CHANDLER. I WANT YOU TO KNOW WHAT MISS
CHANDLER. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER WELCOME. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISORS THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
MY NAME IS BEN AND I LIVE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND DISTRICT
FIVE JUST DOWN THE STREET. AND I'M THE CEO OF A LOCAL
PUBLIC SAFETY TECHNOLOGY COMPANY CALLED HYPER AI THAT
HANDLES NON-EMERGENCY 911 AND 311 CALLS.
I'M HERE BECAUSE SAN FRANCISCO FACES A STRUCTURAL PROBLEM NOT
A PERSONNEL PROBLEM. >> WE HAVE MORE CALLS THAN
HUMANS CAN REALISTICALLY ANSWER FAST ENOUGH.
EVERY DAY THOUSANDS OF CALLS COME INTO 911 AND 311 IN THE
CITY. >> BUT A LARGE SHARE OF THOSE
CALLS ARE NOT LIFE THREATENING EMERGENCIES.
THEY'RE SERVICE REQUESTS, QUESTIONS, ACCIDENTAL DIALS OR
SITUATIONS THAT DON'T REQUIRE IMMEDIATE DISPATCH.
YET THEY STILL TAKE UP TIME AND THE SAME PHONE LINES WHERE
HIGHLY TRAINED STAFF COULD BE ANSWERING PEOPLE WHO NEED HELP
WITH HEART ATTACKS OR VIOLENT EMERGENCIES.
SO THE RESULT IS PREDICTABLE LONGER WAIT TIMES DISPATCH
BURNOUT RESIDENTS LOSING TRUST IN THE SYSTEM.
HIRING HELPS BUT TRAINING TAKES MONTHS.
STAFFING ALONE CANNOT KEEP UP. SO TODAY TECHNOLOGY LIKE VOICE
I CAN ACT AS A FIRST LAYER FOR NON-EMERGENCY CALLS INSTANTLY
ANSWERING GATHERING INFORMATION ESCALATING TO HUMANS WHEN
NEEDED MEANS NO MORE HOLD HOLD TIMES FOR ROUTINE CALLS CALL
TAKERS CAN BE FREED UP FOR REAL EMERGENCIES LESS OVERTIME
IN OPERATIONAL STRAIN AND BETTER PERFORMANCE FOR THE
STAFF. WE ALREADY HAVE.
THIS IS EXACTLY WHAT MY COMPANY AND OTHERS ARE WORKING ON
IN THE IN THE CITY AND WE'RE ALREADY PARTNERING WITH MAJOR
PUBLIC AGENCIES LIKE SAN DIEGO AND TORONTO.
WE ARE PREPARED TO OFFER A FREE PILOT TO PROVE THE CAPABILITIES
OF THESE TYPES OF TECHNOLOGY. BECAUSE THIS ISN'T ABOUT
REPLACING DISPATCHERS. IT'S ABOUT PROTECTING THEIR
TIME AND THE MOMENTS THAT REALLY MATTER.
BECAUSE THIS TECHNOLOGY CAN REDUCE WAIT TIMES OVERTIME
COSTS AND SAVE MONEY BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY IT CAN SAVE LIVES.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. HELLO.
MY NAME IS BARBARA BELLA AND I'M A LONG TIME RESIDENT OF
SAN FRANCISCO. AND I'M HERE TODAY TO TALK
ABOUT THE BIGGEST LITTLE ILLEGALLY DUMPED ITEM IN SAN
FRANCISCO. THE PLASTIC CIGARET BUT IF YOU
HAVE CHILDREN OR IF ANY OF YOU ARE CONSTITUENTS HAVE CHILDREN
I WANT YOU TO REALLY TAKE A LOOK AT THIS.
MANY PEOPLE THINK IT'S COTTON. IT'S NOT.
IT'S CELLULOSE ACETATE. IT'S A FORM OF PLASTIC.
AND JUST THIS ONE LITTLE CIGARET BESIDES BEING
INCREDIBLY STINKY WILL BREAK DOWN INTO UP TO 15,000
MICROPLASTIC FIBERS. >> THOSE MICROPLASTICS DO NOT
DECOMPOSED OR DISAPPEAR. THEY END UP IN OUR SIDEWALKS,
OUR PARKS, OUR BEACHES, OUR WATERWAYS.
>> THEY ENTER THE FOOD WE EAT THE WATER WE DRINK THE AIR WE
BREATHE CHILDREN, PETS, WILDLIFE ARE EXPOSED TO THIS
TOXIC WASTE EVERY SINGLE DAY. >> CIGARETS FILTERS ARE
CONSISTENTLY THE MOST COMMON FORM OF LITTER IN SAN FRANCISCO
MAKING UP UP TO 50% OF OBSERVED LITTER.
THEY DON'T BIODEGRADE. THEY FRAGMENT AND THEY LEACH
TOXIC CHEMICALS LIKE NICOTINE, ARSENIC AND LEAD.
BUT LET'S BE CLEAR THIS IS NOT A FILTER.
>> FILTERS. THESE FILTERS DO NOT PROTECT
HUMAN HEALTH. THE SURGEON GENERAL HAS
REPORTED THEY PROVIDE NO HEALTH BENEFIT AND MAY EVEN CONTRIBUTE
TO A MORE AGGRESSIVE FORM OF LUNG CANCER.
THE TERM FILTER ITSELF IS NOTHING MORE THAN A MARKETING
GIMMICK FROM BIG TOBACCO THAT WE'VE KNOWN ABOUT SINCE THE
1960S. THAT'S WHY TODAY WE ARE
SUBMITTING A LETTER TO EACH OF YOU VINCE, EWEN AND I THAT IS A
REQUEST FOR AN AMENDMENT TO THE SAN FRANCISCO HEALTH CODE 19 Q
TO PROHIBIT THE SALE OF PARTIALLY IN CONSUMABLE TOBACCO
PRODUCTS PLASTIC CIGARET FILTERS.
>> THIS IS NOT ABOUT REGULATING BEHAVIOR.
THIS IS ABOUT REGULATING TOXIC PRODUCT LIKE LEAD.
SAN FRANCISCO ALREADY REGULATES LEAD PAINT, WATER TOYS,
CONSUMER PRODUCTS BECAUSE IT'S TOXIC AND PERSISTENT IN THE
ENVIRONMENT. PLASTIC CIGARET FILTERS DESERVE
THE SAME TREATMENT. >> THIS IS ABOUT HOLDING
MANUFACTURERS ACCOUNTABLE NOT RETAILER.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. I VISORS AND ONE FOR THE CLERK.
MAY I LEAVE IT HERE? >> IF YOU COULD PLEASE PLACE IT
OVER TO THE SIDE AND WE'LL HAVE SOMEBODY COME GET IT.
>> I DON'T KNOW WHERE THE VOICE IS COMING FROM.
YEAH, JUST GO AHEAD AND PUT IT RIGHT THERE.
>> WE'LL COME GET IT. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. NEXT SPEAKER, PLEASE.
WHEN I'M VINCE YOU AND I FOUNDED AND LEAD REFUSE REFUSE
TO VOLUNTEER GROUP CLEANING UP LITTER IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND EVERYONE IS ALWAYS SHOCKED AT HOW MANY CIGARET BUTTS THEY
PICKED UP. THIS WAS SIX VOLUNTEERS IN AN
HOUR RIGHT OUTSIDE CITY HALL TODAY.
AND IF YOU MULTIPLY THAT BY ALL THE BLOCKS AROUND THE CITY YOU
CAN SEE WHAT WE'RE DEALING WITH.
AND AGAIN, LIKE BARBARA SAID, THESE ARE MADE OUT OF PLASTIC.
IT'S THE NUMBER ONE LITTERED SINGLE USE PLASTIC ITEM IN THE
WORLD AND IN SAN FRANCISCO AS WELL ABOUT 35% BY COUNT IS
CIGARETS IF YOU PICK UP 100 PIECES OF TRASH VERY
CONSISTENTLY, 35 OF THOSE WILL BE CIGARET BUTTS.
>> WE'VE BANNED PLASTIC BAGS IN GROCERY STORES AND THAT'S A
DROP IN THE OCEAN COMPARED TO THIS PLASTIC LITTER SOLUTION.
SO WE KNOW WE CAN DO IT. AND I KNOW ALL OF YOU
SUPERVISORS HAVE BEEN LONGTIME SUPPORTERS OF THE CLEANUPS.
I HAVE SEEN ALL OF YOU OUT AT THE CLEANUPS INDIVIDUALLY AND I
HOPE YOU'LL CONTINUE TO SUPPORT THIS.
AND SO I KNOW YOU GUYS KNOW HOW MANY CIGARET BUTTS ARE OUT
THERE AND IF WE'RE TALKING ABOUT CLEAN AND SAFE STREETS
AND PROTECTING OUR FRONT LINE WORKERS, THESE ARE TOXIC
PLASTIC PRODUCTS THAT WE'RE MAKING OUR FRONT LINE WORKERS
PICK UP EVERY SINGLE DAY AFFECTING THEIR HEALTH
IN ADDITION TO OUR ENVIRONMENT. ALL THE OTHER PEOPLE IN THE
COMMUNITY THAT LIVE HERE AND THERE'S A PATHWAY SANTA
CRUZ COUNTY AND SANTA CRUZ AND CAPITAL HAVE ALREADY
FIGURED OUT A PATHWAY THAT THEIR BOARD OF SUPERVISORS JUST
UNANIMOUSLY PASSED THE BILL TO BAN THE SALE OF THESE PLASTIC
CIGARET BUTTS. IT WILL GO INTO EFFECT IN 2027.
THEY HAVE THE PLAYBOOK FOR IT AND I KNOW THAT SAN FRANCISCO
CAN DO IT AS WELL. WE'RE LEADERS IN THE
ENVIRONMENT SO AT LEAST WE'RE SUPPOSED TO BE SO HOPEFULLY WE
CAN CONTINUE THAT TRADITION AND HOPEFULLY WE'LL HAVE THE
SUPPORT OF THE SUPERVISORS HERE THAT WE AS SAN FRANCISCO CAN
UNANIMOUSLY BAN THE SALE OF THESE IN OUR CITY.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER I WON'T LEAVE THESE FOR YOU.
THANK YOU. >> HI, MY NAME IS RICHARD
JOHNSON AND I'M HERE TODAY TO TALK ABOUT THE HAYS STREET
CLOSURE. AND THE REASON I'M HERE IS
BECAUSE WE AS A GROUP I WAS HIV SAFE AND I HELPED CO-FOUND IT.
AND WE'VE DONE OUR DUE DILIGENCE IN WRITING LETTERS,
DOING PETITIONS AND OUTREACHING TO BOTH OUR SUPERVISORS OFFICE
AND TO THE MAYORS AND TO THE S.F. MTA.
TO THIS DATE IT'S BEEN TWO YEARS OF A PERMIT WHERE THERE'S
BEEN 59 WEEKS OF VIOLATION SINCE.
AND WE HAVE BROUGHT THIS TO THE ATTENTION OF THE S.F. MTA BOARD
ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS CONSISTENTLY ADVOCATE THAT THEY
DO THEIR JOB OF ENFORCING THE PERMITS.
TO DATE THEY HAVE NOT AND THEY'VE CHOSEN NOT TO.
AND IT'S BECAUSE OF POLITICS. AND WE FOUND THAT A VERY
CLEARLY LAST WEEK AT THE ICE SCOTT MEETING WHAT WAS STATED
BY BRIAN YOU OF THAT IT WAS BOTH THE PRESSURE OF OUR
SUPERVISOR AND OUR MAYOR THAT WAS PREVENTING THIS FROM BEING
PERMIT FROM BEING REVOKED. AND WHAT WE'RE DOING NOW IS
WE'RE DOING OUR DUE DILIGENCE BECAUSE THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS IS A PROCESS TO APPEAL TO FOR AN INJUSTICE.
AND IN THIS CASE IT'S AN INJUSTICE IN THE FACT OF WHERE
IT'S NOT ONLY VIOLATIONS OF THE PERMIT BUT IT'S ALSO ESCALATED
TO THE POINT WHERE OUR GROUP HAS BEEN LEGALLY THREATENED TO
SILENCE US FROM DOING A JOB THAT THE S.F. MTA IS NOT DO.
AND WE HAVE BEEN FORCED TO DO DOCK STATION.
I WOULD ACTUALLY ASK YOU TO LOOK TOWARDS SUPERVISOR WONG
WHO RECENTLY HELD A MEETING ABOUT THE CLOSED HIGHWAY WHERE
HE ELOQUENTLY AND ADVOCATED FOR BOTH SIDES OF THE ISSUE TODAY.
WE DO NOT SEE THAT WE SEE A ONE SIDED ISSUE WHERE IT'S BEING
RUN BY THE MAJORITY THAT'S DICTATING TO A MINORITY.
AND TO ME IT'S LIKE WHERE IT'S GONE A STEP TOO FAR WITH THE
ESCALATION OF LEGAL THREAT. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. NEXT SPEAKER, PLEASE.
HI, GOOD AFTERNOON. >> MY NAME'S MAX WEXLER.
I'M A NEW FATHER, A LOCAL BUSINESS OWNER AND THE AUTHOR
OF THE 137 USEF MASTER'S PROJECT 137 PAGE PROJECT POLICY
OPTIONS TO MITIGATE CIGARET FILTER LITTER IN CALIFORNIA.
I'LL SAVE YOU THE TIME. SPOILER ALERT BANNING THEM IS
THE BEST OPTION AND SANTA CRUZ COUNTY DESERVES A LOT OF
RECOGNITION AND CELEBRATION FOR RECENTLY DOING SO.
DID YOU KNOW THAT IN 1950 ONLY 5% OF CIGARETS SOLD IN THE U.S.
HAD SO-CALLED FILTERS? THE WORD ITSELF IS AN ORWELLIAN
MISNOMER INVENTED BY BIG TOBACCO IN THE 1960S WHEN
SCIENTIFIC LITERATURE STARTED TO LINK SMOKING CIGARETS WITH
CANCER. THE LIE HAS BEEN SOLD EVER
SINCE THAT CELLULOSE ACETATE PLASTIC FILTERS ARE BENEFIT TO
HUMAN HEALTH. DESPITE NUMEROUS STUDIES
AND STATEMENTS FROM THE SURGEON GENERAL STATING OTHERWISE
THAT'S HOW YOU KNOW YOU'RE REALLY IN TROUBLE WHEN THE
RIGHT LANGUAGE DOESN'T EXIST TO LABEL A PROBLEM BECAUSE THE
MESSAGE HAS BEEN CONTROLLED BY THE PERPETRATORS.
I'D LIKE TO TAKE A MOMENT TO LET THAT SINK IN BUT I'M ON THE
CLOCK. >> SO FOR NOW LET'S JUST CALL
THEM BUTTS. SO ALLOW ME TO PROVIDE YOU WITH
SOME BUT FACTS. A 2014 SAN FRANCISCO LITTER
AUDIT FOUND THAT CIGARET BUTTS COMPRISE 53% OF ALL OBSERVED
LITTER IN THE CITY MEASURED BY QUANTITY, NOT WEIGHT OR VOLUME
. I WAS GOING TO PROVIDE SOME
PUBLIC WORKS STREET SWEEPING DATA AND IT WAS GREAT THAT
THERE WERE HERE WERE FOUR CLEAN STREETS.
YOU KNOW WE WANT TO MAKE THEIR JOBS EASIER.
>> WHAT STREET SWEEPING IS CAPTURING IS JUST A FRACTION OF
A FRACTION OF THE BUST. I MEAN SOME MORE RECENT DATA IS
I JUST PICKED UP 178 BUTTS LIKE AN HOUR AGO AND IT ONLY TOOK ME
A HALF HOUR AND I WAS WITH A BUNCH OF OTHER PEOPLE DOING THE
SAME THING SO WHAT MAKES THIS PROBLEM SO DIFFICULT IS THAT IT
IS BOTH SO MINUSCULE AND SO ENORMOUS AT THE SAME TIME.
HASHTAG NO FILTER. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER BEFORE I SPEAK
SOMEONE LEFT THEIR LAPTOP. >> I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE
THEY WEREN'T HOLDING A CIGARET BUTTS UP HERE.
OH I'M SORRY IT'S HARD TO GET IT.
I'M ALLERGIC TO CIGARETS. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS DENNIS WILLIAMS JR I'M A SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENT
LOCAL COMMUNITY ROOTED DEVELOPER AND THE PRINCIPAL OF
DC WILLIAMS DEVELOPMENT COMPANY .
I'M HERE TODAY BECAUSE THE CLERK HAS FORMALLY ACKNOWLEDGED
RECEIPT OF FOUR WRITTEN SUBMISSIONS FROM ME WHICH ARE
BEING DISTRIBUTED TO THIS BOARD TODAY.
THESE LETTERS RAISE A NARROW BUT CRITICAL POLICY ISSUE
DEVELOPER LEVEL EXCLUSION IN CITY SUPPORTED REDEVELOPMENT
PROJECTS INCLUDING PROJECTS FUNDED BY VOTER APPROVED BONDS
. SAN FRANCISCO HAS MADE PROGRESS
ON CONTRACTOR AND WORKFORCE INCLUSION.
HOWEVER, DEVELOPER LEVEL PARTICIPATION OWNERSHIP
DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY AND LOCAL TERMS LONG TERM SCUSE ME
ECONOMIC PARTICIPATION REMAIN STRUCTURAL INACCESSIBLE TO
LOCAL COMMUNITY ROOTED AND EMERGING DEVELOPERS.
EVEN WHEN WE HAVE BEEN INVOLVED FOR YEARS IN PLANNING
AND ENTITLEMENT PROCESSES THIS IS NOT A REQUEST FOR
PREFERENTIAL TREATMENT AND IS NOT INCONSISTENT WITH
PROPOSITION 209. IT IS A REQUEST FOR LAWFUL RACE
NEUTRAL PLACE BASED STANDARDS THAT DEFINE WHAT DEVELOPER
INCLUSION ACTUALLY MEANS REQUIRE TRANSPARENCY
AND PROCUREMENT AND ESTABLISH ACCOUNTABILITY WHEN PUBLIC LAND
OR PUBLIC DOLLARS ARE INVOLVED .
I HAVE PREPARED A SUPERVISOR READY DRAFT RESOLUTION AND A
ONE PAGE STAFF SUMMARY ALIGNED WITH THE EARTHQUAKE SAFETY
AND EMERGENCY RESPONSE BONDS SPECIFICALLY FOCUSED ON
IMPLEMENTATION OVERSIGHT AND REPORTING NOT MANDATES.
>> TODAY I AM FORMALLY REQUESTING THAT THIS MATTER BE
CALENDAR FOR HEARING BEFORE THE APPROPRIATE COMMITTEE SO THAT
THESE ISSUES CAN BE DISCUSSED PUBLICLY ON RECORD.
WITH DEPARTMENTS IMO KD O IWD REAL ESTATE DIVISION OCI AND A
COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE BE DIRECTED TO PARTICIPATE
AND PROVIDE DATA AND RESPONSES ON THE RECORD AND CITY ATTORNEY
PRESENT. THE BOARD HAS THE AUTHORITY TO
ENSURE PUBLIC INVESTMENT EVENTS PUBLIC BENEFIT INCLUDING
TRANSPARENCY, FAIRNESS AND LONG TERM COMMUNITY STABILITY.
I RESPECT THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. SO I HAVEN'T BEEN HERE IN A
WHILE. I WAS IN THE AMAZON RAINFOREST
FOR A FEW MONTHS. GOOD TO BE BACK.
SEE YOUR FACES. YOU KNOW WHAT I WANT TO CALL
THE KETTLE BLACK. NOT A PERFECT PERSON.
I MADE A LOT OF POOR DECISIONS IN MY LIFE, YOU COULD SAY.
I LEARNED THE HARD WAY FOR A LIVING.
ALL I KNOW IS MAKING MISTAKES. AND I GOT TO SAY I FEEL LIKE A
SAINT STANDING HERE IN FRONT OF THIS BOARD.
I DON'T WANT TO COME HERE TODAY YELLING YOU GUYS USE BAD
LANGUAGE OR ANYTHING LIKE THAT SO I'LL JUST SAY THIS.
YOU DON'T JUST REPRESENT ALL THE SAN FRANCISCANS THAT ARE
ALIVE TODAY. YOU REPRESENT EVERY SAN
FRANCISCAN THAT CAME BEFORE YOU.
THE GENERATIONS OF AMERICANS OF ALL RACES AND RELIGIONS WHO
POURED OUT THEIR BLOOD, SWEAT AND TEARS BUILDING OUR GREAT
BEAUTIFUL CITY. AND SO FAR YOU GUYS HAVE DONE A
GREAT JOB SCREWING THAT UP. WALKING AROUND DOWNTOWN TODAY
ONCE AGAIN SAW NUMEROUS PEOPLE UTILIZING FINAU.
NEXT TO THE PLAYGROUND. THEN LAST NIGHT FAMILY
FRIENDLY. THAT'S A FORMER CHEMICAL
WARFARE ON THE AMERICAN PEOPLE. 5000 SAN FRANCISCAN IS OF ALL
RACES AND RELIGIONS HAVE DIED FROM FENTANYL BETWEEN THE YEARS
2019 2026 INCLUDING MANY OF MY FAMILY AND FRIENDS.
>> I DON'T WANT TO TALK ABOUT HOW MANY TIMES I'VE HAD TO
FIGHT OFF BURGLARS WHO'VE KICKED IN MY DOORS OR HOW MANY
RESTAURANT ROBBERIES HAVE STOPPED OR ALL THE TOURISTS
AND FAMILIES I'VE HAD TO DEFEND FROM VIOLENT DRUGGED OUT
LUNATICS WHO OTHERWISE SHOULD HAVE ALREADY BEEN COMPELLED
INTO AN ASYLUM. >> LOOKS LIKE I'M RUNNING OUT
OF TIME ON THE CLOCK. >> FORGOT WHAT I WAS GOING TO
SAY. LOOK, WE CAN'T BE SHEPHERDING
HORDES OF FIN ALL ADDICTS RIGHT BEFORE THE BIG SUPER BOWL.
>> I THINK THAT'S HAVING A NEGATIVE IMPACT ON SURROUNDING
COMMUNITIES. YOU GUYS ARE TRYING TO CRACK
DOWN ON THE SOUTH MARKET AREA IN THE TENDERLOIN AND THE
SURROUNDING NEIGHBORHOODS ARE DOING REALLY BAD THIS MORNING.
THERE IS A HUMANITARIAN CRISIS HAPPENING IN OUR COMMUNITY.
AND SO FAR YOU GUYS HAVE DONE NOTHING BUT ENABLE CHAOS
AND LAWLESSNESS FOR FINANCIAL PROMISE.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS ON.
THANK YOU. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. BOARD PRESIDENT AND MONEY
AND SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS RICHARD PETERSON.
I JUST WANTED TO COMMENT A LITTLE ABOUT TAXATION WITHOUT
REPRESENTATION WHICH I THINK 250 YEARS WE FOUGHT A WAR ABOUT
AND IT'S HAPPENING NOW AND RIGHT NOW I WOULD LIKE TO
SEE THAT THE MONEY BE FUNDED BUT NOT DOUBLY FUNDED.
>> APPARENTLY THERE IS A STATE UP PROPOSITION THAT HAS TO FUND
MUNI WITH A SUBSTANTIAL AMOUNT OF MONEY AND THERE IS A CITY
PROPER PROPOSITION TO FUND MUNI THROUGH PARCEL TAXES.
I BELIEVE IN PARCEL TAXES. I'VE GOT PARCELS I'LL PAY MY
PARCEL TAX AND BUT THE INTERESTING THING THAT OCCURRED
TODAY IS WHEN I WAS TAKING MUNI UP THE STREETCAR AND I WENT
DOWN TO PICK UP DOWN TO PATRICK'S FURTHER DOWN
AND THREE MEN DRESSED IN BLACK CLOTHING AND WITH BLACK JACKETS
AND A BLACK HAD BOARDED THAT BOARDED THE TRAIN AND THEY HAD
BEEN TALKING AMONGST THEMSELVES FOR A WHILE AND THOSE MEN THEN
PROCEEDED TO VIRTUALLY TERRORIZE MANY OF THE
PASSENGERS WHO SIMPLY BOARDED THE TRAINS WITHOUT SHOWING OR
WITHOUT CLICKING ON THE UP ENTRY AND THEY SAID THAT THEY
WERE IN A NEW ENFORCEMENT PROGRAM.
THEY HAVE BLACK JACKETS WITH A BADGE ON THE JACKET AND THAT'S
SIMPLY ALL THAT THEY HAVE AND THEY SAID THEY'RE GOING TO
CONTINUE TO ENFORCE IT BY TICKETING PEOPLE.
BUT YOU'VE GOT TO FIGURE OUT THAT MOST PEOPLE TO BOARD THAT
THE MUNI AREN'T PAYING. SO YOU GOT TO FIGURE OUT A WAY
TO EMBARRASS THEM TO PAY MAYBE A CATCHING FOR A PAYMENT.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
YOUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> I'M BRIAN DAVIS, CO-CHAIR OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO TOBACCO FREE COALITION AND RETIRED PROJECT
DIRECTOR OF LGBTQ MINORS, TOBACCO AND DISTRICT FIVE
RESIDENT. SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN A LEADER
IN THE FIGHT AGAINST BIG TOBACCO IS THE FIRST TO STOP
ALL TOBACCO SALES IN PHARMACIES.
THE FIRST MAJOR CITY TO END THE SALE OF ALL NON FDA APPROVED
VAPES AND ONE OF THE FIRST TO END FLAVORED TOBACCO SALES.
BUT LATELY THE CITY HAS BEEN LOSING ITS EDGE.
OVER 50 BAY AREA CITIES PROTECT THEIR BAR WORKERS AND PATRONS
FROM DEADLY SECONDHAND SMOKE. BY REQUIRING ALL BAR PATIOS TO
BE SMOKE FREE, THAT IS A LOOPHOLE THAT IS LONG OVERDUE
TO BE CLOSED. TIBURON AND ROSS HAVE ENDED THE
SALE OF ALL TOBACCO PRODUCTS THE PRIMARY GOAL OF THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH.
BUT IF YOU'RE NOT READY FOR THAT YET, SANTA CRUZ CITY
AND COUNTY IN CAPITOLA HAVE VOTED TO STOP THE SALE OF
SO-CALLED FILTERED CIGARETS AND CIGARS.
THAT LAW WON'T TAKE EFFECT UNTIL NEXT JANUARY.
SO SAN FRANCISCO HAS THE OPPORTUNITY TO BE THE FIRST TO
PASSED PASS AND ENACT A AN ORDINANCE STOPPING SO-CALLED
FILTER SALES. OVER 4.5 TRILLION OF THESE
SO-CALLED FILTERS IT'S BEEN DESCRIBED EARLIER END UP IN THE
ENVIRONMENT WORLDWIDE EVERY YEAR CONTRIBUTING MASSIVELY TO
PLASTIC POLLUTION AND ADDING THESE 7000 CHEMICALS IN TOBACCO
TO THE ECOSYSTEM KILLING WILDLIFE.
PEOPLE WILL BE ABLE TO CONTINUE TO BUY CIGARETS AND CIGARS
WITHOUT SO-CALLED FILTERS SO BUSINESSES THAT SELL THEM WILL
CONTINUE TO PROFIT FROM THE SALE OF THE NUMBER ONE CAUSE OF
PREVENTABLE DISEASE IN THE NATION.
UNTIL THE CITY IS READY TO FOLLOW THE LEAD OF OTHERS THAT
HAVE STOPPED ALL TOBACCO SALES 20 1843 NONPROFITS AROUND THE
CITY HAVE SIGNED ON TO THE LETTER THAT BARBARA AND VINCE
HAVE SHARED AND THEY HAVE OVER 5400 PETITIONS SIGNATURES FROM
THE COMMUNITY. THE SAN FRANCISCO TOBACCO FREE
COALITION URGES YOU TO VOTE THIS YEAR TO CLOSE THE BAR
PATIO SMOKING LOOPHOLE AND REGAIN TOBACCO PREVENTION
LEGISLATION LEADERSHIP BY BECOMING THE FIRST MAJOR CITY
TO STOP THE SALE OF SO-CALLED FILTERED TOBACCO.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS SIDNEY SIMPSON, A REGISTERED NURSE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND I'M HERE IN STRONG SUPPORT OF SUPERVISOR
CHAN'S RESOLUTION. A HUGE THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR
CHAN FOR HER LEADERSHIP IN THIS CAMPAIGN TO PROTECT THESE KIDS
. I ALSO WANT TO THANK THE
CO-SPONSORS MANDL MIDFIELDER DORSEY CHEN AND WALTON.
AND I ASK THE FULL BOARD FOR YOUR UNANIMOUS SUPPORT OF THIS
RESOLUTION AND OF THE TRANSGENDER COMMUNITY AT A TIME
WHEN WE ARE ESPECIALLY OUR YOUTH BEING TARGETED, I THINK
UNANIMITY REALLY MATTERS. IT TELLS THESE KIDS, THEIR
FAMILIES AND HEALTH CARE WORKERS THAT THE CITY STILL
BELIEVES IN SCIENCE AND CARE WITHOUT DISCRIMINATION.
AS NURSES WE KNOW THAT GENDER AFFIRMING CARE IS NOT
IDEOLOGICAL. IT'S EVIDENCE BASED
AND LIFESAVING. AND WHEN ACCESS TO THIS CARE IS
THREATENED, OUR KIDS SUFFER. THIS RESOLUTION IS ESPECIALLY
SIGNIFICANT GIVEN THAT ROUGHLY 35,000 CITY WORKERS AND THEIR
FAMILIES RECEIVE HEALTH CARE THROUGH KAISER UNDER A MAJOR
CITY CONTRACT. SAN FRANCISCO HAS A MORAL
OBLIGATION TO ENSURE THAT CONTRACTED HEALTH CARE SYSTEMS
PROVIDE CARE THAT ALIGNS WITH MEDICAL SCIENCE AND THE CITY'S
STATED VALUES. I WOULD ALSO NOTE RESPECTFULLY
THAT WHILE THIS BOARD HAS SHOWN CONSISTENT LEADERSHIP ON THIS
ISSUE, THERE IS PLENTY OF ROOM FOR STRONGER AND CLEARER
SUPPORT FROM THE MAYOR'S OFFICE .
I HOPE THIS RESOLUTION HELPS ENCOURAGE THAT ALIGNMENT.
THROUGH THIS ORGANIZING WE HAVE PROVEN THAT WHEN COMMUNITY
MEMBERS AND LEADERS SPEAK WITH ONE VOICE, HEALTH CARE SYSTEMS
CAN LISTEN. SO AGAIN THANK YOU TO
SUPERVISOR CHAN THE BOARD FOR STANDING UP FOR EVIDENCE BASED
CARE AND I LOOK FORWARD TO CELEBRATING WITH YOU ALL THE
PASSING OF THIS RESO NEXT WEEK. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER PLEASE. WELCOME.
HELLO. >> THANK YOU ALL FOR BEING
HERE. MY NAME IS CALISTA STONE
AND I'M A SENIOR AT THE BASE SCHOOL OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I CARE DEEPLY ABOUT THE ISSUE OF HOMELESSNESS GROWING UP
IN SAN FRANCISCO IN DISTRICT EIGHT.
I'VE SEEN IT ON NEARLY EVERY STREET CORNER AND IT SADDENS ME
THAT MORE THAN 8000 OF MY FELLOW SAN FRANCISCANS DON'T
HAVE A SAFE PLACE TO GO HOME AT NIGHT, PARTICULARLY ON COLD
AND RAINY NIGHT LIKE TONIGHT. SAN FRANCISCO HAS ONE OF THE
HIGHEST RATES OF HOMELESSNESS PER CAPITA OF ANY CITY IN THE
UNITED STATES AND IT'S THE RESPONSIBILITY OF LOCAL
GOVERNMENT TO CREATE EFFECTIVE PROGRAMS AND SAFE SHELTER
OPTIONS TO SUPPORT OUR FELLOW SAN FRANCISCANS.
>> CURRENTLY THERE'S A FOCUS ON RELOCATING UNHOUSED PEOPLE OUT
OF RESIDENTIAL AREAS OFTEN PRIORITIZING THE APPEARANCE OF
A CLEANER CITY OVER THE NEEDS OF THE MOST VULNERABLE MEMBERS
OF OUR SOCIETY. >> SO I WANTED TO COME HERE
TODAY AS A YOUNG PERSON AND AS A SAN FRANCISCAN TO URGE YOU
ALL TO CONTINUE WORKING TOWARDS NEW AND INNOVATIVE SOLUTIONS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS ERNIE JOHNSON. I REPRESENT RAINBOW FAMILIES
ACTION. A LARGE GROUP OF FAMILIES
AND ALLIES OF TRANSGENDER KIDS AND NON-BINARY KIDS.
I WANT TO FIRST THANK SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR BRINGING
THIS TO THE BOARD AND ALSO SUPERVISORS BENJAMIN FIELDER,
DORSEY CHEN AND WALTON FOR CO-SPONSORING.
THIS IS A LONG RESOLUTION AND IT'S A LONG RESOLUTION
BECAUSE THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT IS STRONG ONLY OBSESSED WITH MY
CHILDREN. IT SHOULD BE A SIMPLE QUESTION
. THE BIG QUESTION HERE IS CAN
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT CAN AN AUTHORITARIAN GOVERNMENT TELL
US HOW TO TAKE CARE OF OUR CHILDREN IN SAN FRANCISCO?
IN SAN FRANCISCO WE LIVE BY DIFFERENT VALUES AND THEY'RE
POWERFUL VALUES AND THEY'RE STRONG.
WE TAKE CARE OF OUR CHILDREN. WE TAKE CARE OF OUR LGBTQ
COMMUNITY AND I KNOW THAT THIS IS SOMETHING THAT ALL OF US
AGREE ON HERE AND THAT WE DON'T NEED ANYBODY FROM A TERRIBLE
GOVERNMENT TELLING US WHAT TO DO.
I WOULD SAY WITH THIS HEALTH CARE WE ARE ALWAYS ASKING
OURSELVES WHAT WHAT WHAT IS IT THAT WE WANT TO GIVE TO OUR
CHILDREN? WE ALL WANT THE ABILITY TO GIVE
OUR CHILDREN CARE OF ANY KIND THAT A DOCTOR SAYS THAT WE
SHOULD GET. DO WE WANT THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT GETTING BETWEEN US AND DOCTORS?
NO, WE DO NOT WANT THAT. SAN FRANCISCO HAS FOUGHT TOO
LONG AND TOO HARD FOR EVERYONE TO HAVE HEALTH CARE AND TO BE A
BASTION OF LGBTQ RIGHTS TO ALLOW A FEW CORPORATE LEADERS
TO DECIDE WHICH CHILDREN ARE THROWN OUT OF CARE.
THERE ARE HOSPITALS CONSIDERING THIS RIGHT NOW.
SO I ASK YOU ALL TO PLEASE PASS THIS RESOLUTION TO SEND A
STRONG MESSAGE TO ALL OF THE HEALTH CARE WORKERS AND ALL OF
THE PEOPLE THAT GET HEALTH CARE FROM SAN FRANCISCO BOTH AS
RESIDENTS AND EMPLOYEES THAT YOU SUPPORT THEIR KIDS AND YOU
SUPPORT THEM GETTING WHATEVER HEALTH CARE THEY NEED NO MATTER
WHAT THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT SAYS HOSPITALS HAVE TO PROVIDE
THIS CARE. IT IS THE LAW IN CALIFORNIA.
IT IS NO LAW THAT PREVENTS THEM FROM PROVIDING THIS CARE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ROSARIO CERVANTES AND I'M HERE ON AN ITEM NUMBER
AGENDA ITEM NUMBER 29 CONDEMNING ICE FOR LOSS OF LIFE
URGING ACCOUNTABILITY MEASURES AND CORRECTIVE ACTION TO
PREVENT FURTHER LOSS OF LIFE AND REAFFIRMING COMMITMENT TO
SANCTUARY CITY. WE LIVE IN THE LAND OF, YOU
KNOW, IMMIGRANTS AND WE ARE A SANCTUARY CITY AND I SUPPORT
THE SPONSORS, THANK THE SPONSORS CHEN WALTON FELDER,
MAHMOOD CHAN AND MELGEN AND URGE ALL TO VOTE YES ON IT.
AND I ALSO HEARD THE NEW BUSINESS SUPERVISOR CHEN
PROTECTING THE TRANSGENDER COMMUNITY.
SUPERVISOR CHEN ON THE KEEPING IMMIGRATION, YOU KNOW, OPEN
AFTER 2027 AND THEN MYRNA MELGAR INCREASED THE BUDGET
FOR, YOU KNOW, PUBLIC EDUCATION.
SO I HOPE YOU CAN SUPPORT THAT. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
HELLO. MY NAME IS LISA KING.
I AM AN ACTIVIST JUST A COMMUNITY MEMBER WHO'S REALLY
CONCERNED ABOUT ICE COMING TO OUR TOWN AND DOING WHAT HAS
HAPPENED IN MINNESOTA. I AM HERE TO SUPPORT THE NUMBER
29 THE CONDEMNING OF ICE AND LOSS OF LIFE
AND REAFFIRMING MY COMMITMENT TO SANCTUARY CITY.
APPRECIATE YOU FOR BRINGING THIS UP.
I ALSO WANTED TO MAKE A COMMENT ABOUT POINT NUMBER 31 AROUND
THE STATE ASSEMBLY BILL 1537 I THINK IT'S A HALF MEASURE.
I WOULD SUPPORT IT BUT I ALSO HEAR THAT SCOTT WIENER IS
INTRODUCING SOMETHING AROUND PROVIDING CIVIL RIGHTS
AND CIVIL ABILITY TO GO AFTER ICE FOR ANY LOSS OF LIFE
AND VIOLENCE THAT IS UNNECESSARY AND IF THAT ISN'T
PASSED IN THE STATE I WOULD LIKE TO SEE SOME SORT OF
RESOLUTION AND SOME SORT OF BILL PASSED HERE IN THE CITY OF
SAN FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU ALL.
APPRECIATE THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> LET US KNOW IF YOU NEED
ASSISTANCE GRABBING THAT MICROPHONE FOR YOU.
>> OH, YOU GOT IT. OKAY.
WELL, IT DOESN'T COUNT AS MY TIME.
OKAY. GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS CAROL BROWNSON. I'M A LONG TIME RESIDENT OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND I'M HERE TODAY TO TALK ABOUT PLANNING CODE
SOMETHING OR OTHER PERMITTED PARKING IN DRIVEWAYS A REPORT
THAT'S COMING TO YOU NEXT WEEK I UNDERSTAND.
>> AND WHEN WE ARRIVED IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD THERE WERE THREE
VICTORIANS SIDE BY SIDE MUCH OF THE SAME WITH FRONT GARDENS,
SMALL FRONT GARDENS. IT WAS ESSENCE OF SAN FRANCISCO
BUT MANY OF THOSE FRONT GARDEN TWO OF THE TWO OF THE THREE OF
THOSE FRONT GARDENS DISAPPEARED PRETTY QUICKLY AND WHAT WAS
LEFT WAS A TRACK WAY INTO WHAT WAS APPARENTLY A GARAGE THAT
WAS NOT PERMEABLE BY WATER. SO A LOT OF WATER WENT OUT INTO
THE SEWERS FROM THOSE TWO AND OF COURSE EXCUSE ME CUTS
IN THE CURB WHICH PRIVATIZED PUBLIC PARKING.
NOW I'M THERE ARE HERE SOME COMPLEX RULES THAT I HAVE TRIED
TO READ THAT WILL NEED TO BE ENFORCED IN ORDER TO ALLOW THIS
PARKING OF VEHICLES IN THE DRIVEWAY INTO WHAT IS
APPARENTLY A GARAGE. >> NOW ENFORCING THESE COMPLEX
RULES SHOULD BE INTERESTING. >> YOU KNOW THE STOP SIGNS,
VERY FEW DRIVERS ACTUALLY STOP AT THEM BUT THE RULES ARE VERY
CLEAR. >> THEY'RE VERY SIMPLE STOP.
BUT I DON'T SEE THEM BEING ENFORCED SO THOSE AREN'T
ENFORCED. >> BUT THIS IS ALL GOING TO BE
ENFORCED RIGHT? WELL, ONE OF THE THINGS THAT
ISN'T ENFORCED NOW IS THAT THE CARS THAT PARK IN THOSE
DRIVEWAYS TEND TO PARK MOSTLY ON THE SIDEWALK PAST TWO OF
THEM TRYING TO GET HERE TODAY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, MA'AM, FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> THANK YOU.
AND IF THAT OVERHEAD COULD BE USED HI MY NAME IS PAUL WORMER
AND I'M COMMENTING ON THE SAME ISSUE THAT DOESN'T REALLY SHOW
UP VERY WELL. IT SEEMS THAT DOES BETTER.
>> NOPE. OKAY.
>> SO WALKING DOWN HERE PAST ON ON BUCHANAN A BLOCK AND ON THAT
BLOCK THERE ARE TWO CARS PROJECTING OUT ON THE SIDEWALK.
THAT WAS A VERY UNUSUAL BLOCK BECAUSE THAT SIDEWALK IS WIDE
ENOUGH THAT CARROLL COULD GET BY THEM WITH NO PROBLEM.
IT'S A WIDE FLAT SIDEWALK. IT'S NOT SLOPED.
IT DOESN'T DROP OFF STEEPLY ON EITHER SIDE.
THAT'S UNUSUAL. IT'S NOT ENFORCED.
>> YESTERDAY I WAS WALKING SOMEWHERE AND WAS WATCHING AN
INTERESTING PLAY AT AN INTERSECTION TRAFFIC LIGHT
GARAGE CAR STOPPED AT THE INTERSECTION WAITING FOR
ANOTHER CAR TO COME OUT OF THE BACK OUT OF THE GARAGE.
MEANWHILE WITH THE LIGHTS CHANGING, TRAFFIC IS COMING.
CARS ARE GOING AROUND. CARS ARE COMING DOWN THE HILL
AND THIS IS ON A LOW RELATIVELY LOW TRAFFIC CROSS STREET WHERE
PEOPLE ARE RUSHING TO GET THROUGH THAT INTERSECTION.
WHEN YOU SET UP A SITUATION WHERE PEOPLE BACK OUT ONTO THE
STREET AND WAIT AND BLOCK TRAFFIC, YOU CREATE FRUSTRATED
DRIVERS. THAT'S A SAFETY HAZARD.
>> OH, IF YOU DO THAT ON STREETS WHERE THERE ARE BUS
LINES THAT DELAYS THE BUSSES THAT INCREASES THE OPERATING
COST FOR MUNI THAT MAKES PEOPLE FRUSTRATED WITH MUNI BECAUSE
THEY'RE DELAYED SO I UNDERSTAND THAT THIS LEGISLATION SOLVES
SOME VERY REAL PROBLEMS BUT ABSENT ENFORCEMENT AND ABSENT
OF THINKING ABOUT HOW THIS PLAYS IT AT CERTAIN
INTERSECTIONS IS MAKING THINGS WORSE FOR OTHER PEOPLE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU PAUL WARMER FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. WELCOME.
HELLO EVERYONE. MY NAME IS RICHARD SEGOVIA
AND I AM THE PROUD OWNER OF THE LATIN ROCK MURAL HOUSE ON 25TH
IN YORK. >> I WAS APPROACHED WITH A
BEAUTIFUL CERTIFICATE OF HONOR FROM THE SUPERVISORS FOR ALL
THE WORK AND EVERYTHING THAT I'VE DONE.
I HAVE PROCLAMATIONS FROM MERELY MAKING SEPTEMBER 17TH
WHICH IS SEGOVIA DAY. SO WHAT I LIKE TO SEE HAPPEN IS
TO MOVE FORWARD TO MAKE MY HOUSE A LANDMARK.
>> I AM ONE WHERE A LOT OF PEOPLE TODAY IT'S BEEN A REALLY
HARD DAY FOR ME. MY GOOD FRIEND MINGO LEWIS WHO
PLAYED CARLOS SANTANA HAD PASSED AWAY TODAY AND CHUEY
FROM KPFA RADIO I MEAN FROM XM RADIO CAME OVER THE HOUSE
AND YES, WE ARE GOING TO PUT TALK TO LOCAL ON MY HOUSE THIS
YEAR. I HAVE OVER 180 PEOPLE ON MY
HOME. YOU HAVE TO REMEMBER ONE THING.
LATIN ROCK MUSIC WAS CREATED IN SAN FRANCISCO'S MISSION
DISTRICT JUST LIKE MOTOWN AND DETROIT.
SO I FEEL THAT MY HOME SHOULD BE PROTECTED BY THE CITY
AND STATE. THEY GAVE ME THE FUNDING TO GET
THIS MURAL DONE. WE HAVE TO MAKE THIS PART OF
SAN FRANCISCO'S HISTORY. LATIN ROCK MUSIC IS IN MY
VEINS. I'VE BEEN A PROFESSIONAL
MUSICIAN FOR 37 YEARS. I PLAYED THE OPPORTUNITY TO SIT
IN WITH SANTANA TO PLAY WITH TO PLAY WITH EDDIE MONEY TO WORK
WITH THE DOOBIE BROTHERS AND SOME OF THE GREATEST
MUSICIANS LIKE GREGG ALLMAN ALL OVER THE WORLD.
SO I ASK YOU AND I PLEAD WITH YOU.
LET'S MAKE GUS VAN GOGH THE HOUSE OF LATIN ROCK.
AND BE PROUD TO BE A PART OF SAN FRANCISCO'S MISSION
HISTORY. MY MOTHER WAS BORN IN THE
MISSION DISTRICT IN 1919. SO I ASK YOU PLEASE AS I TALK
TO MISS FELDER ABOUT THIS, LET'S MAKE MY HOUSE A PART OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO'S HISTORY. I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR
TIME. >> GOD BLESS YOU AND TAKE CARE.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
CALL ME JACKIE. BYE BYE.
THE CITY BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND MAYOR OFFICE OF SAN
FRANCISCO. THE TITLE OF THIS IS AUDITION
AND CALL FOR A NATIONAL ANTHEM OF LADY GAGA.
>> TWO YEARS AGO WHILE WORKING IN THE FLORIDA SIX FLAGS I
MASTER AND ACCLIMATE THE PLATFORM TO SPEAK ON BEHALF TO
CEOS BUTTERFLIES, PENGUINS AND FINALLY THE BEAST DOLPHINS.
TODAY I TAKE FULL ADVANTAGE OF THE ACOUSTICS OF HIS CHAMBER TO
RECORD AUDITIONING CALL FOR THE NATIONAL ANTHEM AND SUBMIT IT
TO THE SAN FRANCISCO 49. I'M NOT GOING TO MAKE IT TO THE
SUPER BOWL BUT IT'S A PROCESS AND HOPEFULLY THE GUY WILL JOIN
ME ON STAGE AND ANYBODY THE PUBLIC OFFICE WILL JOIN ME
AND IT GOES LIKE THIS. OH SAY CAN'T YOU SEE BY THE
DAWN'S EARLY LIGHT WHAT SO PROUD WE HAIL.
>> AT THE TWILIGHT'S LAST GLEAMING WHOSE BROAD STRIPES
AND BRIGHT STAR FRUIT A PEARL IS HIGH ALERT THE RAMPARTS WE
WATCH WERE SO GALLANTLY SPEAK. >> AND THE ROCKET'S RED FLAG
THE BOMB BURSTING IN AIR GAVE PROOF ROOT AND I THAT OUR FLAG
WAS STILL THERE. I ALWAYS SAY THAT STAR SPANGLED
BANNER YET WERE OVER THE LAST AND AFTER FREE AND HOME OF THE
BRAVE. >> I HOPE TO SEE EVERYONE AT A
STADIUM. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
THE NEXT SPEAKER, PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARDS
SUPERVISOR ROGERS THANK YOU. I'M DOWN TO VICKERS BUSINESS
REP FOR LOCAL 1414 AND THE NATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF
MACHINISTS AND AEROSPACE WORKERS.
I'M SPEAKING ABOUT THE 78 BUDGET DEFICIT AND THE CHANGES
MANAGEMENT IS DISCUSSING TO WORK CONDITIONS AND BENEFITS.
WE RECOGNIZE THE BENEFITS IS REAL BUT BALANCING THE BUDGET
ON THE BACKS OF FRONT TO FRONTLINE WORKERS IS NOT THE
LONG TERM INTERESTS SAN FRANCISCO HAS OPENED TO THE
PUBLIC. FIRST OUR MEMBERS PROVIDED
ESSENTIAL SERVICE THROUGHOUT THE PANDEMIC OFTEN THE FEEL
AND ONSITE HELPING KEEP THE CITY RUNNING DURING A HISTORIC
PUBLIC HEALTH EMERGENCY. THOSE SACRIFICES AND THE RISK
TAKEN BY OUR MEMBERS AND THEIR FAMILIES HAVE NEVER BEEN
PROPERLY ACKNOWLEDGED. SECOND LOCAL 1414 PERFORMS
CRITICAL WORK WHEN THE MODES ARE UNAVAILABLE OR INADEQUATE.
WE SUPPORT THE SYSTEM WITH MAINTENANCE AND RELIABLE DIESEL
HYBRID SERVICE. WHEN ELECTRIFIED SERVICES
DISRUPTED WITH THE PETROL YARD PROJECT BEGINNING SOON DIESEL
HYBRID BUSSES WILL BE NEEDED TO COVER RIDES THAT CAN'T BE SENT
FROM PETROL. ONCE AGAIN OUR MEMBERS ARE
STEPPING UP TO KEEP THE CITY MOVING.
THIRD, WE UNDERSTAND MANAGEMENT IS CONSIDERING CUTTING EARLY
MORNING SHIFTS AS A COST SAVING MEASURE.
BUT MANY OF THOSE SHIFTS EXIST TO MEET REAL OPERATION NEEDS.
REMOVING THEM WILL REDUCE EFFICIENCY AND RELIABILITY
AND IT UNFAIRLY PLACES THIS POOR APPROPRIATE SHARE OF CUTS
ON OUR MEMBERS. WE URGE YOU PUSH FOR SOLUTIONS
THAT BALANCE PHYSICAL RESPONSIBILITY WITH SAFETY,
RELIABILITY AND RESPECT FOR THE WORKFORCE THAT KEEPS OUR SYSTEM
MOVING. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
IF YOU ARE HERE TO PROVIDE GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT PLEASE
COME ON AND OVER TO THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER.
OTHERWISE THIS MAY BE OUR LAST SPEAKER.
>> WELCOME SIR. SUPERVISORS MY NAME IS SCOTT
FEENEY, MY SERVICES CARE RESIDENT AND I'M HERE TO TALK
ABOUT HOUSING IN PARTICULARLY A VERY MISGUIDED OP ED THAT WAS
PUBLISHED TODAY BY U.C. BERKELEY PROFESSOR WHO
SUGGESTED THAT LOWERING SAN FRANCISCO'S REAL ESTATE
TRANSFER TAX WOULD INCREASE HOUSING PRODUCTION BUT THAT
TAXES ON SALES OF EXISTING HIGH VALUED PROPERTIES NOT ON
DEVELOPMENTS AND IT TOPS OUT AT ONLY 6% FOR THE HIGHEST VALUED
PROPERTIES OVER $25 MILLION. THAT'S LOWER THAN THE SALES TAX
THAT STUDENTS USED TEXTBOOKS. ANY IMPACT THAT WOULD HAVE ON
DEVELOPMENT IS A DROP IN THE BUCKET COMPARED TO WHAT'S
REALLY HOLDING HOUSING BACK WHICH IS HIGH INTEREST RATES,
HIGH MATERIALS COSTS AND GREATER RETURNS AVAILABLE
TO INVESTORS ELSEWHERE INCLUDING IN THE BOOM.
THOSE MACROECONOMIC REALITIES ARE NOT THINGS THAT WE'RE GOING
TO BE ABLE TO TAX CUT OUR WAY OUT OF.
AND IF WE'RE NOT THOUGHTFUL ABOUT THIS WE COULD END UP IN A
WORST OF BOTH WORLDS SITUATION WHERE WE NOT ONLY DON'T HAVE A
LOT OF PRIVATE HOUSING PRODUCTION BUT WE'VE ALSO
REMOVED THE REVENUE THAT WAS GOING TO FIND AFFORDABLE
HOUSING PRODUCTION INSTEAD OF CUTTING THE TRANSFER TAX.
THIS BOARD SHOULD WORK WITH THE MAYOR TO DEVOTE TRANSFER TAX
REVENUE TO ITS INTENDED PURPOSE OF BUILDING SOCIAL HOUSING.
20/20 PROPOSITION I WHICH RAISE THE TAX ON SALES OF HIGH VALUED
PROPERTIES WAS INTENDED TO FUND SOCIAL HOUSING BUT A LEGAL
LOOPHOLE ALLOWED FORMER MAYOR BREED TO IGNORE THAT
VOTER INTENT AND SPEND THE FUNDS AND OTHER PURPOSES
INSTEAD OF BUILDING BADLY NEEDED AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
THE BOARD CAN NOW WORK WITH THE MAYOR TO CORRECT THIS MISTAKE.
DIRECT PUBLIC INVESTMENT IN SOCIAL HOUSING WE'LL GET
CONSTRUCTION MOVING AGAIN AND BUILD HOMES AFFORDABLE TO
SAN FRANCISCANS AT ALL INCOME LEVELS.
IF WE WANT TO SEE CRANES ON THE SKYLINE AND ULTIMATELY A MORE
AFFORDABLE CITY PROPOSITION I AND THE TRANSFER TAX CAN BE
PART OF THE SOLUTION NOT THE PROBLEM.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ARE THERE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT? >> MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE. AGENDA ITEMS 29 THROUGH 58 ITEM
20 NINE THROUGH 58 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION BUT
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE. A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY.
ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST
APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN.
>> THANK. THANK YOU BOB.
>> I WOULD LIKE TO SERVER NUMBER 20 NINE.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON. THANK YOU.
PLEASE SEND ITEMS 32 TO 58 TO COMMITTEE.
>> RIGHT. >> ALL RIGHT.
MADAM CLERK ON THE WOULD BE ITEMS 30 AND 31.
>> COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 30 AND 31.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON MOLTEN IRON
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN II MANDEL I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
AND SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 29 ITEM 20 NINE RESOLUTION TO
CONDEMN IMMIGRATION AND CUSTOMS ENFORCEMENT ICE FOR ACTIONS
THAT HAVE LED TO THE LOSS OF LIFE.
URGING STATE AND FEDERAL PARTNERS TO CALL FOR THIRD
PARTY INVESTIGATION ON ALL DEATHS THAT HAVE OCCURRED AS A
RESULT OF ACTIONS TAKEN BY ICE OFFICERS.
CALLING FOR A MORATORIUM ON ICE DETENTION UNTIL A THIRD PARTY
INVESTIGATION COULD BE CONDUCTED AND CORRECTIVE ACTION
BE IMPLEMENTED. AND TO AFFIRM SAN FRANCISCO'S
COMMITMENT TO UPHOLDING SANCTUARY CITY POLICIES.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN, THANK YOU PRESENT GENTLEMEN.
>> SINCE INTRODUCTION OF THIS RESOLUTION ICE HAS ESCALATED TO
TEAR ITS INFLICT ON COMMUNITIES AROUND THE COUNTRY.
IN 2026 ICE HAS ALREADY KILLED NINE PEOPLE.
IF THIS TREND CONTINUES WE WILL QUICKLY OUTPACE LAST YEAR.
EACH AND EVERY ONE OF THESE PEOPLE DESERVE JUSTICE.
AS AN ELECTED OFFICIAL, A COMMUNITY MEMBER AND A MARTYR,
I AM ABSOLUTELY HORRIFIED BY WHAT IS HAPPENING FROM THE
SHOOTING OF ALICE PETTY TO UNLAWFUL SEARCH AND SEIZURE AT
PEOPLE'S HOME TO DETAINMENT OF A FIVE YEAR OLD BOY.
I HAVE NO WORDS. I WANT TO BE I WANT TO BE
EXPLICITLY CLEAR. OUR CHILDREN ARE NOT BE OUR
CIVILIANS ARE NOT TARGETS. >> OUR COMMUNITIES WILL NOT BE
TORN APART. >> NONE OF US ARE SAFE UNTIL
ALL OF US ARE SAFE. AND I LOOK FORWARD TO HAVING
YOUR SUPPORT ON THIS RESOLUTION SO WE CAN CONTINUE TO SEND A
CLEAR MESSAGE ABOUT WHERE OUR CITY STANDS.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE
AGENDA ITEMS? >> THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT.
WOULD YOU PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM?
>> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE
FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS. ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR MILKER
FOR THE LATE MR. JOSE BERNARDO COYER AND THAT OKAY ON BEHALF
OF SUPERVISOR CHERYL FOR THE LATE MS..
CHU CHANG YOW HOON ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR THE LATE
MS. RUTH VERLIN DAVIS ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN AND ON
BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WAS AT THE
PRESIDENT'S REQUEST FOR MR. ALEX JEFFREY PRETI ALL RIGHT.
>> I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA, MADAM
CLERK. >> DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER
BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK WE ARE
ADJOURNED